[MUSIC PLAYING]
CARTER ZENKE: Well hello,
one and all, and welcome
back to CS50 Introduction
to Databases with SQL.
My name is Carter Zenke,
and today we'll focus
on optimizing-- trying to
reduce the time our queries take
as well as reducing the storage
space our database might use.
We'll also see how to
handle concurrency.
That is, many queries all at once.
Now we'll do all of this in
the context of a new database,
this one-- the Internet Movies
Database, or IMDb for short.
If you've been to imdb.com you may have
seen this whole big database of movies,
and we've compiled that into our very
own SQLite database for us today.
Now this database is big.
It is much bigger than
anything we've seen so far.
In fact, it has over 200,000 movie
ratings, over 400,000 movies,
and 1.4 million stars or people
who have acted in some movie.
And the goal of this database is to
represent movies, the people in them,
and the average ratings
for each of those movies.
Now we have ourselves an
entity relationship diagram
to describe this database,
and it looks a bit like this.
We have people in one
table, movies in another,
and ratings in a
separate table down here.
Notice that people have
a name and a birthday
along with an ID, the
primary key for that table.
Movies too have a title and
the year they were released
as well as their own
primary key ID here.
Rating down here has the
average rating for a given movie
as well as the number of votes
that went into calculating
that average rating here.
And notice too that the movie and people
table has a many-to-many relationship.
That is, a person can star
in more than one movie
in the same way a movie
can have multiple stars.
So if we want to implement
this many-to-many relationship,
we've seen one way to do that.
Let me actually ask
the audience here, how
have we implemented a many-to-many
relationship historically?
What kind of tables do we
need for this, do you think?
All right.
So not to worry if you don't have an
idea of what we're going to use here.
Let's take a peek at what
tables we can actually use.
So here as we've seen historically we
might have two tables, one for people
and one for movies.
And notice here in the
people table we have names
along with a primary key called ID.
And similarly in our movies
table, we also have a title
column along with a movies own
primary key, an ID column over there.
Now to implement the relationship
between people and movies,
we have to have some table
in the middle of these two.
One that relates people IDs
or person IDs with movie IDs.
And if we look at this
table, I could see
that if I see person ID next
to some given movie ID, well
it means that the person
with this ID has starred in,
played a role in, this movie here.
We see person 158--
let's see, Tom Hanks-- was in the
movie ID with 114709, or Toy Story
as we see in the movies table.
And now knowing this, how
can we figure out which
movies Kristen Bell has starred in?
If we know of Kristen
Bell's ID, what should we
then do to find the movies
Kristen Bell has starred in?
AUDIENCE: You could select the ID of
the people then look into the stars
table, then look at
[INAUDIBLE] the movies table.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
I like your thinking.
So there's multiple steps here.
We have to go through each table to
find ultimately the movie that Kristen
Bell has starred in.
The first step might be to
ask, what is Kristen Bell's ID?
Well it seems to be 68338.
Then, to your point, we
could look at the stars table
and find out what movie IDs
correspond to that ID here.
So it seems like 2294629 corresponds
with Kristen Bell's ID here.
Then finally we look up
in the movies table, well,
what title corresponds with 2294629?
It seems to be the movie Frozen.
So visually, we have this
relationship among these tables here.
So let's now dive into
our movies database
to actually get a sense of
what data is inside of this.
And for that I'll go back to my
computer so we can open this database up
in SQLite.
I'll come back over here and
I'll open up my own environment
where I can type sqlite3 movies.db.
movies.db.
And now if I zoom in just a bit, I
can then type .schema to show you all
the tables that exist in this database.
I see up top I do have a movies table
that has a primary key called ID,
a column called title
and a column called year.
I have that same people table
with names and birthdays,
and I also have this stars table that
corresponds with person IDs and movie
IDs, relating in this
case people and movies.
OK, so let's try selecting
then from our movies table
to see what movies we have,
take a peek at our data.
Well, we saw a little
bit ago, we could try
to take a peek at our data
using a certain SQL keyword.
I could SELECT * from "movies"
to see all columns from movies,
but if I have let's say
400,000 rows I don't
want to print all those to the screen.
So what could I use instead?
A certain SQL keyword.
I'm hearing LIMIT, so let's try that.
I'll say LIMIT 5.
I only want the first five results here.
I'll hit Enter, and here I'll see those
first five movies in my movies table.
They each have their own
unique ID, a primary key.
They have a title and the
year that they were published.
But if you've been to
imdb.com, you may have wanted
to search for a particular movie.
Maybe you wanted to find your favorite
movie among all the possible movies
in their database.
And we can simulate that kind of
query by querying the database here.
Whenever you type in IMDd's browser--
that's like the search for a movie
called Frozen, for example--
odds are that behind the
scenes a database is actually
running that same query
to return to you what
movies have that title called Frozen.
Now for me my favorite
movie since I was a kid
is one called Cars, so let me
try to search for Cars here.
I'll try to find SELECT * from
"movies" where the "title" = 'Cars'.
And you could imagine me going to
IMDb, typing in Cars in the search bar,
and behind the scenes
this SQL query gets
run to find what movies
have the title Cars.
So let me hit Enter here, and now I'll
see that one movie has that title Cars.
Came out in 2006 and the ID is 317219.
But this is a lecture on
optimizing, so it's worth
asking how much time did it
take for this query to run?
Let's find out.
Well I can use a SQLite
command here called timer.
I'll say .timer on to make sure
that I time my future queries.
I'll hit Enter now.
And now if I try selecting again,
I'll hit the up arrow twice
to get back my old query.
I can type Enter and I'll
see not just the results
but the time it took to run that query.
Now notice, we have several
different measures of time here.
I have the quote, unquote "real
time" which is essentially
the stopwatch time, meaning from the
time I press Enter to the time I saw
these results, how long did that take?
But of course you're
familiar with computers.
You know there's more involved
than just this query running.
I also have to wait for
the operating system
to finish other processes as well.
That's where user and
system time come in.
User time is how much time this
query particularly took on the CPU.
System time is how long I spent
waiting around for other processes
to finish before I could run this query.
For us, we'll focus on real time.
What was the wall clock time,
the stopwatch time, so to speak,
between the time I pressed Enter
and the time I saw these results.
OK.
So here we have a query
taking 0.084 seconds.
I mean, that is pretty good.
If I only wait around for less than a
tenth of a second, I'm not complaining.
But if I'm an engineer
at IMDb, why might I
be concerned about a query that
takes 0.084 seconds, particularly
if I have lots and lots of users?
What's the problem there?
AUDIENCE: For users, the database
might be overwhelmed by the queries.
And you should also consider how
much time the application takes
to form the query to the database too.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So the basic idea here
is that when I have
a single query that takes maybe less
than tenth of a second, that's fine.
But if I have many, many users
running those queries all at once,
that time is going to add up.
And so if I'm an engineer
or even somebody in finance,
I want to reduce that time because
I'm paying per second that I
run this database on some other server.
So we can optimize these
queries, but let's first
get a sense of how
they're presently running.
What is SQLite doing underneath the
hood to find this movie called Cars?
Well for that, I'll bring up a certain
visual here of our titles column.
So imagine here that we have a
smaller database called Movies
that just has titles in this case.
And now I want to search these
titles, but I'm a computer.
I'm not a human.
Meaning I can only look
at one item at a time.
I can only look at one
row and check its title.
Now if I want to find the row or
the rows that have Cars in them,
what's the best I could do
if my titles are not sorted?
What's the best approach
I could take here?
If I can only look at one row at a
time, how might I search this column?
AUDIENCE: You should use a
linear search then, right?
CARTER ZENKE: So I like your intuition.
There is an algorithm,
a step-by-step process
called linear search where
we look at one element
at a time or, in this
case one row at a time.
That's exactly what we
can do for this table.
I can look at one row at a time to
find is this title in this column
or is it not?
So here to visualize, I
could take this title column.
I can only look at one at a time.
But if this data is not sorted, I can
do no better than looking at every row
exactly once.
So here we start with Toy Story.
We ask, is Toy Story equal to Cars?
It's not, so we'll keep going.
Here I'll check Cars 3.
Is Cars 3 strictly equal to Cars?
It has Cars in it, but
it's not Cars exactly.
So I'll keep going.
I'll look at Frozen.
And Frozen is not Cars either, so I'll
keep going again and here I see Cars.
So maybe I could stop here.
But why couldn't I?
Well if I need to find not just the
one row that has Cars but all the rows
that have Cars, I have to keep going to
see is Cars elsewhere in this column?
Is it not just here, but
also in other rows too?
So I'll keep going.
I'll look at WALL-E,
Ratatouille, Soul, Turning Red
until I get to the end of this column.
And this process is called
a scan of the table.
We're scanning our column top
to bottom looking for the result
that we need to find.
But it turns out we can
actually optimize this search.
We can do a bit better than
going one by one by one by one,
and for this we need a
bit of a metaphor to think
about how we can search our table.
So if you have ever
seen a kind of textbook,
you might have seen something
a bit like this here.
This is a Handbook of
Education Research.
And maybe I want to find
which pages correspond
to how students learn computer science.
So one thing I could do is
open to the start of the book.
I could go page by page looking
for which pages have "how students
learn computer science."
I keep going here, and if I want
to find all the pages that have
"how students learn
computer science" on them,
I can do no better than
going through every one
by one by one until I'm at
the end of this textbook.
But chances are you
yourself don't do this.
You do something better.
And there's some built-in
structure in this book that could
help you find what you're looking for.
What might you use to find something
in a textbook or some other book too?
AUDIENCE: We can use
the index of the book.
CARTER ZENKE: You can use the index.
So often a book like a
textbook has something
at the very back of
the book that tells me
all the subjects that are inside
this book, but in alphabetical order.
So I can see here there is a subject
index in the back of the book
here that lists the subjects
in alphabetical order, A to Z.
And if I want to find "how
students learn computer science,"
I could perhaps search for
computer science in this index.
I could find A, B, C. There's C,
and here I see computer science.
Now I know all the pages I need
to look at inside this book
without going through each
of them one by one by one.
So in the same way that
books have an index, so too
can databases and tables
have an index as well.
So let's see a definition
here for what an index is.
Well an index is a
structure that we can use.
It's built into our
database to help us speed up
the retrieval of rows from that table.
I first search my index, find out
what rows my given search term is in,
and then look those rows up in my table.
Now if I want to create an index on
a table, I can use some SQL syntax.
I can say "create index"
and give it some name.
But I need to also specify
a few other things.
Similar to my books index,
that index has some content.
It's an index by subject
or an index by author.
So I need to tell this
index what to include.
So I should also say create index,
give it a name on some table
and some columns in that table,
telling my index what data for my table
it should include.
So let's create our very own
index in the movies table
to identify how we can make this
query just a bit faster overall.
So I'll come back to my computer here,
and let's now try to create this index.
I will open up a new tab here.
A new tab.
And then I'll log back into my database.
I'll say sqlite3 movies.db.
And now I want to first
create some index here.
So I'll turn my timer back on and now
I'll type the syntax we just learned.
I want to create an index.
And if I'm searching my
title column in Movies,
I should probably include the
Title column in this index.
So I'll say call this
the "title_index" here.
It'll be on the Movies table and
it'll contain the data in the Title
column of Movies a bit like this.
Now I'll hit Enter and I'll see this
index took some time to be created.
There's some stuff going
on underneath the hood
where I'm putting this data in a new
structure we're calling the index here.
But now if I rerun this query,
if I say SELECT * FROM "movies,"
SELECT * from "movies" where
the "title" = 'Cars' semicolon,
it was a lot faster.
Here I see 0.01 seconds real
time compared to 0.084 seconds.
That's a savings of almost eight times.
Almost eight times faster
now that we have this index.
Now it took some time
to create the index.
If I run just a few
queries, I much easily
make that time up in
terms of the time I'm
using on my server to look up these
kinds of pieces of information.
OK, so let's actually take a
look at how we can ensure a query
is using some index.
Here I'm just kind of
taking it on my word.
Here it was faster,
so it used the index.
But there is a way for you to
know whether an index was used.
I could use a SQL statement
called EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN.
Other DBMSs might call
this just simply EXPLAIN,
but in SQLite it's EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN.
And then after EXPLAIN QUERY
PLAN, I can type the query
that I want to learn the plan for.
That is, how does SQLite plan
to find me this information?
How does it plan to execute this query?
So now I'll type SELECT * FROM
"movies" WHERE "title" = 'Cars'
like this, semicolon.
I'll hit Enter.
And now I don't get
the results, but I do
get the plan SQLite intends
to use to find me this result.
And take a look here.
I see QUERY PLAN, and underneath
I see what SQLite intends to do.
It will search the movies
table, but it will do so
using the index that
we called title_index.
And it will do so given
some value for title here.
So we can actually see SQLite
does plan to use the index
to speed up this query.
We can confirm that this is
exactly what's happening.
But let me try now to
remove this index and see
what SQLite would have done
when we didn't have this index.
I'll come back over here and I'll
go back to my other connection
to my database.
This one over here.
And now I'll remove the
index we just created.
To remove an index I can drop it.
I can say DROP INDEX
"title_index" semicolon.
And now that took just
some amount of time,
but now I don't have the index anymore.
I can type .schema, and I'll see
that index is not part of my schema.
But now if I try EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN
SELECT * from "movies" WHERE "title"
= 'Cars' semicolon, I'll see that
the plan is not to use the index.
The plan is to scan movies,
where scan, we saw before,
means to go top to bottom
through that title column
and find me all the rows
that have Cars in them.
So you can see here the
optimization we're already
making by using this index here.
OK, so let's take a
moment here and pause.
What questions do we have about indexes
and how they're used in this case?
AUDIENCE: Doesn't databases have
implicit algorithms to optimize search?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
Do databases have implicit
algorithms to optimize search?
They do for some columns.
So if we saw in our table earlier,
we had a primary key column like ID.
In SQLite and most other DBMSs, if I
specify that a column is a primary key
then that database management
system will automatically
create an index via which I
can search for a primary key.
If though I have a regular old column
like title or like year or so on,
it doesn't go through the process
of automatically optimizing
that search for me.
I have to try to do that
myself as we're doing here.
Let's take one more.
AUDIENCE: Would it be advisable
to create a different index
for every column in case we need it?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I mean it
seems like indexes are so good.
They speed up queries for us.
Why not create an index
on every column we have?
Well as we'll see in
just a moment, there
are some trade-offs involving space
and also the time it later takes
us to insert or add new data.
So good questions.
I'll come back to my laptop
where we can continue on.
So we've seen how indexes
can speed up queries.
We're searching for one column
here, but they could also speed up
queries across multiple tables.
So let's try a different
kind of query here.
What I might do now is try
to find all of those movies
that Tom Hanks starred in.
And we did a bit of a example of
this a little earlier visually,
but my goal is to find all of those
titles that Tom Hanks played a role in.
Well if my goal is to end
up with titles of movies,
I could try selecting "title" from
the "movies" column like this.
But if I look at that
movie's table, oh no, I only
have titles, year, and
the ID of those movies.
I don't have anything
related to Tom Hanks.
Well Tom Hanks though is probably
showing up in the stars table
where I could correspond Tom
Hanks's ID with the movie IDs
that Tom Hanks played a role in.
So let me try filtering
these movies by an ID.
I'll say WHERE the "id" of that
movie is IN some list of movie IDs
that also correspond with
Tom Hanks's person ID.
So I'll make a subquery here
to find exactly those films.
Now I'll say SELECT "movie_id"
FROM "stars" where the "person _id"
is equal to--
well I don't know Tom Hanks's person ID.
I could try to hard-code it
here, but I could do better
by having another subquery to
find what is Tom Hanks's ID?
Now I'll indent not just
four times but eight
to show this is my next
level of a subquery here.
I'll now SELECT "id" FROM "people"
WHERE the "name" = 'Tom Hanks'.
'Tom Hanks' like this.
And now I can close out my subqueries.
I've found the ID of Tom Hanks,
I've found those movie IDs that
correspond with the
person ID of Tom Hanks,
and then I've found the titles
that correspond to those movie IDs.
Now I'll hit a semicolon here,
press Enter, and I should see--
I get back all of Tom Hanks's movies,
all of those that he played a role in.
And I'll also see the time that it took.
The real time for this query
was about 0.197 seconds.
So getting a little bit slower now that
we're looking across multiple tables
and having multiple subqueries.
One index could speed this up as well.
I can make a new terminal here.
Let me open up the connection
to my database again.
I'll say sqlite3 movies.db.
And now I should figure
out what columns do
I need to index to speed up this query?
Well one thing I could do is
try EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN again.
I want to understand what SQLite
plans to do to execute this query.
So I'll EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN and I'll
type in the same query from before.
I'll say SELECT the
"title" FROM "movies" WHERE
the "id" is IN those movies
that Tom Hanks played a role in.
So I'll SELECT in this case movie_id
from the "stars" table where
the person_id equals Tom Hanks's ID.
Now I'll find that.
I'll indent eight times to show
this is my next level subquery.
I'll SELECT "id" from
"people" WHERE "name"
= 'Tom Hanks' and I'll wrap
the line just a little bit.
Let me zoom out so you
can see it all in one go.
And now I'll close out these
subqueries just like this, hit Enter,
and I should see if I zoom back in the
plan SQLite intends to use to find me
the results of this query.
Now let's take a look here.
I'm planning to first scan people.
To understand the
structure of this I need
to first go all the way in
to this bottom part here.
I'm going to scan people to
find presumably Tom Hanks's ID.
Then after I do that, I'm
going to scan stars presumably
to find all the movie IDs
that have Tom Hanks's ID.
But then up here I'm finally
going to search movies
using integer primary key.
Some index is automatically
created for me
as we saw before for my primary keys.
So it seems like the optimization
here could be in the people
table and the stars table.
Now let me ask, if I wanted to
create an index on either the people
table or the stars table, what
do you think I should include?
Which column should I include in
this index given my query here?
What column should I include in this
index given this previous query?
AUDIENCE: We could index the
ID and the name of the person?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good idea.
Index the ID and the name of the person.
So if we look at this query again
we'll see that our WHERE clause here
is searching by the name
in the people table,
and up here this WHERE clause
is searching by the person ID
column in our stars table.
So it would stand to reason
that I should actually
create an index that includes
the name column in people
and the person ID column in stars.
Perhaps two separate indexes.
One for each year.
So let's go ahead and create those now.
I'll come back to my computer and
here I will try to create this index.
I'll say first create an index.
CREATE INDEX called "person_index."
And I'll create it on stars and
the person ID column in stars
as we just discussed.
Now if I hit Enter I should let it
take some time to build up this index,
but now I can also create my next one.
I'll say CREATE INDEX, and then I'll
choose "name_index" on people table.
And I'll include the name column here.
So now I'll hit Enter.
That too will take some
time to run, but now
if I try to explain
the query plan again--
I'll clear my screen, try EXPLAIN QUERY
PLAN, and then I'll type in this query
again.
I'll say SELECT "title" FROM movies
WHERE the "id" is IN those movies
that Tom Hanks played a role in
that have the person ID next to it.
Then I'll say which is Tom Hanks's ID?
And I'll close out the
subquery here just like this.
And now if I explain
the plan yet again, I
should see I'm now optimizing
this query even further.
I can see down below here, my plan
is to search the people table.
Not to scan it, but to
search it using what we call
a covering index called "name_index."
The one we just created.
We'll explain covering
index in just a little bit.
Next though, I'm going
to search stars using
the index we just created called
"name_index" given some person ID.
And then finally, I'll
search movies using
an integer primary key
index, the one that's
automatically created for me here.
So here we see some new vocabulary.
Not just using index, but
using a covering index.
Well, what is a covering index?
A covering index, it turns
out, is still an index.
It's the same kind of
idea, but it is one
in which we have all the data
we need inside the index itself.
It's one in which the query data can
be found only by searching the index.
There's no need for me to go
from the index to the table.
I can just look it up in the index.
It's similar to me searching this
textbook and getting to the index
and not then needing to actually
go back in the book's pages.
I can find everything I'm
looking for in the index itself.
And this is good because if I need to
not just find the items in my index
but then look them up in my table, that
look up in the table takes some time.
So if I instead have
a covering index, one
that includes all data I want to
find exactly right there in it,
that's going to be faster for
me than a regular old index.
So let's try then turning one
more index into a covering index.
I'll come back over here.
And we saw before that we
had the index on the stars
table using just a regular old index.
Using index person index.
But what are we trying
to find from this index?
We're trying to find
the movie ID column.
So I could create an index that
includes the movie ID column as well.
I can have indexes that
span multiple columns.
So let's try that here.
I'll come back over and
I'll create this new index
that intends to cover our search here.
I want to include not just the person
ID column but also the movie ID
column so I can quickly find that
data inside the index itself.
Let me drop our current implementation
of the person index like this.
And I'll hit semicolon here,
and now that index is gone.
But if I type now
CREATE INDEX, I'll also
call this "person_index" ON "stars."
and I'll say let's include
not just the person ID column.
Let's also include in this case,
the movie ID column like this.
Now I'll hit semicolon, Enter.
And it'll take a bit of
time to run, but once it's
done I can probably try to explain
the query plan again and see
if we have our covering index.
I'll go back up top here,
I'll EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN,
and I'll choose to recreate this
query from before just like this.
I'm going to select the "movie_id" FROM
"stars" and then find Tom Hanks's ID
and then close out these
subqueries here just like this.
And now once I EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN,
we've optimized even further.
Now I have two covering indexes.
I can find all the information I need
just by looking in these indexes,
not by doing a table lookup.
So let's now run this query and see
just how much faster it might be.
I'll come back to my laptop here, and
let's get rid of EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN.
Let's now turn our timer on.
I'll turn the timer on like
this and I'll rerun this query.
I'll say we select title from movies
where the ID is in the stars table
so long as the movie ID
aligns with the person ID.
Then I'll find Tom Hanks's person ID
here, I'll close out my subqueries,
and I should be able to find that
this query is just a little bit--
this is an understatement here.
A lot faster.
So if I go back to my old query here,
I'll see this one took 0.197 seconds.
This one with two covering
indexes takes 0.004 seconds.
This is an order of magnitude
faster than my prior query
because I've used indexes now.
So, let's see.
If we have all these benefits of
indexes, we must be paying something.
If I have this book here and I'm
trying to find some data inside of it,
what might the trade-offs be
if I want to create an index?
Let me think first about
this database on my computer.
What am I giving up?
If I'm making sure my query is faster,
what am I losing, do you think?
AUDIENCE: Space will
require for indexing also.
The more index we would have,
the more space and more memory
we would have to consume for that.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So it's a general theme
that when I try to speed up
something in computer science,
I have to pay some cost which
is often in terms of space.
That when I create an index I'm
using more space in my database.
And this similarly applies
to an old fashioned textbook.
If I have an index in
here, I'm literally
paying in pages to print so
people can find content better.
This is some extra
money I have to spend,
extra pages I have to print in
order to make my queries faster,
either on this book or in my database.
So let's understand why
indexes take up so much space
by looking at the underlying
data structure they
use to store information.
Well it turns out that the
part of the reason indexes
take up so much space is because
they use a certain data structure,
a way of organizing data called a
B-Tree, or a balanced tree structure.
So not to worry if you don't
know what a tree structure is.
Here's a visual to keep in mind as you
think about using trees in computer
science and in indexes in particular.
A tree might look a bit like this.
And notice how it's similar to
a family tree with grandparents
and parents and children and so on.
You could if you wanted to kind
of do a 180 on this diagram.
Flip it right side up
and now you might see
more of a tree structure
going from top to bottom.
You can see down here what might
call the trunk of the tree followed
by some branches-- these over here.
And then the leaves.
These up top kind of the
edge of this tree diagram.
And there's a few
vocabulary words you might
want to know when you talk about trees.
One of them is this idea of a node.
So this right here is a
single node in our tree.
A tree is made up of a collection
of nodes, and each of these nodes
stores some value.
Maybe it's a value in the column
we're trying to index, for example.
But in addition to that
value, this node also
stores pointers, kind of arrows
metaphorically, to other nodes
to tell us where in
memory these nodes are.
And by stringing these
nodes together, we
can build up this tree-like structure.
Now this node here points
to three other nodes.
And some new vocabulary here is
that this node has three children.
Going back to that
family tree example, we
see that this node here has three
children which are these right here.
But these nodes themselves also
have three children of their own.
So if I were to go down to
the next level of our tree--
well if I'm referring to this
node here, these nodes down below
are that node's grandchildren.
The children of its children.
Now these nodes here
also have another name.
We saw before they're
often called leaf nodes.
They're the edge of our tree.
And we know a node is a leaf node when
there are no other nodes it points to.
So this is the general idea
of what an index looks like.
But let's get a little
more concrete and try
to build an index from our title
column in our movies table here.
So let's assume we have a
table of IDs and titles here,
and I want to create an
index on this title column
to search it more efficiently.
Well we saw before that the best I
can do when this data is unsorted
is to go top to bottom.
First look at Toy Story,
then look at Cars 3,
then look at Frozen, all
the way down to the bottom.
I can only scan this
column, so to speak.
But I know I could probably do a
little better if the data is sorted.
If the data is sorted I could
look roughly in the middle,
and if I've gone too far,
go back a little bit.
Or if I haven't gone far
enough, go forward a little bit
and do a fewer number of lookups
to find data I'm looking for.
So let me sort this title column.
I'll put it like this.
What have I done wrong?
First I had this, then I
wanted to sort my title
column to make it faster to search.
But what rule did I break here by
sorting this title column like that?
AUDIENCE: Yes, Carter, the thing
is that by sorting only the movie's
name and not the ID you will break
the entire other databases that
relates to that one.
So for example, let's look for
a movie in which, I don't know,
Johnny Depp is working or has worked on.
And the result may be,
I don't know, Titanic.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I love that example.
That really drives it home here.
And in more general terms, I
had this primary key called ID.
And in the prior state I had
Toy Story with the ID of 114709.
A primary key means that Toy Story
should be consistently identified
with this number, 114709.
But to your point, Mateo, if
I sort only the title column,
well now Cars has that ID--
114709.
I've broken that
relationship, particularly
if other tables are relying on Toy
Story being identified by 114709.
So I can't do this.
This is bad.
I need some other way
to sort my title column.
So let's bring this back
to what it was here.
Let me focus just on the title column.
Well I can't sort this title column
because it's part of my table
and the ordering of
that table does matter.
What I could do though is
create a copy of this column
and maybe sort that copy.
So I'll literally create a copy of
this title column elsewhere in memory.
And let me just remove this
title column identifier here
so I have just the data.
Just the data in this column
somewhere else in memory.
And now I could sort
this data like this.
So let's say I now want to find Cars.
Well now that my data is
sorted, what could I do?
I could look first in the middle--
at Ratatouille for instance--
and then realize, well Cars
comes before Ratatouille.
Maybe I'll go a little
higher in my index here.
I'll search in the middle
of this first half.
I'll look at, in this case, Frozen.
And Cars-- well it still
comes before Frozen,
so let me look up at the
first half of this first half.
I'll then go up here and
I'll have spotted Cars.
So a much faster way to search for
information now once I have it sorted.
But I don't think we're quite there yet.
If I wanted to find the
year that Cars was released,
I found that it's in my title column but
what am I not able to do at this point?
I've copied the data
somewhere else, but now I
want to find some
other data in my table.
What can't I do?
AUDIENCE: We need to point to index.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
I need to be able to
find some way to relate
this index with the rows in my table.
So here this is elsewhere in memory.
It's good that I can find that
Cars is in my title column.
But if I want to find the other
data in this row like the year
that Cars was released,
well I have to have
some way of linking this
data here, Cars, to my table.
So often in an index, we won't just
copy the data to some new location
and sort it.
We'll also have some link between
these indexed pieces of data over here
and our rows and our table back here.
So for instance here is Cars,
and Cars appears to be in row 4.
Similarly Cars 3 looks to
be in row 2 in my table.
And I could metaphorically visually
draw some lines between Cars over here
in my index and Cars in my table.
I could draw one that looks a bit
like this going from Cars in my index
to actually Cars in my table.
I could draw one for Cars 3
going from this index place
here to row 2 in my title column.
So that is the way I can link
my index with my table data.
I could do the rest of these too for all
of my other pieces of data in my index.
So let's focus on this now just
to check for understanding.
I have this index.
That index has my sorted
title data and also
the row number in which I
found that piece of data.
So let's say here I want
to find the movie Soul.
I want to find the movie Soul.
How could I find Soul in my index?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, since
it is already sorted
I believe you could use binary search.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
I could use algorithm called binary
search, which if you're not familiar
simply means start in the
middle and if I've gone too far,
look at either the left
half or the right half
and repeat that process over and over.
So here is my index again.
I'll go roughly to the middle and
I'll look at Ratatouille here.
Well Soul, I know, comes after
Ratatouille alphabetically,
so what should I do?
I should now look in
this second half here.
I might go to Toy Story.
Once I see Toy Story, I know
I've gone a little bit too far.
Soul comes before Toy
Story alphabetically,
so I'll look in the first
half of this second half.
And what do I see?
I see Soul right there.
OK.
So our index seems to be working.
It allows me to more
efficiently find data.
I no longer have to look
through every single row.
I can simply use a more efficient
algorithm like binary search.
But now there's one more catch which
is, if I had many, many, many rows--
not just nine but literally thousands
or hundreds of thousands or millions
of rows in this index, that's a lot of
data to store in one location in memory
or even to load into my
computer's RAM, so to speak--
its random access memory--
so it can do all this jumping around.
Ideally what I would do is break
this index up into smaller pieces
so I don't have to load
all of this at once.
And in reality our index is
not a single column like this,
but often individual nodes
where each of these--
1, 2, 3-- might be some node
scattered about the computer's memory.
But what problem have I introduced now?
If these are around
the computer's memory,
I can't actually jump
between them anymore.
I can't go maybe one space
above Toy Story and find Soul.
This node might be elsewhere in memory.
And so we'll need some
other nodes to actually help
us find what we're
looking for in this index.
I might have one more over here
that tells me what kind of data
is in each of these nodes.
Maybe I have one here that
has both Frozen and Soul.
Notice how here Frozen is the
furthest down alphabetically in this
node up here.
And notice down below here
Soul is the furthest down
alphabetically in this node here.
That is, if what I'm looking
for comes before Frozen,
I should look at this node.
If what I'm looking for comes
after Frozen but before Soul,
I should look in this node.
Or if what I'm looking for comes before
none of these, it comes after Soul,
I should look at this node down here.
So let's find an example.
Let's say I want to find Cars now.
Well I'd start in this root
node, this base of this tree
we're building here that I've
turned kind of right side--
this way.
Let's say Frozen.
I'll go here and does
Cars come before Frozen?
Well it does, so I'll
look in this node now.
I'll come up here and I'll
find Cars in that node.
Let's see here.
Maybe I want to find Ratatouille.
I'll go back to the beginning and
I'll look through this root node.
I'll say, does Ratatouille
come before Frozen?
It doesn't.
It comes after Frozen, so
I'll look and check Soul.
Does Ratatouille come before Soul?
Well it does, so I'll
look in this node now.
I'll go find Luca.
I'm not quite there yet,
but I will see Ratatouille
so I know that I've now found
Ratatouille in my index.
And now for one more--
let me check for understanding here.
How could I find Turning Red?
What steps would I follow
to find Turning Red?
I might start at that root node, but
then what questions should I ask?
AUDIENCE: From Frozen also we can
see Ratatouille is to the right
so that we move in direction of Soul.
Now once we get there we find the middle
elements and we can see Ratatouille
is to the right of the middle elements.
So that's how we find it.
Divide the list into two
halves and look into the half
that the element is found.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I like
what you were thinking here.
So you're talking about traversing this
tree we've built and turned on its side
here.
And let's visualize that search here.
So first we'll start at Frozen and ask,
does Turning Red come before Frozen?
It doesn't.
It comes after, so I'll keep looking.
I'll look at Soul.
Does Turning Red come before Soul?
It doesn't.
It comes after Soul, so I know I
need to look at this node down here.
I'll go find Toy Story.
Not quite there yet, but
now I'll see Turning Red.
I'm able to find what I'm looking for.
And not just that.
I can find what row number Turning
Red is actually in in my table.
So when you use an index, SQL or
SQLite is using some algorithm a bit
like this.
It creates some tree
structure a bit like this here
with individual nodes
that has your column data.
It then uses this kind of
algorithm to search that index
and find whether or not that
piece of data is in your index.
And if it is, it will go ahead and look
up that piece of data in your table.
So see here, although this is
turned on its side, the relationship
between a kind of tree.
We had a root node or a trunk node here
pointing to some of these leaf nodes--
the edge of our graph right here.
And you can see some relationship
between these nodes here
and our tree as well
right here with arrows
pointing across these individual nodes.
So let me pause here and ask what
questions do we have on this structure
and how we've searched it?
AUDIENCE: Is that related
to linked lists or arrays?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
Is this related to
linked lists or arrays?
So if you're familiar, a
linked list is some set
of nodes that have been linked together
in memory using these arrows like we
saw on our diagram here.
It is the case that sometimes an
index will include a linked list.
Let's take one more here.
AUDIENCE: I want to
know, a covering index--
how is the [INAUDIBLE] covering
index and what has been--
I mean, if we just [INAUDIBLE] index
and then we just start covering index,
how SQL automatically getting
that covering index that's here?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so I think we're
asking, how is the index created?
Like, what is the
process for doing that?
Well it turns out that just as we saw
here in the slides, SQLite or whatever
DBMS you're using will take a copy of
the data that should be in that index
and organize it into a tree
structure like we saw here.
It may or may not be similar
to the structure we saw just
a little earlier with nodes that have
different pieces of row data in them.
Good question there.
OK.
So we've seen now the
trade-off that we get
with index, which is they're
very fast to look up some data
but they take up a lot more space.
There's a lot of
redundancy to them here.
There's also one more
trade-off, which is
if I want to insert something into this
structure, it'll take me more time.
I have to navigate this structure here.
I have to figure out should it come
before this value or after this value?
And I'll have to traverse
this tree every time verses
without an index I could just add
something to the end of this list.
But with a B-Tree, with an index,
I need to traverse all these nodes
and figure out where should
that piece of data go?
So these trade-offs are
something you should
keep in mind as you build indexes
and optimize your queries.
OK.
There are ways though to
actually optimize the space
that we use using a tree like this.
We can use a structure called not
an index, but a partial index.
And if you're concerned about space,
a partial index might be good for you.
A partial index only includes a subset
of the data from a given column,
thus making your index smaller overall.
You could think of a partial
index being useful when
you know that your users
will only query a subset--
only a small number of
rows from that table.
And for example in IMDb,
maybe we know people
are more likely to search for a movie
that came out this year versus someone
that came out 15 years ago or so.
So we could create an index that
focuses on those movies that
came out this year versus 15 years
ago or so, and we'll do just that.
If I want to create a partial
index I can use this syntax here.
I could say create an index
and give it some name,
then include some data from
this table and this column here,
or a list of columns I can provide.
But then what I need0 to do is add a
condition where some condition is true.
These are the rows I want
to include in this index.
Before we had just create index name
on table from a list of columns.
Now we can add in this WHERE clause
that says only include those rows where
this condition is true.
So let's try that now.
I'll come back to my computer.
And why don't we try
creating a partial index
to help speed up the lookup of
movies that came out this year.
Well I could come back to my terminal
and I could remove, let's say,
this one over here.
Now I'll try to create
this partial index.
I'll say create an index called
"recents" to indicate this
will help us search for recent movies.
Now I'll make this "recents" ON
"movies" in the ("title") column.
I want to look up titles
ultimately, but now I
only want to create an index for
those rows where the year equals 2023.
I only want to include those titles in
my index that were released in 2023.
So I'll hit Enter now and I'll see I
created this index for myself here.
Now let me try searching for those.
I'll SELECT "title" FROM
"movies" WHERE the "year" = 2023.
Enter.
And I'll see a lot of
movies came out in 2023.
Now, it's taking 1.3 seconds here.
But now I could prove to you
that we are using some index.
I could say EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN and
now type SELECT "title" FROM "movies"
WHERE the "year" = 2023.
Hit Enter.
And now we'll see-- what are we doing?
We're going to-- we'll
scan movies but we're still
going to use the index we
just created called "recents."
So it's helping speed us up
just a little bit overall.
Now let me try dropping this index
and showing you the opposite.
I'll come back over here
and I could try dropping it.
And actually, before
I do that let me show
you what would happen if I
didn't search for movie in 2023.
I would try EXPLAIN QUERY PLAN.
And let me try SELECT "title" FROM
"movies" where the year = 1998
like this.
And see now I'm only
back to scanning movies.
So before in my prior query
I was able to use the index
because my WHERE clause included 2023.
Now though I'm using 1998,
which were rows that were not
included in this partial index.
OK.
So let me ask now, what
questions do we have
on these partial index which
we can use to optimize some
of the space these indexes take up?
AUDIENCE: Are indexes
not saved in schema?
CARTER ZENKE: A good question.
Are indexes saved in the schema?
In SQLite if I type .schema I can
actually see them in my schema.
So let me go back here and show you.
If I now type something like--
let me turn timer off here--
.schema, you can see down below here
that I actually have these indexes
as part of my schema.
I'll see the create index
statements I used down below here.
Create an index called name_index,
called person_index, called recents.
And all that I used to create
these indexes now inside my schema.
If I drop some index it'll then be
just removed from my schema altogether.
Good question.
OK.
So speaking of dropping
indexes, one other way
we can more efficiently use space is
to do a bit of vacuuming so to speak.
So let's introduce this idea
of vacuuming up our database.
Let me show you a slide here.
And this one involves this
idea of trying to clean up
unused space in our database.
Often when we delete something,
either a rows or an index,
we don't actually delete
those bits that were
being used by those rows or that index.
We just mark them as being available
for whatever we next insert.
They can be overwritten, so to speak.
But if I want to actually
reduce the size of my database
after I delete something, I should
use something like vacuum in SQLite
or optimize in some other DBMS.
Vacuuming is a bit like taking those
unused bits and just sucking them up.
Taking them back in so we can give
them back to the operating system.
And the keyword we can use for
vacuum is just simply vacuum.
So let's try this.
I'll come back to my computer over here.
And let me open up a new
terminal-- one that I can use
to find the current size of movies.db.
So I'll hit this + button here
and now I could type a command.
Not a SQL command or a SQLite
command, but actually a Unix command.
I could type du -b for
the disk usage in bytes.
How many bytes is a particular file?
I could then say movies.db here, and
if I hit Enter I should see movies.db
is something like 158 million
bytes or 158 megabytes.
So let's see what happens if I were to
delete an index which you know takes up
some amount of space in our database.
I'll go back to my terminal here.
And let me try to drop an index
that we had recently created.
I'll say DROP INDEX "person_index" to
remove the person index in this case.
I'll hit Enter and now I see
that "person_index" is dropped.
If I type .schema here, I no longer
see it in my schema down below.
So now let me check the disk usage
in bytes and see if it's any smaller.
I'll hit the up arrow to get access
to that same command, hit Enter.
It seems like it's the same size.
It's still 158 megabytes.
So let me try dropping
something more here.
I'll go back to my terminal
here and now I'll try--
what other do I have?
I have "name_index" so I'll say let's
DROP index "name_index" like this.
I'll hit Enter and I'll
see that index is now gone.
Well now I'll also try dropping recents.
I'll DROP INDEX "recents" and
now I believe all of my indexes
should be gone.
If I type .schema, I don't
see any more indexes.
So now let's check on
the disk usage in bytes.
I'll go back to my other
terminal, hit du -b again,
and it's still 158 megabytes.
Well what can we do to clean this up?
We could run vacuum.
If you remember here when we delete
an index-- we drop the index,
we don't actually shrink
our database file.
We just mark those bits that
were part of the index as being
available for re-use.
So let's now vacuum
and compress our file
to give back those bytes and those
bits to the operating system.
I'll come back to my terminal
here and type VACUUM; hit Enter,
and I'll wait for it to
find those bits and bytes,
wait for it to give them
back, to de-allocate them,
to go back to the operating system.
And now if I come back and I
type du -b again, hit Enter--
I should see a much smaller file.
So before we had about
158 million bytes.
We're down to in this case 100
million after dropping our indexes
and using VACUUM.
So let me ask now, what questions
do we have on vacuuming?
AUDIENCE: Can we do
vacuuming in a faster way?
CARTER ZENKE: Can you
vacuum in a faster way?
So I think it depends on
the size of the vacuum
that you're trying to implement here.
If you have a lot of
bits and bytes you're
trying to de-allocate,
that could take more time.
The process here is the computer has
to find those bits and bytes you're
no longer using and then give each of
those back to the operating system.
So it could depend on the size
and how long they take to find.
And let's take another question here.
AUDIENCE: Initially you said once we
drop a database, we don't lose the--
the data is not deleted.
The space is just reallocated, right?
If I go you right.
So does that mean the
queries we run today,
are they locked somewhere that--
let's say you mistakenly did a query.
You can go back and pull that data back?
Is that possible?
Kind of like a reversal of a query.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so you're
talking about some forensics here.
Like, could we mark something as
deleted but still find it later?
There actually are people who are
trained in this, in forensics,
to find pieces of data that
you thought were deleted
but are actually still on your
computer just forgotten, if you will.
In this case in SQLite it
would take a lot of work
to go ahead and find all of those
bits and bytes we've removed.
But once we vacuum, once we actually
give them back to the operating system,
we can no longer find
those in the database
because they're not just
marked as being de-allocated.
They actually have been given back and
they're no longer part of our database.
Good question there.
OK, so we've seen here
how we can optimize
our queries by reducing
the time that they take
although at the cost of some space.
When we come back, we'll see how we
can handle not just one query at a time
but many all at once.
See you in a bit.
And we're back.
So we've seen so far how to optimize
individual queries, ensuring
they take less time and
also to ensure our databases
use as little space as possible.
What we'll focus on
now is trying to ensure
we can handle not just one query
at a time but multiple all at once.
And this is this idea of concurrency.
Concurrency is when I get multiple
queries, multiple interactions, all
at roughly the same time and my
computer system, my database,
needs to figure out how to
handle all of those at once.
This is particularly important for
websites that get a lot of traffic,
or even for the financial sector.
People are constantly making
trades, placing orders,
exchanging money, and so on.
So let's see one example here of a bank.
Let's say here I have
a table of accounts
and each account has a name
and some balance to it.
Well we decide here that maybe
Alice wants to pay Bob $10.
So what should I do to
update the balances here?
Maybe the first thing I should do is
make sure that Bob receives that money.
I could update Bob's account to have
a balance not of $20 but of $30 now.
From $20 to $30.
But here's the thing.
If at this moment somebody looks at this
table, what will they see that's wrong?
What will they see that they might not
get the right picture of at this point?
I'm hearing they might not see
the correct balance for Alice.
Bob has gotten some money.
He's gone from $20 here to $30.
But now I have not just--
let's see, $60 in the bank.
I now have $70 it looks like.
So if somebody looks at this
transaction in this moment
they'll see some incorrect information.
What I should then do is
update Alice's balance,
subtracting $10 so we're at the right
amount of dollars across our bank
accounts here.
So this is an issue.
When I have one ongoing
transaction like this
and somebody else wants
to look at that data,
they really shouldn't be able
to until this transaction is
complete in its entirety.
So ideally-- let's go back to what
we had before with Alice at $10
Bob at $20.
Ideally if Alice wants to pay Bob, this
should happen to an outside observer
all at once.
Bob should get those
$10 and Alice should
lose those $10 at the same
exact moment so nobody
can look and see that Bob has more money
while Alice doesn't have less money.
Now we can implement this
idea of this transaction using
a very similarly-named idea in
databases called a transaction.
Now a transaction in
the world of databases
is an individual unit of work.
That means a transaction can't be
broken down into smaller pieces.
It happens all at once or not at all.
And in fact a transaction
has several properties
and helps implement several
properties of a database.
Among these are ACID--
A-C-I-D. You may have heard of these
if you've looked up something about
databases, but each one stands for
some principle of ensuring a consistent
and reliable database.
In fact, A stands for atomicity, which
means I can't break a transaction down
into smaller pieces.
I can't break a transaction
between Alice and Bob
into Bob's update and
then Alice's update.
It's just update both
accounts at the same time.
Consistency means a transaction
to help me ensure that I
don't violate some database constraint.
Let's say I try to pay
Bob from Alice's account,
but Alice doesn't have the money.
If that is the case, a
transaction will revert, undo.
So I go back to being in this
consistent state for my database.
Isolation means if I have more
than one person trying to access
this database, their queries--
their transactions won't
interfere with each other.
And then finally, durability means
if I were to unplug this database
or we were to encounter a power
failure or the server to crash,
all that data would still be there from
the time we committed our transaction
or saved the results there.
So transactions do a lot for us, but
they have some very simple syntax.
I can simply use BEGIN TRANSACTION and
then follow it up with some statements
I want to include in that transaction.
And once I'm sure I want to save
the results of these statements,
I can then say COMMIT, meaning
save these changes thus far.
And it's using this
kind of syntax we can
ensure that nobody sees
incorrect balances,
let's say, for this
bank account table here.
So let's try this out and implement
a payment between Alice and Bob,
but now using a transaction.
I'll come back to my computer here.
And let me show you a new database.
I'll type sqlite3 bank.db.
I'll hit Enter.
Oh, sqlite3.
Sorry.
bank.db.
I'll hit Enter, and now let me type
.schema to see the schema of this
database.
I'll see here a few different columns.
But I have an "id"
column, my primary key,
a "name" column like we saw in our
slides that is text and can't be null,
and then a "balance" column.
There's an integer, a whole number of
dollars, that also must have a value.
Can't be null.
And I have a check
constraint here saying
the balance must be at all times
greater than or equal to 0.
So this is our implementation
of a table of bank accounts.
Let me try querying here to see
what our account balances look like.
I'll say SELECT * FROM
"accounts" semicolon.
And now I'll see that very same
arrangement we saw in our slides.
Alice has $10, Bob has
$20, and Charlie has $30.
So let me try then processing this
transaction between Alice and Bob.
Well at this moment I might
try to update Bob's account
at the first [? bat. ?] I'll say--
let's try update and
I'll update the accounts
table, set the "balance" equal to
"balance" + 10 where the "id" equals 2.
Remember, Bob's accounts "id" is 2.
So now if I hit Enter here, Bob should
have gotten just 10 more dollars.
But there's a problem.
If I also connect to this database
through another connection here,
sqlite3 bank.DB.
Maybe I'm somebody who's checking
on the balances of the bank.
I say SELECT * FROM "accounts."
What do I see but an
incorrect total balance?
We should have $60, but here I see $70.
So I need to complete
this transaction to ensure
that I actually have the right
amount of balances across the board.
Let me go back here and let me
try to run the next part here.
Let we update this.
I'll say UPDATE "accounts," and I'll SET
"balance" equal to "balance" minus 10.
Minus 10 where the "id" equals in this
case 1 where Alice's bank account ID
is 1.
Now if I hit Enter I should be able
to go back to my other terminal
and check on the balances again.
And now I'll see the right
balances all together.
But there is a way to avoid
me looking at this table
and seeing an incorrect state, and the
way to do that is called a transaction.
So let's go back here, and
I will reset my terminals.
I'll now also give back Alice's money.
Let me give back Bob the $10.
I'm going to go back--
[INAUDIBLE] say where
"id" equals 1 here.
Now Alice will have 10 more dollars.
And I'll go back and
I'll update accounts.
I'll set the "balance"
equal to "balance" minus 10
where the "id" equals 2.
So I'm giving Bob back the $10
that they just gave to Alice.
Now if I SELECT * from "accounts"
we're back to where we began.
So ideally I should able to complete
this transaction between Alice and Bob
without somebody seeing the
intermediate process of Bob
having more money than Alice.
So let's try this.
I'll say BEGIN TRANSACTION; Enter.
And now I can include what I want
to have happen in this transaction.
First I want to update Bob's account.
I'll say UPDATE "accounts" and SET
"balance" equal to "balance" + 10
where the "id" in this case equals--
let's see, 2, because
Bob's account ID is 2.
Now I'll hit Enter, and now I'm
in the middle of this transaction.
But if I go to my other terminal--
let's say I'm somebody new
and I check on the balances of the bank.
I say SELECT * FROM "accounts".
What do I see?
I don't see any change from before.
Alice still has $10, Bob has
$20, and Charlie has $30.
And even though in
this terminal I've been
able to update the account balance,
I haven't committed those changes.
I haven't saved them to
the database just yet.
So let me try now removing
money from Alice's account.
I'll say UPDATE "accounts" and set
"balance" equal to balance minus 10
where the "id" equals 1.
Now I'll remove $10
from Alice's account.
Hit Enter, and still if I go
back to this other perspective
here from somebody else checking
on the bank balances, I see--
well everything is still the same.
But the moment I then
go to this transaction
and finish it by typing COMMIT, meaning
save these changes, I'll commit here.
I can go back and I'll
see all in one moment
that it appears Alice has paid Bob $10.
So this is the atomicity
part of transactions.
I don't see the intermediate
steps in the transaction.
I only see that it happened
all at once or not at all.
OK, so this is one example
here of a transaction.
Let me ask what questions we have so
far on the transactions we've made
and how they can be used.
AUDIENCE: You are
searching based on ID--
like an ID is equal to a question mark.
But in a real-world scenario,
how they would Search maybe
like using the Transaction
ID or basic account number?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
So here I'm searching by ID.
I'm saying that I want to update the
balance of account with ID 1 or ID 2,
for instance.
And this is similar in spirit
to how your bank account likely
has some unique number, an
account number so to speak.
So here in this table
I'm updating balances
by referring to the account number.
You could imagine me
using names, but there
might be in some world
multiple Alices, multiple Bobs.
So I should uniquely identify each
account using its ID in this case.
OK, so let's come back and think
through more kinds of transactions here.
And let's think through a transaction
we actually don't want to complete.
So let's go back to our balance sheet
where we have Alice at $0 and Bob
at $30, and let's say Alice
wants to pay Bob 10 more dollars.
Well if I go through this
transaction, what's going to happen?
Alice will have -$10
and Bob will have $40,
and that violates our check
constraint that we saw in our schema.
The balance of Alice's account
must always be at least $0.
So if I were to complete
this transaction,
that would bring our database
to an inconsistent state.
It violates some
constraint that we have.
But what I can do is undo these changes.
Revert them so that we go
back to the original state
if we ever violate some
constraint like we just did.
There's a technical name for
this, which is rolling back.
So if I ever want to not save
the changes in this transaction,
I can say ROLLBACK.
Go back to the beginning, think about
it as if this transaction never even
happened at all.
So let's try it.
So I'll come back to my
computer, and what I'll do
is try to implement this idea
first without a transaction.
I'll go back to, let's say
this first terminal here,
and I'll SELECT * FROM
"accounts" like this.
Notice how Alice has $0 and Bob has $30.
Well I want to pay Bob 10
more dollars from Alice,
so I'll update Bob's account.
I'll find here my prior
statement, UPDATE "accounts"
SET "balance" equal to "balance"
+ 10 where the "id" equals 2.
And recall that Bob's account ID is 2
I'll hit Enter, and now if
I SELECT * FROM "accounts"
if we're looking somewhere else--
SELECT * FROM "accounts," I'll
see Bob has 10 more dollars.
But now I need to subtract
money from Alice's account.
So I'll use the same thing but now I'll
say minus 10 where the "id" equals 1.
Alice's account ID is 1.
Now I'll try to subtract $10 from Alice,
but I get a constraint failure here.
My check constraint failed
on the balance column.
Why did it do that?
Because I now have less than
$0 in that balance column.
So I need to undo this but I
don't have a transaction here.
What could I do instead to
undo what I've just done?
AUDIENCE: So we can roll back.
CARTER ZENKE: We could roll
back, but here's the thing.
A rollback only works while
we're inside of a transaction.
And a transaction begins when
we say begin transaction.
So here I actually didn't
say begin transaction.
What I have to do instead is
run another update statement.
I have to update, let's
see, Bob's account
to remove the $10 that Alice paid Bob.
So let's try that.
I'll come back to my computer
and I will then revert back.
I'll say let's undo this.
Let's subtract $10 now from
Bob's account where the ID is 2.
Now we're back to where we began.
If I check in from some
other [INAUDIBLE] here,
I'll see we're back to Alice
having $0 and Bob having $30.
But we ideally want to use rollback
to undo some changes that we
have made in a transaction.
So for that let me
now use a transaction.
I'll say BEGIN TRANSACTION
like this, hit Enter.
Now I want to update Bob's balance.
I'll say UPDATE "accounts SET
"balance" equal to "balance" +
10 where the "id" = 2.
Bob's account ID is 2.
Now let me subtract $10
from Alice like this.
- 10.
I'll go back here and say
where the "id" equals 1
for Alice's account, hit Enter.
But now I get that same
constraint failure.
Alice has less than $0,
which can't be possible.
So what do we do?
Instead of having another
update, we could just roll back.
We could undo all of these
previous statements here.
ROLLBACK like this, hit Enter, and now
I should see from another perspective
here my table exactly as it was before
with no intermediate step of Bob
having money but Alice
having negative $10.
So let me ask m we've
seen COMMIT and ROLLBACK.
What questions do we
have on transactions now?
OK.
Seeing none so far, so let's keep going.
Transactions are helpful for
ensuring that our data is consistent
like we just saw, and
that they're also--
we have atomic transactions.
We can't break things
down into smaller pieces.
But there is a case that
transactions can help guard
against some adversarial kind of attack.
We're into what we call race condition.
A race condition is when we have
multiple people, multiple processes
trying to access some value and also
making a decision based on that value.
If unaddressed it can lead to a scenario
that's inconsistent in our database.
And actually hackers can
exploit race conditions
to bring our database to an inconsistent
state in a way that benefits them.
So let's say our friends
Charlie and Alice here, they
decide to rob our bank.
They decide to take money from
it by exploiting race conditions.
And here are the logs of what
Charlie and Alice actually did.
We see here that Charlie and Alice
executed three concurrent transactions
with our bank.
On the one hand Charlie
opened up his bank account
on two different computers.
He logged in and he said let
me transfer $30 to Alice.
He at the same time clicked transfer
on both computers knowing just well
he had only $30 to give to Alice, but he
was going to send her $60 in this case.
He was hoping that we weren't
guarding against race conditions.
That he could send $30 on
both accounts to Alice.
Now at the same time
Alice is at the ATM,
and they're hoping that at the
same time Charlie presses transfer
Alice hits confirm on their transaction
to withdraw $60 from the ATM.
And when all of these
happen at once, we might
run into some inconsistent
states in our database.
Let's say first we run
this transaction here.
Let's focus on this one.
The first step is to
check Charlie's balance.
Does Charlie have $30?
It seems like Charlie does.
We continue we might say, OK, let me
add $30 to Alice's account like this.
Then let me subtract $30 from
Charlie's account down below here.
And finally, that's the
end of our transaction.
We checked Charlie's balance,
we added $30 to Alice,
and subtracted $30 from Charlie.
But now at the same time, we're also
processing the other transfer of $30
to Alice.
So here we check in terms of
our time, top to bottom here--
we check Charlie's
balance at this point.
It's still $30.
Knowing this, this process
goes ahead and says
let's add $30 to Alice's account.
And now only later let's
subtract $30 like this.
Now Charlie well appears to
have no money in his account.
But at this time above we've already
sent $30 to Alice's account two times.
And if Alice is waiting
at the ATM over here
and they press Confirm on that
withdrawal, what might happen
is something like this.
At that moment that Alice
has $60 in their account--
they check and they see it-- they
could then withdraw that $60.
And now that money is
gone from our bank,
even if we realize Charlie
shouldn't have been
able to make that transaction happen.
So what logically is a solution here?
It seems these transactions
happened all at the same time.
But what would you do to reorder
these statements to make it clear
that we can only do one at a time?
What would you do in this case to
update this table to fix this problem?
AUDIENCE: I would do the withdrawal
and the debits as one transaction.
So the subtraction is
done and the addition
is done as one unit of work in order
for the double transfer not to happen.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So ideally we should treat each of
these as a separate transaction.
Literally a transaction in the database
sense where if I go back to this table
if Charlie transfers $30 to
Alice at roughly the same time,
I should handle these sequentially.
I should first do this one,
then I should do this one.
And only after that should Alice be
able to withdraw their $60, or at least
try to in this case.
So we need to make these transactions
sequential, and the word for this
is isolating our transactions.
Here they are not isolated.
They're working at the same time.
But in reality I want
them to be isolated--
happen one after another after another.
So ideally our table
looks more like this.
Charlie hits transfer at the
exact same time on two laptops,
but because we're working in
transactions we only process one first.
We start with this one here.
We check the balance, we say let's add
$30 to Alice's account and subtract $30
from Charlie's.
Once we're sure that is OK,
we'll commit the transaction
and that is a done deal.
Now though, we'll go down below.
We'll say begin transaction.
We'll then say Charlie's balance
is $0 because we're doing this
after we did our first transaction.
Charlie has no more money to give Alice.
At that point what we'll do
is try to add $30 to Alice
but subtract $30 from Charlie, and
we'll realize we made a mistake.
We should roll back and
undo what we just did here.
So these now are separate
transactions happening sequentially,
and we avoid our error
of giving Alice $60 when
she shouldn't have that money at all.
And then only after this is done do
we let Alice try to withdraw $60.
We'll go over here and see.
Alice tries to have a balance of
$60, withdraw $60, and commit it.
But at this point she wouldn't
actually have that money there.
So let's see now what questions
do we have on the way transactions
are sequential in this case?
AUDIENCE: In particularly I want
to ask that there are millions
of transactions that are going on.
Particularly, also, is it like there
that sequentially these transactions
are being handled for the
financial transaction over here
that because there are a number
of banks in a single country
or international transactions.
Are they handle sequentially or there
is some parallel earning mechanism
also exist if you may please clarify.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
So here visually we see these
transactions are actually
sequential in the operation here.
And then your question is, are
they literally sequential, like one
after another after another?
In reality they are very much
just sequential like this.
A database can get
creative with use of locks
as we'll see you in just a
minute, but by and large they
are sequential one after the other.
And it's the job of a
database module to ensure
that these transactions are executed
sequentially in an isolated way.
Good question.
OK.
So let's see now how, if a database
is able to make these sequential,
it must be using something
underneath the hood
to ensure that these
transactions don't interfere.
And in SQLite and other DBMSs we use
this idea of a lock on the database
to ensure people can't access data
when they really shouldn't be able to.
So here let's look at
an idea of what SQLite
has at different kinds of
locks on this database.
We have a few different kinds--
unlocked, shared, and exclusive,
among some others here.
Each one has a different
meaning for different processes.
So let's take a look here
at our bank account table.
Let's say two computers want
to access this account's table.
Well at this time because nobody is
accessing our database, it is unlocked.
Anyone could read from the
database, sort of see what's inside,
or write to it-- add some
data or update some data.
But let's say we have one computer here
who wants to read from this database.
They want to see what data is inside.
Well that database in
SQLite would acquire
what's called a shared lock like this.
They're able to read
the database but also
it's to allow others to read as well.
A shared lock means I'm only reading.
You too could read as well.
So let's say this computer comes in.
They decide to read from this table.
They could acquire the same shared lock.
And because we're only
reading, not updating,
multiple transactions
can read all at once.
We don't have to make these sequential.
But if we have a transaction that's
hoping to write to the database,
to update some value--
well that's when things
get a little weird.
I can't let somebody else read
my data while I'm updating it.
So what I need is for
this process here, if it's
writing, to acquire an exclusive lock.
Meaning this is the only
computer, only transaction that
can read and write to this database.
All others must hold off
in order to be sequential.
So we've seen transactions
then are sequential
and they use this idea of a
lock to ensure other folks
can't read when they're doing something
sensitive like writing to the database.
Let me ask now what questions we have
on locks and how they work for us here?
AUDIENCE: OK, my
question is that suppose
you're one computer [INAUDIBLE].
For what amount this would
allow to do the exclusive lock?
Maybe if the timestamp is
larger, then some other computers
will get timeout exception
and other things, right?
Because it's not allowed to do--
exclusively it's a lock.
How are we going to decide those things?
At what time one
instance is going to be--
put the exclusive lock on the resource?
CARTER ZENKE: So the
question is, at what point
does the transaction actually
get an exclusive lock,
and how do we decide how to prioritize
different transactions here?
Well there are a few algorithms
you could use, one of which
is simply taking the transaction
that just came first.
If at this point I receive a
request for an exclusive lock,
I might just wait for others to finish
reading and allow that one to proceed.
I could also use a process called
time-stamping, which is similar to this
where I look at the timestamp, the time
my database tried to write to the log
and use the one that is
earliest in that case.
Now it's important to note that an
exclusive lock does block others
from running their own transactions.
If I have an exclusive lock, no
one else can run their transaction.
That is kind of a necessary
downside in this case
to ensure that I don't make
mistakes in updating my table.
Let's take one more here.
AUDIENCE: What's the
granularity on locking?
I mean, you seem to say you locked
the database, but that's craziness.
Do you lock a table or do
you lock a record on a table?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, it might
depend on the DBMS itself.
So at the very coarsest, a lock
might just lock the entire database.
I can't actually see
anything inside of it.
And I'll be able to demonstrate
that for you in a minute here.
Let me go back to my computer.
Let me try to deliberately
lock this database.
If I go to my terminal, I
can begin a transaction that
automatically has an exclusive lock.
In SQLite the statement
is BEGIN EXCLUSIVE.
BEGIN EXCLUSIVE TRANSACTION.
I'll hit Enter like this, and now I'm
in the middle of this transaction.
It's exclusive.
Has an exclusive lock
nobody else can read.
If I go back to my other terminal
here, connect to my database,
I could try SELECT * FROM "accounts"
just to read from this table.
And now I see Runtime error--
database is locked.
The entire database cannot be read
from at the very coarsest level
of an exclusive lock.
Now because these locks are so coarse--
I have to lock the entire database,
SQLite has its own module,
a way of prioritizing transactions
and ensuring that a transaction only
has an exclusive lock for the
duration it absolutely needs to.
Because otherwise you would
slow down substantially
if I had to wait and wait
and wait for somebody
to finish with their transaction.
OK.
So this then is how we can handle not
just one query at a time but multiple.
And today we've seen how to optimize
our databases from making sure queries
are faster to also making sure our
databases use as little space as
possible.
We'll see next time how
to actually scale up
our databases using other DBMSs--
like MySQL-- besides SQLite.
We'll see you next time.