[MUSIC PLAYING]
CARTER ZENKE: OK, well, hello,
one and all, and welcome
back to CS50 Introduction
to Databases with SQL.
My name is Carter
Zenke, and this week is
the culmination of all you've
learned over the past several weeks
in the course.
Today, we'll give the tools to
all that you've done in the past,
but now just at a bigger scale.
Now, when we're talking about scale,
it's worth defining what scale is
and what it means for some
application to have scalability.
For an application to be
scalable or to have scalability,
it means it can take some number
of requests and handle those,
whether that request is small or large.
And so to kick things off
here, let me ask a question.
What are some famous tech
companies you've seen
that have needed to scale over time?
Let's brainstorm here.
Which ones are you
familiar with that needed
to scale over time to handle
more users, more data?
What have you seen?
AUDIENCE: Any social media
sites, such as Facebook?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
any social media sites.
You can think of things like Facebook,
now Meta, Instagram, and similar.
And these kinds of sites might have
some really large number of users
that are always accessing their data.
But even though they have a
constantly large number of users,
there might even be spikes in the
number of requests that they get.
Maybe during the World Cup, for
example, everyone is on Facebook,
everyone's on Instagram.
That would be a spike our
application should be able to handle,
if it is truly scalable.
Let's take one more idea here.
What other kinds of companies-- tech,
prominently-- have needed to scale?
AUDIENCE: So I think for banking
systems, they might start locally,
but if we consider national and
international level banking?
CARTER ZENKE: So you're right.
A banking system might need to scale as
they gain more users, or more accounts,
or they want to process
more transactions.
Now, today, we'll introduce you to a
few new DBMSes, or database management
systems, like MySQL and PostgreSQL--
or just Postgres for short.
And developers often
reach to these when they
want to scale some
application or some database
because, whereas SQLite was a
embedded database, MySQL and Postgres,
these are database servers.
That means they often run on
their own dedicated hardware
that you connect to over the
internet to run your SQL queries.
And now, being a database server,
they have a few advantages.
They can store data not just on
disk, like on an SSD or a hard drive,
but in RAM, or Random Access Memory,
which often allows for faster querying.
They also have a full
feature set to take advantage
of ways you could scale, like
replication and sharding,
that we'll talk about later on today.
Now, before then, we'll actually
compare MySQL and Postgres with SQLite,
paying attention, in
particular, to types.
But later on, we'll focus on their
features for scaling as well.
Now, we'll do all of this
in the context of the MBTA,
or the Massachusetts Bay
Transportation Authority.
This is the subway
system here in Boston.
And if you're ever in town
and you want to get around,
you might use one of these subway lines.
You could enter under the ground, get on
a train, and go across town on either,
let's say, the red line, on
watch Harvard and MIT are
a part, the green line, the
orange line, or the blue line.
And if you recall, in
our week on designing,
we talked about how to represent all
of the riders and stations on the MBTA
here.
Now, one thing we discussed
was that the MBTA doesn't
keep track of individual people.
You often don't register
your name with them.
You, instead, get your
very own CharlieCard
that you might swipe when
you enter some station.
Often, if I'm getting on
the Harvard Square stop,
I'll take out my CharlieCard
and enter that station.
I'll swipe it against some
counter, and that will log my fare.
I could also swipe my card
to deposit some funds,
to pay my fare in the future.
And in some stops, I might
actually swipe to leave the station
and pay some extra fare there.
Now, we decided, then, to represent, in
this case, cards, swipes, and stations
with their own table for each of them.
Cards just had their own unique ID,
and those cards made some swipe.
And like we just mentioned,
this swipe has a certain type.
Did I swipe it to, let's
say, enter the station,
did I swipe it to exit
the station, or did I
swipe my card to deposit
some funds into my account?
And each swipe has, as well, its
own date and time it occurred
as well as some amount
associated with it.
Did I pay some money to enter,
or did I deposit some money
to actually add to the
funds in my account?
And then, finally, this all
happens at individual stations,
with their own IDs, their own
names, like the Harvard Square stop
or the Kendall/MIT stop, and
their own line, like the red,
green, blue, or orange lines.
So our goal will be to first
compare MySQL with SQLite, seeing
how we can translate a schema
like this from SQLite to MySQL.
OK, let me come back to my computer
here and open up our very first instance
of a MySQL server.
So to connect to this
server here, I can run
some command that begins with mysql.
This is a command line
program I can run to connect
to the server over the internet.
Now, unlike SQLite, MySQL actually
has individual user accounts
to log into the database.
And here, I want to log in as the root
user or the admin for this database.
Now, to say the user I want to log
in as, I can type dash u, where
u is in lowercase here,
followed by the name of the user
I'm logging in as-- in this case, root.
And again, root to just some synonym
for the admin of some database.
Now, I connect to this
database over the internet.
And I might often include the IP address
of the computer, the unique identifier
of that computer on the internet.
For my sake, though, this database
is on my very own computer here.
So for the host--
or I type dash h, where
h is in lowercase--
I can say 127.0.0.1,
which, if you're familiar,
is the IP address for my own home
computer, also known as local host.
Now, I can keep going,
and I could tell MySQL
what the port I'm connecting to is.
In this case, I'll type dash p,
where p is an uppercase, and then
the port number--
3306 by default. And then I want to
be prompted for the root password.
So I'll type dash p,
where p is lowercase.
And finally, I'll hit Enter to connect.
I'll type in my password,
and I should see
that I'm connected to my MySQL server.
Now, this is a full database server.
And as such, it could have
multiple databases inside of it.
In fact, there are a few here already.
If I type SHOW DATABASES,
just like this,
you should see, by default, on your own
MySQL installation on your own server,
a few default databases,
like information schema,
or MySQL, or performance
schema, or system.
And these are tables or
databases that have some meta
information on the server, like
the user accounts, how performance
is configured, and other details
that you might care about
if you're a system administrator.
So we've seen here how to log in to a
MySQL server and some of these default
databases.
Now let me ask, what questions
do we have on MySQL so far?
AUDIENCE: What's -u root?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, let
me go back to my computer.
I can show you what that looked like
so we can refresh our memories on that.
So if you recall-- let me
open up a new terminal here--
to connect to this server I
typed mysql u root, or -u root.
And what this means is when I
want to connect to my server,
I have to connect to it
using some user account.
Unlike SQL, where I could just
kind of log in without any users,
MySQL has users.
So the -u says, here comes
the user I want to log in as.
And root, in this case,
is a name for the admin,
just some geek historical term
for the admin of some system.
I could also very well use -u carter
if my username was just Carter.
But here, we're using
route to get access
to some administrative privileges.
OK, good question.
Good to clarify that.
So let's keep going.
And right now, we have access
to our database server,
with the databases inside of it.
But our goal is to
design the MBTA system
and create our very own
database, now in MySQL.
So let me try creating
some new database.
I'll say CREATE DATABASE, like this.
And now I'll give it some name.
And in MySQL, I don't use double
quotes, like I did in SQLite.
I use back ticks, like this.
CREATE DATABASE, back
tick, mbta for title,
back tick again to close that all out.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see the query
goes, OK, one row affected.
If I now type SHOW DATABASES--
SHOW DATABASES-- I should see that
MBTA is now part of this server.
And if I want to run my future
queries on this database,
I could use another command,
another statement here, USE.
I'll say USE mbta, semicolon, hit Enter.
And I see Database changed.
So now all my future queries will be run
on this MBTA database that I just made.
So presently, our database is empty.
And it's up to us to add in some tables.
So let's think through how we could add
tables to our very own database we've
just made here.
But one thing we should focus on is
this idea of the types for our columns.
I think we know already
what tables we'll have
and what names we'll give them, but it
remains to be seen what kind of columns
should we add.
And actually, in MySQL, we get
a lot more control over types.
We no longer have just text
and numeric and integer.
We have a lot more control
and a lot more variety.
So let's look here at our cards table.
We want to recreate this now in MySQL.
And this is from SQLite here.
Recall how we had a table called cards
that had an id column, with the type
affinity of INTEGER.
And that was our primary key down here.
So our goal is now to think about
how do we translate this from SQL
right to MySQL.
So we should think, what kind of
types might MySQL have for integers?
Well, it turns out there's
more than just one.
There are actually several here.
We have tiny int, small int,
medium int, int, and then big int,
so lots of choices over our integers.
And these vary just based on their size.
I mean, they all store whole numbers.
But they do vary based on their size.
So a tiny int is only a single byte.
It's about 8 bits.
But a big int, that's
8 bytes, or 64 bits.
Now, why do we have so many of these?
Why can't we just have one?
Well, let me ask you all
to use your own intuition.
I mean, what does using
more bytes and more bits
get me when I'm trying
to represent an integer?
MySQL basically, it depends on the
need of the DB or the organization.
If the data requires much
more storage, then it
means we need to have
a bigger data type.
But if currently if we need
smaller sizes, then it means
we need to use smaller data types.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so
I like your thinking.
And I think kind of behind that is
this idea that if we used more bits,
we'd be able to count higher.
Just as I have on my hands, like
10 fingers, if I had more fingers,
I could count higher in
unitary notation, right?
Or if I had more digits, I could
count higher using decimal.
So it's the same thing in binary
here, where I could count higher
the more bits that I have.
So if I take a look at this
table here, each data type
has a range of values that
it could possibly store.
If I'm talking about both
negative and positive values,
here's the range for
each of these data types.
You could see for a tiny int
we can only count up to 127.
And that is it.
We cannot count higher
using a single byte.
But if I used a big int, well, I
could count all the way up to 2
to the 63rd power minus 1.
That is almost unpronounceably big.
It's something like a
quintillion number of options
that you might have between
these two minimum values
and the maximum values here.
So all trade off what
you want to represent.
But our goal here is to
translate a primary key.
A primary key, it isn't negative.
So we could perhaps use something
called an unsigned integer.
An unsigned integer has no
negative value, starts at 0,
but can then go to a
higher positive value
because we're now using some of
those combinations of ones and zeros
that represented negative numbers
now for positive numbers too.
So here an int can go up to almost
4.2 billion values, between 0
and 4.2 billion.
So an int is already pretty darn big.
So with these in mind, tiny int, small
int, medium int, int, and big int,
let's go back to our SQLite
CREATE TABLE statement.
And let me actually ask you all, what
would you substitute in place here?
We no longer have integer
for our primary key.
But which of these do
you think seems the best
substitute for our primary key on cards,
tiny, small, medium, int, or big int?
AUDIENCE: So in case we know that
it's not going to be really huge,
we can just use an int.
But if it's going to be very large, like
say a timestamp, we could use big int.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
I like your thinking.
So if it's big but not too big,
maybe an int would be good.
If we know for sure though
it's going to be huge, well,
a big int is probably best.
And let me offer some intuition here.
So if there are fewer
than four billion people
on this Earth, which I
believe is a true fact,
and we're using one of these
IDs to represent one card,
well, if everyone on Earth visited
Boston and got their own CharlieCard,
we wouldn't run out of
values using an int here.
So it seems like that's
a pretty safe bet,
unless we knew that
everyone in Boston was
going to have 10 CharlieCards, or 20,
or more, then we could use a big int.
But in this case, an
int seems pretty safe.
So let's update this.
Let's go from SQLite now to MySQL.
So here I had the ID column
with type affinity integer.
And my first step in
converting should probably
be to get rid of these double quotes.
I no longer need to use double quotes.
I should use back ticks as
a matter of style in MySQL.
But now I should update this type from
integer perhaps to a plain old int.
As we discussed before, some
intuition for that is we'll
probably never have more than four
billion CharlieCards in our table.
Now, there's one more thing to add
too, which is this, auto increment.
So SQLite for free gave us a primary
key that if I inserted some value
and didn't provide a
value for the primary key,
SQLite would generate that for me.
But in MySQL, I have to
actually say auto increment.
If I add some new row, make sure you
take the highest primary key right now,
increase it by 1, and
assign it to that new value.
So you'll often see primary keys
being defined with the name ID,
and the type int, and the auto
increment property of that column there.
So let me ask now, what questions do
we have on these integers and types
so far?
AUDIENCE: For ID we
have using integer type.
Why we know that ID cannot be negative
it will always start from one and go
onward.
So we should use it and [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
So here we didn't include
it partly for slides sake.
But you could if you wanted to
make sure that the ID is unsigned.
So unsigned means going from 0 all
the way up to some larger number.
Whereas not unsigned, or
just assigned integer,
goes from negative to
some positive value.
Absolutely right.
OK, let's keep going then.
And let's think through
our next table here.
So our next table is not
just the cards table.
It's also the stations table.
And actually, before we do that, let's
actually try to add in our cards table
to our server.
So I'll go to MySQL here.
And now, let me try to create this
table to store it inside of our server
before we move on to stations.
So I'll say create table cards.
And then I'll follow
some very similar syntax
from what you've seen
before, create table cards.
Now, let me add an ID column,
int, and auto increment like this.
And now, I'll make the
primary key ID, like this.
Now, I'll close out my create
table with a semicolon, hit Enter.
And I should see the query is OK.
Now, if I use the MBTA database,
as I did before, I typed use MBTA,
I could show tables, like
this, semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I'll see I have a cards
table inside the MBTA database.
So kind of like, for example, typing dot
schema or dot tables, in this instance,
in SQLite to see what tables I have.
Now though, let me try this.
Let me try describe cards.
Describe is a bit more like dot schema
to show me the schema of this table.
I'll describe cards.
And I'll see a few
different columns here.
Let me come over to this board here.
And we'll see that this table, cards,
has one column, one field, called ID.
The type of this column is an
integer, as we said it was before
in our create table statement.
Now, this null here, this
is whether this column
can accept a null value, yes or no.
Yes means it can accept a null value.
It can hold null.
No means it should
never hold a null value.
So this ID should never
include a null value.
Now, the key, key column tells
us what role this column plays
in terms of the keys of this table.
PRI here, P-R-I, stands for primary key.
This is the primary key of our table.
Default means the initial
value given to any value.
If we inserted some
row with no value, we'd
get back this default value here, null.
And the extra is what we
included auto increment.
It should increase by one
every time we add some new row.
So using describe and show
tables, you can actually
see what you're creating along the way.
So now, let's keep going.
Let's actually focus on
creating our stations table.
And for that, we'll pull up our SQLite
syntax we use to create that table.
So here, here was what we used to
create the stations table in SQLite.
We gave each station an ID that was an
integer, the primary key of this table.
We then gave them each
a name and a line.
Like the name could be the Harvard
Square Station or the Kendall MIT
station.
And the line could be red,
green, blue, whatever line
this station is a part of.
And of course, the primary key is
our ID column, as we just said.
Now here, we've seen how to
handle this integer type.
But we haven't yet seen
how to handle text.
Like could we do better than
this in MySQL compared to SQLite?
It turns out that we can.
We have a variety of options for
representing strings, basically
this collection of text here.
And two of the more popular ones
are going to be char and varchar.
So char is a fixed width string, a
string that only has and will ever
have the same number of characters.
You could think of,
for example, in the US,
we abbreviate state names using two
letters, like MA from Massachusetts,
or VA for Virginia.
You might do the same thing
with countries as well.
Now, that would be useful for a
char because this char will always
hold only two characters.
But often you're not sure
how long the string is.
You're going to add to your column.
Like let's say you're trying
to store names of people.
Well, my name is Carter.
But yours could be longer or shorter.
So a varchar works
well for that scenario,
where a varchar can accept
a variable length string up
to some number of characters.
And when you use these,
MySQL will ask you
to provide how much space this
type should take up using M here.
So I could say char
parentheses 2 to get back
a fixed width string of two characters.
For varchar I could say varchar and
put in the middle here like, let's say,
16, or 32, or 64.
And that would be the
maximum size of the string
that I could represent using varchar.
So good here for strings that are
going to be a bit shorter in length.
What if though you want to
store the text of a book
or something a bit longer than that?
Well, you could use another
type, this one called text.
And this is different
than SQLite's text.
In SQLite's text I could store short
strings, long strings, et cetera.
In MySQL text is good for longer chunks
of text, paragraphs, pages of books,
and so on.
And you actually have some options for
the length or the size of this text.
You could use tiny text,
medium text, or long text.
Each just uses some variable amount
of space on your computer to store,
in this case, characters
that are going to be
longer than any particular
string, like a name,
and more like some page in a book.
Now, besides text we do
have our old friend blob.
And blob still stores binary
exactly as you give it.
And more interestingly though,
we also have enum and set.
And these are brand new.
These are not in SQLite.
But they're very useful for us.
If you remember back in our week on
designing, we introduced constraints.
Maybe a constraint is that this column
should only have certain values.
Like let's say if we're
calculating t-shirt sizes,
I should only have xs for extra
small, s for small, m for medium.
There's some fixed range of
values this column could hold.
Well, I could use enum
for that, where enum
lets me enumerate the possible
options I could put into this column,
like xs, s, m if I'm doing t-shirt
sizes, or something else altogether.
Now, set complements enum.
Enum means I can only
have one of these options.
If I had xs, x, s, m and so on for
t-shirt sizes, I can only choose one.
But a set will allow me to choose more
than one to store in that same cell.
You could think of, for
example, movie genres.
A movie isn't just a
horror, or a fiction.
Or it isn't just comedy.
It could be all of those together.
And so set would allow you to choose
not just one option from your list,
but multiple and put it inside
of that single cell there.
So let's go back to our
SQLite create table statement.
And let's update this for MySQL.
Well, the first thing you do is what?
Change these double
quotes to back ticks.
So I'll do that here.
And now, let's update this ID.
We saw before we could use regular
old int and auto increment, like this.
But now we have some more choice.
Like for this name
field that should store
the name of a station, let me actually
ask you all, what do you think
is the best type to use?
I'm just wanting the
name of some station.
AUDIENCE: It would be a varchar
simply because you don't know
how long the station name actually is.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a good point.
So we're always creating new stations.
And maybe some station
name is pretty long.
Or maybe it's short.
We can't really tell, right?
So a varchar is good if we have
some variable amount of characters
inside the text we're trying to store.
And notice how a station name
isn't paragraphs of text.
It's just maybe a few words.
That's good for a varchar.
And in general here I could say,
well, let's try to use a varchar
and say we could use up to 32
characters including spaces.
I think that will cover us pretty
well for names of stations.
Now let's talk about the line.
Now, in Boston, there are a few lines.
There's the blue line, the green line,
the red line, even the silver line.
But what type should we
use for storing lines then
that these stations are a part of?
AUDIENCE: In this case,
I believe that there
can be two options, where it
would be a small integer number
and point it to another
table storing the colors.
Another one will be limited char taking
into account that perhaps the longest
color name will be like
aquamarine, or something like that,
and truncate it just to that size
will be another option as well.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I love your
thinking through multiple options here.
And indeed, there's usually
more than one option
for any given type of a table here.
So for this one, I mean, you could
actually have line be a foreign key
and reference some other table,
to your point, of those colors.
So line might then be an integer.
We could also make line another varchar.
Maybe this one's a little shorter.
Like it's always going to be
just blue, green, red, or so on,
so a pretty short string, but
still variable length nonetheless.
So you could say varchar
maybe 9, for instance,
if we're representing a color here.
One other option though exists,
one that kind of constrains us,
but that might still be a good fit.
AUDIENCE: Maybe it would
be good to use a set.
CARTER ZENKE: To use set.
You could use set as well.
So you could say that a station might
be on the blue line and the green line
as exists in the real world.
You could certainly use set for that.
For our purposes, I might just go ahead
and simplify things and just say enum.
A station will only be on one
line at a time for simplicity.
But if you wanted a station on more than
one line, you could use set as well.
And in this enum or in this set we
could include the possible lines
that currently exist in the MBTA.
So great reasoning through
some different data types here.
Let's now build this into
our MySQL server here.
I'll come back.
And I will create this table.
So we saw before I could
simply use create table.
I could say create table.
And then I could say give
it a name called stations.
And inside I'll make sure to include--
let me indent four spaces
here, one, two, three, four--
give it an ID, which has the
type integer and auto increment.
Then afterwards, we also want to
include the name of our station, which
could be a varchar up to size 32.
It could include up to 32 characters.
And this should also
be not null and unique.
Those same kind of column constraints,
they're still here in MySQL.
Now I could also
include the line column.
And for simplicity, I could just assume
every station is part of only one line.
So I'll say enum here.
And I'll choose blue, and
green, and orange, and red.
These are four lines for the
subway that exist here in Boston.
And I'll make sure this
has to have a value.
It can't be null.
Put that not null constraint here.
Then I'll say my primary
key is the ID column.
And I will go ahead and close
this out, hit semicolon and Enter.
And I'll see query OK.
So now, if I show tables, Enter,
I'll see both cards and stations.
And if I were to describe
stations, what do I see here?
Let's take a look.
I'll come back over here.
And I'll see I have three
columns, ID, name, and line.
And each of these has
their very own type,
as I see in this column
of my describes output.
I see here that the type
of ID is an integer.
The type of name is a varchar 32.
And the type of line is an enum.
Blue, green, orange, or red are the
possible values for that column.
Now, none of these columns can
have a null value inside of them.
But here's the interesting part.
I see ID has a key, PRI, primary.
That means ID is my primary key.
But I also see uni, where
uni stands for unique.
Now, we saw before this name column.
I applied a unique constraint,
meaning there can only
be a given station with a unique name.
I can't duplicate station names.
And then of course, over here we also
saw the extra column auto increment
that I applied to the ID column here.
So let me ask.
We've seen now some new types for
text, some new types for enum, and set,
and so on.
What questions do we have on these
new types and how we've used them?
AUDIENCE: I was wondering if it
would be perhaps possible to include
a table as the argument to enum?
CARTER ZENKE: Oh, a good question.
I actually am not sure.
I could imagine the possibility
of using a nested select for that.
But I mean, let's reason
through this here.
If I had a table that
was growing, would I
want to use those table results
in my create table statement?
I would argue probably not because then
things are going to change over time.
So probably worth just enumerating
one at a time explicitly
what might go into that enum.
But I encourage you to try that
out too and see what happens.
Let's take one more.
AUDIENCE: Here's the
problem for a database
if I, for example, I have no idea how
long could be the name of the station.
And if I write a varchar,
for example, 100 or 300.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so maybe
you're thinking of a scenario
where you don't know how
long it's going to be.
So you'd be kind of extra safe.
You'd say like varchar
300, for instance,
just to accommodate anything
you could put in there.
That is OK.
But the trade off is you're
then using up to 300 bytes
every time you store a smaller string.
Like if I use varchar
300 and I only ever use,
let's say, like 10 characters
on my longest string, well,
I'm wasting some space.
So it's worthwhile to
think through beforehand,
what should I actually use here?
And something to keep in
mind is you can always
expand a varchar using
MySQL's alter table statement.
So we'll see that in just a
bit, how to use alter table.
But you could always
expand if you need to.
OK, good questions here.
Let's keep going then.
And our next table is going to be
the table that represents swipes.
We have cards and stations.
But now we have to represent
swipes at those stations.
Well, let's come back to our
schema for swipes in SQLite.
Here, I had this table
called swipes that
had some columns up top and some
primary foreign keys down below.
But the important part for us now is
going to be these three columns, type,
date time, and amount.
And remember that on the MBTA,
I can take my CharlieCard.
I can make a swipe when I enter, exit,
or deposit some money at a station.
That's that type column here.
It could be either
enter, exit, or deposit.
Now, date time is the time
and date I swipe that card
to enter, exit, or deposit some funds.
And amount is the amount in dollars
associated with that transaction.
Now, the fare nowadays is like $2.40.
Back in the '50s it was
maybe like a dime or so.
It changes over time.
So it's worth keeping
track of in our table here.
So let's think through some
options that MySQL gives us.
Among them are options
for dates and time.
So whereas in SQLite we had
numeric for dates and times,
in MySQL we actually have
explicit date and time types.
For instance, we have
all these here, date,
which is just a date, like the
year, the month, the day, time,
which is the actual time, like
hours, minutes, and seconds.
We then have date time, which
combines those, timestamp,
which is similar but used with a
bit more precision often for logging
events on your own software, and
then year, which is just 2023,
or 2020 for instance,
in a single column.
Now, you can get more
particular about how precise you
want to be with these times.
For time, date time,
and timestamp, I can
specify how many decimal
digits I want to keep
track of after the decimal point.
Do I want to keep track of tenths of
seconds, hundredths, or thousandths?
I could specify that using this (fsp).
In this case, I could say
one, two, three, four, up to I
believe six to figure
out how precisely do I
want to keep track of time, where
more digits means more precision.
So I could use these
for dates and times.
That could get us through part
of our table migration here.
But I should also think about how
to represent real numbers, that is
numbers with a decimal point in them.
Now, you might think back to SQLite
and remember the real data type.
And we have some similar options here.
We have float and double precision,
where the only difference is
float stores a number in size 4 bytes.
Whereas, double precision
stores that number in 8 bytes.
And you might be thinking,
well, if they both store
a decimal number, a real number, why
would I choose one over the other?
Or why would I use more space when
float does the same thing for me
in fewer bytes?
Well, it turns out that
in computer science,
we run into this problem of floating
point imprecision, where there
are an infinite number of real numbers.
Like if I asked you to find me all of
the decimal numbers between 1 and 2,
you would be here for
literally an eternity.
And if we have so many numbers
to represent, but so few bits,
it goes to say that we can
only represent some of them
and not all of them.
So at the end of the day, floating
point numbers, decimals, real numbers,
will be imprecisely represented.
Now, a double precision could
get us more of the way there.
We could use more bits to
more precisely represent
some number, which you might use if
you're a scientist, someone who wants
to keep track of things very precisely.
If you don't care as much
though, you could use a float
and just use a little bit less space.
Now thankfully, this trade off
isn't quite so salient in MySQL
because you also get access to
fixed precision types, where
fixed precision means I can specify
I want to always have two places
after the decimal precisely represented.
And one type for this will be the
decimal type, where I can use a decimal
and then say, I want to store
a certain number of digits
with some number coming
after the decimal point.
Now, for example, I could
say decimal 5 comma 1.
And I could store any number
between negative 999.99 up to 999.99
so long as there are only two
places after the decimal here.
Now, I could increase this.
I could say I want to
go beyond this range.
I want to have more digits.
I could increase this first parameter
here from five, let's say, to six.
And now I have a wider range.
I have 9,999 all the way down
to negative 9,999, in both cases
0.992 decimal digits
after this decimal point.
Now, I can keep going.
I could say 7 and get
an even bigger range.
But if I want to present something
precisely after the decimal point, what
could I do?
I could change this one too from
2, let's say, to 3 or even to 4.
I could keep going.
But notice how my range shrinks.
What I get in return is just more
digits after that decimal point
precisely represented.
I don't have to worry about
floating point imprecision,
so long as I'm using decimal and
telling MySQL how many digits I want
and how many come after
the decimal point.
OK, so let's try this here.
I want to migrate this
table from SQLite to MySQL.
The first thing to do,
change these quotes
from double quotes to back ticks.
I could then update my
primary key, and so on.
But let's focus now on this type.
This type column should only
have some set of values,
like enter, exit, or deposit.
And when you see that, you
could think I should probably
use an enum to only
store some data types,
some values that are
inside of this list.
So I'll make this now an enum.
But the question then becomes,
what should I use for date time?
What type have we seen so far that
could be useful for storing the date
and time I swiped my CharlieCard?
AUDIENCE: Yes, I believe we can
use that date time data type.
CARTER ZENKE: I could use date time,
so kind of self-explanatory here.
I mean, the column is called date time.
And coincidentally,
MySQL also has a type
called date time that stores both
a date year, year, year, mm, dd,
and then the hour.
Along with that, I could say date
time here to get both day and time.
Now, the next one, amount.
Now, it's worth noting I want
to be precise with this amount.
Like if I'm going to sum up
many, many amounts, many fares,
I want it to be accurate.
So I don't want to deal with, let's
say, float or double precision.
I want to specify how
precise I should be.
Let me ask, what data type might be good
for storing the amount of some given
fare?
AUDIENCE: I believe we can
use the decimal data type.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, you could absolutely
use the decimal data type here.
So decimal was part of MySQL's
fixed precision kinds of types.
So we could use that here to precisely
represent the amount column here.
I could change this from numeric
in SQLite to decimal now,
where decimal I could say takes five
possible digits, like five total.
And two now could come
after the decimal point.
So I could have amounts
or fares that go up
to hundreds of dollars, which
often isn't going to happen.
But I could be safe
here if I need to be.
OK, let's go ahead and combine this
and put this inside of our MySQL server
here.
I'll come back to my computer here.
And my goal is to run this
create table statement to create
this table on our server.
I'll say create a table
called swipes, like this.
And I'll include a few columns we didn't
show on the slides just for simplicity.
All first include the
ID column with type int.
And I also want to make sure this
auto increments as I add to it.
I'll then go on.
And I will also include a card
ID column that has a type int.
And then I'll include a station ID
column, which also has type int.
So now, I can see which card
ID is swiped at which station.
Now, when they swipe here at the MBTA,
swipe can mean a few different things.
You can have a different type.
One type we might care
about is the enter type,
when I swipe to enter some station.
I could also swipe to exit
some station or to deposit
some funds into my account.
And a type should never be null.
It has to be not null constraint here.
Now, a swipe happens at some
particular date and time.
So I'll include the date time column
and say that this is of type date time.
I want to make sure this
column always has some value.
So it's not null.
And the default when
I insert some new row
will be this special value here, current
timestamp, the current date and time.
Now I'll go on.
And I'll include the
amount of some swipe.
I'll hit space.
And then I'll say amount here.
This is the amount
associated with that swipe.
Was I charged money?
Was I adding money?
Here I'll say I want this to
be a decimal type because you
said we want this to be precise.
And decimal is a fixed precision type.
I'll say I want five decimal digits
with two after the decimal point.
Now, decimal should be not null.
And I'll include our
same check constraint.
I'll check that amount with back
ticks here does not equal 0.
And if that's the case, I'll be
able to insert some new swipe.
Now, I'll assign my table constraints,
like primary keys and foreign keys.
I'll say my primary key is
the ID column, like this.
And then if I hit Enter again, my
foreign key, in this case card ID,
should reference, it references
cards table and the ID column
in cards, like this.
So that card ID column references
the ID column in the cards table.
Now, I'll include my last foreign key.
The foreign key station ID
references the station's table
and the ID column in stations.
And now to quickly review to make sure
I typed everything in correctly here,
so we have the ID column, the card
ID column, station ID, type of enum,
date time, amount.
I think we'll be good here.
So if I hit Enter and then
use parentheses semicolon,
I should see query OK
zero rows affected.
Now, if I type, in this
case, show tables Enter,
I'll see I have a new swipes table.
And if I type describe
swipes, like this,
I should see some familiar output.
If I go back to my screen
over here, we can take a look.
We have again, our fields, ID, card
ID, and so on, types, int, enum,
date time, decimal.
Some can have null
values, some should not.
We have a primary key here.
But now the interesting
thing is this M-U-L. Well,
if I look at card ID and station ID,
what do we call those two columns?
What kind of constraints did I
apply to card ID and station ID?
AUDIENCE: So we uses the foreign
key constraints, the foreign key.
So it's referencing the station
and the card [INAUDIBLE]..
CARTER ZENKE: You're exactly right.
We applied the foreign key constraint
to the card ID and station ID columns.
So this M-U-L here is referring to
the fact that these are foreign keys.
And M-U-L stands for something
like multiple or multi.
It means I could have, in this
case, multiple of the same value
because it is a foreign
key in this table.
Now, the default here we
now see current timestamp.
When I insert some
value into this table,
insert some rows, sorry, into this table
and don't supply a value for the date
time column, I'll instead
make that default value
the current date and the current time.
And here we see some extras, like
auto increment that we saw before,
and now default generated, meaning
this is a generated column that
will automatically create some value
for me when I insert some new row.
OK, so let me ask, what questions do
we have then on these new types, dates
and times, and more?
AUDIENCE: Yes, I wanted
to know the precedence
in which the attributes, the specific
constraints, the attributes are added.
So is it in the format
of the describe table?
In the describe table,
there's a setting format
in which the data is the
priority in which you do it?
Let's say an integer before.
Let's say a unique constraint before.
And not null.
What's the precedent?
And secondly, is there any
type affinity in MySQL?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, both good questions.
I'll answer the first one first.
So the first one is,
what's the precedence,
I believe, of these
constraints we're applying?
If I look at this output
of describe swipes here,
I see that I applied some constraints.
Among them are the foreign key
constraint, the primary key constraint.
Some I made sure that I couldn't
have some null value in here.
In effect, they all combine
to work for me here.
So when I made that
create table statement,
I applied multiple constraints,
like not null and unique.
And I could put those in any order.
MySQL is designed so I
can do it in any order
and get the same result
forwards or backwards.
When I read this table, I might just
read it left to right here and kind of
get a feel for which constraints are
being applied in no particular order,
in this case.
AUDIENCE: Yeah, the second question
has to do with type affinity.
With SQLite we had
something like the type
affinity where a particular value is
appropriate for a particular role.
So is there anything like that in MySQL?
CARTER ZENKE: Yes, there is.
So in SQLite, you're right, we had type
affinities, where we defined a table
and said that this column should
store values of this type.
We're doing the very same thing in
MySQL when we say ID of type int
or the name of a station of
type varchar 16, for instance.
One difference though
is that SQLite will
allow you to add in some
value that doesn't actually
have the type of that given column.
So if I had a SQLite column of type
text or of type, let's say, type numeric
and I added some text,
it would try to convert.
But if it couldn't, it would
actually just store text.
MySQL is more strict than that.
It will make sure you
have the proper type when
you insert some new rows, at least
by default. OK, great questions here.
Let's keep going and show
some more features of MySQL.
So one of them is the ability to alter
tables in a more fundamental way.
So let me zoom back in here.
In SQLite we had some
options to alter tables.
But at the end of the day, they
just weren't all that powerful.
With MySQL, though, we're actually
able to alter tables a little bit
more fundamentally.
So let's say that the MBTA adds
in a new line, a new subway line.
And actually, the silver
line, if you can see it here,
is currently a bus line.
But it was planned to be a subway line.
So if I wanted to add in a subway
line called the silver line,
well, I can't currently do that because
my type for the lines is an enum.
It only has red, green,
blue, and orange, not silver.
So I should actually
edit this create table
to now be able to
include the silver line
as a possible value among that enum.
So I'll come back over here.
And I'll introduce you to
MySQL's alter table syntax.
So in MySQL we have still
alter table, similar to SQLite.
They're all based on the SQL standard.
But now we have modify, where modify
can take some column definition
and change it on the fly.
So I'll go to MySQL here.
And let me describe
again the stations table.
I'll hit Enter now.
And we'll see that the line is an enum.
And it has a few options,
blue, green, orange, and red.
But now I want to add silver here.
So what could I do?
I could do this.
I could use alter table.
And I could say, I want to alter table.
I want to alter the stations table.
And I want to modify.
I want to modify the
line column to be this.
I want it to be an enum with these
options, blue, green, orange, red,
and silver, like this.
Now I have more options in my enum.
I could also include
not null too, hit Enter.
And I should see--
oops, I think I might have
forgotten a quote somewhere.
I believe I did.
Let me fix this.
I will finish the quote, hit semicolon.
And let me show you how I noticed that.
If I go back to my screen here,
see in MySQL, it's kind of helpful.
If I finish a line and I haven't closed
this quote here, like I did in red,
it will alert me on this next line,
with this single quote here saying, hey,
you didn't close that thing that you
probably thought you were going to.
So let me restart.
I'll come back over here.
And I will try this again.
I will alter table stations.
And then I will modify the
line column, as we said before,
to be an enum with a
few different values,
blue, green, orange, red, closing
both quotes now, and then silver,
again closing both quotes.
And let me double check.
I believe we're all set.
I'll then say not
null, semicolon, Enter.
And I'll see the query is OK.
Now if I do describe stations,
like this, semicolon,
and zoom out just a bit, I see
I've added to my possible values
for this enum.
I have blue, green,
orange, red, and silver.
So this is one example of using alter
table to adjust a column definition.
To an earlier question, you could also
use this to expand the size of varchars
or to change your table all together.
You can do so a bit more
powerfully than you can
with SQLite, just because MySQL decided
to focus on this particular feature.
So let me ask now what questions we
have on altering tables in MySQL.
AUDIENCE: This is generally
regarding to MySQL and Postgres.
Can we use those applications
instead of v score
[INAUDIBLE] that user interface?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a good question.
So I think you're asking,
what would be the difference,
or how could I use MySQL and
Postgres compared with VS Code?
In effect, they're kind
of different use cases.
So VS Code, as you might know,
is an IDE, Integrated Development
Environment.
It allows you to write code
in a file, to run that code,
and to edit it and see
it all in one place.
Whereas MySQL and
PostgreSQL, those allow
you to write SQL statements
on a command line,
talking to some underlying server.
So a bit different.
You could, for example, use VS Code and
connect to a MySQL or PostgreSQL server
to run your SQL queries
you're creating in VS Code.
Good question there for workflows.
OK, so what we'll do is
take a quick break here.
And we'll come back and talk
about stored procedures,
some functions we can define to
run over, and over, and over again.
We'll see you in a few.
OK, and we're back.
Now we'll next talk
about stored procedures,
which are a way to automate
the running of SQL statements
over, and over, and over again.
This is useful as your scaling because
if you have some process you often
call, you can put it inside
of a stored procedure
and run it all the more simply.
So to demonstrate stored
procedures, what we'll do
is go back to our example
of the Museum of Fine Arts,
one of Boston's oldest
museums, also called the MFA.
And if you remember, in the
MFA, we had a certain number
of tables, where one of these
tables was a collections table.
It is the items the MFA has
in their collection, the items
they put on display, for instance.
Here we had a few pieces,
Farmers Working at Dawn,
Imaginative Landscape, and so on.
Each had their own ID.
And they also had a deleted column to
implement what we call a soft delete,
where to delete something
we wouldn't remove the row.
We would instead just mark this
deleted column from a 0 to a 1,
sort of hiding it or marking it as
having been deleted to keep data
around, not removing it all together.
Now to find all of the items
that weren't marked as deleted,
we could use this query, select
star from collections where
deleted equals 0, at least in SQLite.
Now, we then created a view.
We said, maybe I want to just always be
able to view those items that have not
been marked as deleted, one
table called current collections,
or one virtual table, a view
called current collections.
If I were to update Farmers Working
at Dawn to be marked as deleted,
what would happen?
This deleted column would become a 1.
And I would not see it
in current collection.
So our goal then is to
re-implement something like this,
but now not using a view.
In this case, using a
stored procedure, we
could simply call to find all the items
that have not been marked as deleted.
So to create a stored procedure,
we have some syntax we can use.
And that syntax looks a bit like this.
We could say create procedure
and give it some name.
Well, this procedure we could
call maybe current collections,
being able to view what is inside our
collection and not marked as deleted.
We could then, similar
to a trigger, say begin
after which we say the SQL statements we
want to run as part of this procedure.
So begin, we then type the
SQL statements we want to run,
and finally say end, this
is the end of our procedure.
And then later on, we could
use a statement called call
to call this procedure
over and over again.
So let's work on creating our
very first stored procedure
to find all the items in our
collection that have not been deleted.
Well, I'll go back to my MySQL server.
And I'll show you a new
database I've made here.
I can type show databases semicolon.
And now I should see I have not
just the default MySQL databases.
I also have the MFA database.
So if I type use MFA semicolon,
I should see database changed.
Now all my future queries
will run on this MFA database.
And so I could type show tables to see
all the tables inside of this database.
Hit Enter.
And I'll see I have artists,
collections, and created.
I could even if I wanted to
describe the collections table,
describe collections semicolon.
And now I'll see the description
for this collections table here.
I have an ID, title, accession number
column, and an acquired column too.
But what am I missing?
I want to be able to
implement soft deletes.
If you were to look at
this describe output,
what am I missing if I want
to implement soft deletes?
AUDIENCE: You're missing
the deleted column.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, the deleted
column is not yet in this table.
I know because I use describe here.
So I don't have deleted yet.
But I can add it using alter table.
So I'll come back to my computer.
And let me use alter table to
add in this particular column.
I could say alter table
collections, like this.
And then I could use add column.
Modify was good for modifying
a column that already existed.
Add column is good for
adding a brand new column.
I'll call this one deleted.
And its type will actually
be a tiny int, a tiny int.
Why?
Well, it's only ever going to be 1 or 0.
I should use as few bits as possible.
And tiny int gives that to me.
Now I'll say the default
value is 0 for not deleted.
And I'll hit Enter.
And now if I describe
collections again, I
should see that I'm back to
having a deleted column of type
tiny int with a default value of 0.
OK, so now, we saw I
could select everything
from collections that's not deleted
by saying something like select star
from collections where deleted equals 0.
I can implement the same thing here, but
now using a stored procedure, something
I could call again, and
again, and again to speed up
this process just a little bit.
So I'll say I want to create this
procedure, current collections.
But there's something a little
interesting about the MySQL syntax
here.
If you remember, if I
go back to some slides
here, in the middle of
begin and end, we're
going to put our very own SQL statements
to run as part of this procedure.
Well, to end a SQL statement,
we have to have a semicolon.
But MySQL might actually
prematurely end this statement.
If I type quit procedure name begin
some statement then a semicolon,
it'll say, OK, you're done.
But I'm actually not.
I might want to add more statements.
I might want to conclude
with this end down here.
So a workaround is to temporarily
declare a different delimiter.
Instead of ending my queries
with a semicolon here,
I'll end them with,
let's say, slash slash.
And we'll see that in
just a moment here.
I'll come back to my computer.
And for the sake of
writing this procedure,
I'll change my delimiter, that is what
icon represents the end of my query
to slash slash, like this.
Then I'll hit Enter.
Now I can start creating my procedure.
I'll say create procedure.
And I'll call this one current
collections with a open and closed
parentheses after this.
This is common for names here.
Then I'll say begin this procedure.
And in this procedure, I want to
select the title, accession number,
and acquired columns.
I want to do it from the collections
table, where deleted equals 0.
And now I can safely include a
semicolon because my delimiter
for this entire query is a slash slash.
So this is the end of this
particular query inside my procedure.
It's also the end of my
procedure in general.
And now to declare the
end of this procedure,
the end of this overarching
statement, I could
say slash slash instead of semicolon.
Now, if I hit Enter, I'll see query OK.
And now I should change back
to, in this case, semicolon,
so I can get back to what I'm
used to using to end my queries.
I'll hit Enter.
And now let's see what we can do.
I could say call current collection.
I think we called it
collection, singular.
And I'll say this, semicolon there.
Now, I should see all of the items
that are marked as not deleted.
So using call, can I then call this
procedure I've made and stored?
Let's try deleting something.
I'll try maybe deleting
Farmers Working at Dawn.
I could say update, in this case,
collections and set deleted equal to 1
where the title equals Farmers
Working at Dawn, semicolon.
I'll Enter again.
I'll see one row has changed.
If I call current collection
again, like this, semicolon Enter,
I'll see that particular
artwork is now gone.
It's not returned to me by the
query that was part of my procedure.
So this then is one example of a stored
procedure, one way of saving a query
and calling it again and again
if I might use it very often.
But what questions do we have
so far on stored procedures
and how we can use them?
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
Just like in other languages,
do we have the provisioning
that we can pass the parameters
and arguments in the function,
in the procedure as well, in MySQL?
And secondly, can we call other
procedures also in one procedure,
like in other languages we have
one function call from other?
CARTER ZENKE: A great question about
the power of stored procedures.
So the first question, could
I add parameters or arguments
to this procedure?
And could I change what
I do based on that input?
The answer is absolutely
yes, you can in MySQL.
And I'll show you that
in just a minute here.
The next one, which is, can I call
other procedures inside my procedure?
Yes to that as well.
Any statement you might write, you
could probably put in a procedure too.
OK, let's take one more.
AUDIENCE: Yes, I have a question.
There is any way that I can add
any note or comment to the table?
CARTER ZENKE: Can you add any
note or comment to your table?
A good intuition, like it's good
to include notes to yourself
or to include notes to others.
To my knowledge you would
best do that in something
like a schema dot SQL file.
If you have a text editor,
you could make a dot SQL file
and store your schema inside of that.
At which point, you could leave
comments to other developers
to make them know what you are
thinking as you were building this.
There might be a way to
leave comments in MySQL.
But I don't personally
know what that is.
You could do some research
to look that up too.
OK, great question.
Let's keep going then.
And to our question about
procedures and trying
to make sure they could have
inputs, let's see that as well.
Well, we saw too that I might want
to mark some particular item as sold
as soon as I mark it as being deleted.
So for that I'll need a new table here.
If I type show tables semicolon, I'll
see artists, collections, and created.
But back in our week on the
MFA, we also had a table
to keep track of transactions,
when we might buy and sell
some piece of artwork.
So let's recreate that table here.
I'll create a table called transactions,
create table transactions, like this.
And then I'll give it an ID column
with the type int and auto increment.
Then I'll give it a title to
mark as being sold or bought.
Let's say the title is a
varchar of size up to 64.
And it can't be null.
Then I'll say the action,
which can be either bought
or sold-- did we buy or sell this piece
of artwork with this particular title?
So I'll say this is an enum with
the possibility of bought or sold.
Then I'll say this is not null.
And I'll then say the primary
key of this table is ID.
And I'll close out this create
table statement here hitting Enter.
Now I can see I have a transactions
table to log the buying
and selling of pieces of artwork.
Well, it stands to reason that when
I update my collections table and I
set some item to be deleted from
a 0 to a 1 in that deleted column,
I want to add it to the transactions
table and also mark it as sold.
So normally, that is two
steps, updating the table
and also adding it to transactions.
With a procedure though, I could
give that entire sequence one name.
So let's try that here.
I'll say I want to make
my delimiter slash slash.
I'm going to create some procedure here.
I'm going to end it with slash slash.
So I'll say create procedure.
And I'll call this one sell, like this.
But now instead of open
parentheses and closed parentheses,
I actually want to give
some input to this function.
And let me actually ask you
all here, what kind of input
should I give to this
sell function, so I can
identify the painting I want to sell?
AUDIENCE: It should
be with a primary key
and refer to the name of
the painting probably.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
I like your thinking.
We could think about what
identifies this artwork.
Maybe it's the ID or the title.
In this case, I like your intuition
for the ID, which is unique,
will never change.
So let's actually use the ID here
of an item in the collections table
to mark it as sold.
So I'll come back to my computer.
And I'll say that sell
actually takes an input.
And I can say in here to
note a value as an input.
I'll say the input is something called
sold ID, the item we're selling.
And the type of this
is an int, like this.
So now I have a procedure that takes in
some value in integer called sold ID.
Now, I'll say let's
begin this procedure.
Let's begin down below.
And the first thing I should do
is update collections, like this,
and set deleted equal to
1 under what condition?
Well, perhaps under the condition where
the ID is equal to our input, which
is called sold ID.
So I'm using the input of sold
ID to find in collections which
artwork I'm marking now as deleted.
But the next step--
I'll say semicolon
here to end that step--
is to then insert it into
the transactions table.
I've marked it as being deleted.
But now I need to insert
into transactions.
I'll say then I want to insert into
transactions in the title and action
columns some values here.
Well, what values?
The first value is actually
the title of this artwork.
And I only have the ID right now.
But I could use the ID
to get back the title.
I could say write a
subquery that is select,
in this case, title from collections
where the ID equals sold,
sold ID like this.
That is a subquery that gives me
back the title of this artwork.
Now, I'll also log sold here, like this.
And then I think that's the end
for that particular query there.
Let me just double check this,
insert into transactions,
title, action, value, select
title from collections
where ID equals sold ID, sold.
OK, I think we're good.
I'll hit Enter on that.
And then I think I can
safely end my procedure.
I'll say end here slash
slash, Enter again.
I see everything was OK.
So now if I change my
delimiter back to a semicolon,
I can call sell on some particular ID.
Like let's say I now want
to sell the particular item.
I could say maybe select star from
collections to see what I have.
And now I want to sell Imaginative
Landscape, which has the ID of 2.
Well, I could try call sell and now
pass in that value 2, call sell 2.
And if I now hit Enter, I should
see some rows were affected.
This procedure worked.
Let me check.
I'll say select star from
collections semicolon.
And I'll see that piece
now has been updated.
Its value was 0.
But now it's 1 for the deleted column.
Now if I say select star
from transactions semicolon,
I'll then see Imaginative
Landscape being sold here as well.
So good check here.
And I'll actually just check on this.
So I think the ID was 2.
And that actually makes sense here.
So the ID we're thinking about
[INAUDIBLE] and is different here.
So this is the ID of
the transaction, which
is different than the idea
of the painting, which is 2,
just to clarify that.
OK, so what other questions then
do we have on stored procedures?
We've seen some without
inputs, now some with inputs.
What else are you wondering?
AUDIENCE: Is it possible to pass in
multiple inputs to a stored procedure?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, could
it have multiple inputs?
It absolutely could separated by some
commas inside of those parentheses.
So you could imagine in sold ID
int comma some other input as well.
And a procedure can
also output some value.
You could say I want to store
the result in some variable I
could keep track of in the server too.
Let's keep going then.
And we'll kind of end stored procedures
on this note here, which is I seem to--
if I go back to what I
had discussed before,
I was able to update some
item in my collections table
and then add it to the
transactions table too.
So if I say select star from
collections, there is some danger here.
Like if I try to sell something
that has already been sold,
I might run the procedure and mark
something as being sold twice.
Now, I'll actually leave this
up to you as your own exercise.
But I want to give you a
few tools to think about
for writing your own procedures.
Among them are some
constructs you might be
familiar with if you've
programmed before.
So here you might notice a
stored procedure can actually
be compatible with some familiar
programming syntax, like conditions,
for example, if, else if,
and else, and also loops,
like the ability to do
something more than once
or to repeat something over,
and over, and over again.
So you can use these to really
build up your own stored procedures
to combine statements and
automate processes that you're
going to do very frequently on
your database at large scale.
So we've seen here some
options for stored procedures.
What we'll do is come back
and talk next about Postgres.
See you in a few.
And we're back.
So we've seen so far MySQL, which
is a new DBMS that [INAUDIBLE]
just a bit more than
SQLite at a larger scale.
It's worth also taking a
brief detour into Postgres
just to get a taste for
what it looks like and get
an understanding for
how it can represent
some of these same tables
in a different environment.
So we'll talk here about Postgres.
And our goal will be to do the same
thing we did with MySQL, converting
our tables from SQLite over
to Postgres taking advantage
of some new types and
some new affordances
it might offer that are
particular to Postgres itself.
So here then is our table
we used for cards in SQLite,
just to remind you again.
We had an ID column of type integer.
And that was our primary key.
What we saw in MySQL, we
had a variety of integers.
And here we actually have
the same thing in Postgres.
But they just look a little
bit slightly different.
So here I have a table of integers in
Postgres, the signed and signed values
over here going from
negative to positive.
So unlike MySQL, which
had tiny int, medium int,
and so on, in Postgres we only
have small int, int, and big int,
just a little bit fewer options
because the developers thought
you might not need a
tiny int or medium int,
just give you three particular options.
Now although there are
fewer integer options,
we also get something
a little bit different.
I can also use a serial type, small
serial, serial, or big serial.
Now, a serial is still an
integer, a whole number.
But it actually does what we try to
do in MySQL for me, which was try
to include an auto increment attribute.
A serial will automatically
increment for me,
making it good for primary keys.
So here, if I go back
to my cards table, and I
had this ID column of
type integer, I could
update that to now be a serial, where
a serial means some whole integer
number that will increase as I add
more and more data to my table.
Now, what else do you notice here?
Well, it seems like these double
quotes are back in Postgres.
So in MySQL you had back ticks.
In SQLite you had double quotes.
Well, in Postgres you have double
quotes for your identifiers here.
So this then is how we've
changed our cards table.
And now let's actually do
this inside of Postgres.
I'll log in and create my very
own database and my own table.
So I'll come back to my computer here.
And now let me do this.
I will log in to Postgres
using this command right here.
I'm going to open PSQL, which is
essentially the command line interface,
like MySQL, but now just for Postgres.
I'll hit Enter here.
And I'll log in as the
default Postgres user.
This is the admin for Postgres now.
I'll type in my password.
And I'll see a prompt.
It looks just a little bit different,
but the same kind of spirit here.
If I want to list all databases,
I don't type show databases.
I just type backslash l for list.
And I'll Enter here.
And now I'll see a collection
of default databases
that come with the
Postgres installation.
Similar to MySQL, these
are databases that
contain configuration
information, metadata
on this installation of Postgres.
But now I want to create my
own database, one called MBTA.
So I'll say create
database, same as before,
and call it MBTA now
using double quotes.
If I hit Enter now, I should see create
database, confirming this statement.
And if I type backslash
l I'll now see MBTA
is included in my list of databases.
So if I want to connect to a
database, in MySQL I used use.
In Postgres I'll use backslash C.
So I'll say backslash C
and then MBTA, hit Enter.
And now I'm connected
to the database MBTA
as this user whose name is Postgres.
And now if I want to see
what tables I already
have, I could type
backslash dt, hit Enter.
And I'll see no relations, no tables,
but just another way of figuring out
this is an empty database.
So we've seen so far how to log in to
Postgres and some basic navigational
statements we can use to work
our way around this database.
But it turns out there is some
stuff that's familiar here.
Like if I want to create
a new table, I can do it
the very same way I did it before.
I could use create table.
I could say create
table, let's say, cards.
And then let me include,
in this case, an ID
column of type serial, which means an
integer that auto increments for me.
Then I'll apply the primary key
constraint, familiar old friend here.
Then I'll close out cards,
like this, hit Enter.
And I should see it confirms
I created this table.
If I now type slash
dt to list my tables,
I'll see I have a table called cards.
And if I want to look at this table in
particular to understand its schema,
I could type slash d and
the name of that table,
cards, like this, hit Enter.
And now I should see some more
information on this cards table.
It has a column called ID, a type called
integer, and some more information
like we saw in MySQL, but now
just in a different format.
So not to worry.
If these commands seem maybe
arcane to you at first glance,
you'll get used to it with
some practice if you choose
to learn either MySQL or Postgres here.
So let me pause before we go any further
and just ask, what questions so far
do we have on Postgres, if any?
AUDIENCE: What's the sort of thing
that indicates there's an error?
CARTER ZENKE: A good question.
So similar to SQLite
or MySQL, you'll know
you have an error when you hit Enter
and it doesn't say either query
OK or ptu, that command you just used.
It might give you a particular
error, like maybe you forgot a comma,
maybe you forgot a quote somewhere.
It should of give you
an idea of what you
didn't do correctly with the syntax.
The best way to see it is to try it and
figure out what it tells you as you go.
OK, let's keep going then.
And we'll see a few differences
between Postgres and MySQL too.
So we have our cards table.
But our other goal is to
create a stations table.
So let me pull up what
we did for this one.
Let me find stations here.
So this was our stations table with
Postgres, or sorry, with SQLite.
We had an ID, a name, and a line
column, integer, text, and text
for those types.
Now we've seen in Postgres I could
change this integer for my primary key
to be a serial.
That's a little more apt
for this use case here.
And it turns out that in Postgres I
also have varchars I could use inside
of this stations table.
I could make name a varchar
here up to size 32 characters.
And for simplicity, though
we used an enum earlier,
I'll now use a varchar for line as
well just to keep things simple.
So here we've updated our stations table
using what Postgres might offer us.
The real differences though
come not in our stations table
but actually inside of our other
table, this one called swipes.
So this here was our swipes
table, or some section of it.
We had IDs up top and primary key and
foreign key constraints down below.
Now remember, we had type of text, date
time of numeric, and amount of numeric
as well.
Well, Postgres offers some other types
we could use to update these as well.
Among them are enum,
our old friend again.
But we use enum a
little bit differently.
So instead of including enum
inside of our column definition,
we actually create our very own type.
Postgres supports something like this.
Create a type and give it some name.
And then I could say what
that type actually is.
So here I've created some type and
called it swipe type and then said,
this type can have the following
values, enter, exit, or deposit.
And I can then use this name, swipe
type, as my very own type in future
create table statements, so something
that Postgres has that MySQL might not
in this form.
Let's consider then dates and times.
So dates and times, largely similar.
I have timestamp, date,
time, and interval,
a particular type representing
the distance between times,
how long did something take?
But we still have our old friend's
date and time for dates and times
respectively, and also timestamp
to combine these two into one.
And then we also have
precision with these.
I could say I want to represent to
the hundreds place, the thousands
place, or so on for each of
timestamp, time, and interval.
Continuing on, we could also
work with real numbers, which
are largely the same amenities
between MySQL and Postgres
with a few differences.
One is that at least in Postgres
we call decimal numeric.
So numeric in this case can
specify some precision, that
is the number of digits,
and the scale, that
is the number that come
after the decimal point.
And newer to Postgres is a
type particularly for money,
which depending on your
settings in your database
will put to you either a
certain number of decimal points
and include perhaps a dollar sign,
or a euro sign, or a pound sign,
whatever it is you're
using and whatever it
is you've configured in your database.
So let's update now.
Let's go ahead and improve
this statement in swipes
from SQLite to Postgres.
Here, I had type.
Well, that could now be
our very own swipe type.
Notice here I defined
up above as an enum.
Now I'm going to use it down
below in my swipes table.
This type column has
the type swipe type.
And it cannot be null.
Then I'll keep going.
And I'll make datetime just timestamp.
Timestamp is the newer
version in Postgres
of what MySQL had called date time
and what SQLite called numeric.
And then instead of, let's
say, current timestamp,
Postgres just uses this function
called now, the current timestamp it
will get for as you add some new row.
And then finally, amount,
we could use money.
We could use numeric.
We'll stick in this case to just
numeric, like we did for MySQL
and say numeric up to five digits, two
of which come after the decimal point.
So a whirlwind tour of some differences
in types between MySQL and Postgres.
What questions do we have on these?
I'm not seeing too many here.
Let me keep going.
I'll come back to my computer here.
So it's worth showing that
we're able to create a table.
We can then show it and
describe it like this.
But then the question remains,
how do you get out of Postgres?
Well, for that you can use-- let me
clear my screen-- simply slash q.
Whereas in MySQL you could use quit.
In Postgres it's slash q.
So I'll hit Enter on this.
And we'll say goodbye
to Postgres for now.
But after the break, we'll come
back and keep working with MySQL
and focus on actually what features we
can use to scale up our applications.
What does MySQL and Postgres offer
to serve more users, more frequently?
Back in a few.
And we're back.
So we've gotten a taste so far
of both MySQL and Postgres.
But now it's time to think
through the features each
offers to scale up our application.
So let's envision a sample application
here, one that starts off pretty small.
We have users trying to read from this
database about 100 times per minute.
But they're also
writing to the database,
adding new data about
50 times per minute.
And maybe this application over
time it grows a little bit.
Maybe instead of 100 reads, it goes
up to 1,000 and multiplies by 10,
and same thing for our writes.
They also multiply on
average by about 10.
And this application, it gets even more
popular, increases by 10-fold again.
Now we have 10,000 reads per
minute, 5,000 writes per minute.
And then finally, it keeps
growing another 10-fold.
And now we're at 100,000 reads per
minute and 50,000 writes per minute.
What might be the problem?
If I had a single server, like
this, why might my application
start to slow down?
AUDIENCE: So yeah, I would like to
say that whenever the requests are
increasing with the time to which the
server would reply will also increase.
And the list would
seem to grow on and on.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I
like your thinking there.
So you can think of the
time that each query takes.
As we saw in our optimizing
lecture, we could time our queries.
And if I have many, many, many of
those queries running all at one time,
I mean that could add up substantially.
So it's worth thinking about
whether one computer can really
handle all of these reads
and all of these writes.
So if you find yourself
writing some application
and it behaves a little bit slower than
you want it to, particularly at scale,
you have a few options.
And I want to ask you just to
use your own intuition here.
Like if you encountered this problem
of your application slowing down,
what might you try to do
to solve that problem?
AUDIENCE: You could try
to optimize your queries.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, try
to optimize your queries,
make sure they take a little
less time than before.
Or you could even try to throw
more hardware at the problem.
Like maybe you have
optimized your queries
to the maximum you think you can.
And it's just still not fast enough.
Well, one approach might be
what's called vertical scaling,
trying to make this single
server all the more quicker
at replying to your queries.
So vertical scaling is about
increasing your application's capacity
by increasing the capacity of
a single server, the computing
power of that server.
So whereas this was our
regular, old server,
you could imagine trying to
vertically scale this server
just making it more powerful,
optimize your queries
and have them run on this server
faster than they did before.
But there's also another
approach you could take.
Here we focused on one server.
But what else could you logically
do to just have more resources
at your disposal?
AUDIENCE: Maybe we can
horizontally scale up the server.
We can add two or three more
servers so we can manage it.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
I like your thinking.
So maybe we buy a
fancier server like this.
But if we ever run out of
this server's capacity,
well the only logical thing
is to buy more servers.
Like let's have not just
one, but three for instance.
And this is an example
of horizontal scaling.
So horizontal scaling is increasing
your application's capacity
not by increasing a single
server's computing power,
but by spreading it
out, buying more servers
to handle that load across
more, in this case, individuals,
people who can do work on those queries.
So horizontal scaling might
look a bit more like this.
We have not just one server,
but now three overall.
So this process of having not
just one server, but multiple,
it's a process called replication.
So replication is keeping copies of
your database not just on one server,
but on multiple.
And this seems like a good idea.
Like wouldn't it be great to have a
copy of your data not just in one place,
but in multiple?
Maybe you yourself have made a backup
of your own data on your computer.
This is not a dissimilar idea.
But it turns out there are
some challenges with this.
Like it's very complicated to have
servers communicate with themselves
to keep track of who has the
most recent updates, who should
I follow, who should lead, and so on.
And so for that reason, there
are a few models of replication
that you should at least know about.
Among them are single-leader
replication, multi-leader replication,
and leaderless replication.
So single-leader means that there is
a single database server out there
that takes in the incoming writes to an
application, the updates to some data.
And that single server
passes them on to some copy
to take care of making
sure it's redundant,
that this data is stored not just in
one place, but multiple places too.
Multi-leader means there's not just
one server listening for updates.
There are multiple.
And suffice to say, it
gets a lot more complicated
when there are more than one
leader trying to listen for updates
and process them.
And finally, there are some other
ones, like leaderless and some more,
that actually do away
with leaders altogether
and do something totally different.
But today will focus on single-leader,
one of the most basic application
strategies you could try and
one that is built into MySQL.
So let's focus on this one here.
You could imagine, in this
case, that you have a computer.
And you're trying to connect
to some social network.
Well, here are two databases.
One is a leader.
And one is a follower.
And just to check for
understanding here,
let's say I want to
upload a profile photo.
I'm updating some data.
To which server would I send that data?
If I want to change
something on the server,
who's listening for that request?
AUDIENCE: I think that
we'll send to the leader
because the other servers
would get data from the leader.
They would get it from the leader.
But I will send to the leader
because it will have the latest
data for other servers and other users.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, exactly right.
So if I want to change
some piece of data,
I know by definition the leader has
the most recent copy of that data
and is also the designated server
to process updates to my database,
changes to its data, like
insertions, or updates, or deletions.
So if I'm uploading some profile
photo, I'll send this photo of me
right here to my leader.
And that leader will then
take that profile photo
and store it on the database.
But before long, the leader will also
talk to, communicate with the follower
and make sure that the follower
has a copy of this data elsewhere.
So it will forward on this
update to the follower
who will then process it in turn.
And now that both the leader and
the follower have this data, well,
who could I ask to see the latest
profile photo for Carter Zenke?
Which server might have that?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
servers that have the data.
CARTER ZENKE: So I could ask
either server for information
on this profile photo.
I could ask either the leader
or the follower because each
is storing a copy of this photo,
or rather a copy of its location
on the server itself.
Now let's say here I asked the
follower for this profile photo
so I can see it on my own browser.
Here, I'll ask the follower and get back
that image inside of my own browser.
But I could have asked
either one to distribute
that load across both of these servers.
Now, this follower is what's
known as a read replica.
A read replica is a server from
which we would only ever read data.
If I ever wanted to update some
photo or insert some new rows,
I would never ask the follower.
I would always ask the leader
who's in charge, so to speak,
of handling these updates and
these writes to that database.
So the next step is to think about not
just the types of leaders that we have,
but also how they communicate.
And in general, there are two options
for communication, both synchronous
and asynchronous.
So synchronous means
that the leader will
wait for the follower to
get the data and process it
before doing anything else.
It synchronizes with that follower.
Asynchronous though, means the leader
sends that data to the follower
and doesn't wait for the
follower to finish processing.
It just keeps going and going,
hoping the follower is keeping up.
So let's focus first on a few of
these, in particular on synchronous.
Now, in this diagram, I
have a client and a server.
My client is my computer.
The server is some database.
And on this x-axis here,
left to right, I have time.
Well, if I want to make
a request to this server,
I might denote that
with a line, like this.
My client sends some
request to my server.
Maybe it asks for data or
tries to update some photo.
Then that takes some time to get the
request from my client to this server
down here.
And the response itself
also takes some time.
Maybe the server responds,
hey, everything's OK.
I got your photo.
Here's your data, et cetera.
It'll take some time for
that to get back to me.
So between here and
here, that's how long
it took for me to receive
some data from this server.
Now let's focus on
synchronous replication
here, where the leader and the
follower are always in sync.
So this might look a bit like this.
If I add in the follower, I now
have a leader and a follower.
I might send that profile photo
to the leader, a bit like this.
The leader then sends it to the
follower down below and waits.
It waits until the
follower has confirmed
they have received that photo.
They have added to the database.
And now they send back a
request saying, look, I got it.
Everything is OK.
And now only at this
point, once the leader
has received the OK from the follower,
does it then communicate with me.
It then says, everything's OK.
We got your photo.
So this is great because it's redundant.
Like I know for sure that my photo is
on both the leader and the follower.
But there is a downside.
And looking at this diagram here, what
do you think that downside might be?
AUDIENCE: Maybe it's too slow.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, exactly.
It could be just too slow.
Like if I have to wait for the follower
to get the OK back to the leader
and then back to me, that's
just more time for me to wait.
And maybe my application
shouldn't wait around that long.
You might use this, though, if you're
working in finance or healthcare, where
you have to be doubly sure you have data
stored exactly as you want it to be.
But if you're like a social media
site, like a Facebook or a Twitter,
I mean, maybe you don't care if you
lose a tweet every once in a while.
It's OK.
So maybe synchronous isn't the best,
most ideal scenario for that as well.
So let's think through now asynchronous.
So we'll go back to asynchronous here
and think through our diagram again.
Well, in asynchronous, the
leader doesn't wait around
for the follower to get the data.
So to visualize, my
client could send this
to the leader, maybe a
photo update, for example.
Then simultaneously, the leader tells
me, I got your photo, everything's OK,
and then sends the
photo to the follower.
The follower might later on tell
the leader that everything is OK.
But the leader already told me,
look, all good, we got your photo.
So there's nothing
more to do after this.
Now, this admittedly is faster.
Like this amount of
time is much shorter.
But again, there is some downside here.
Why might I not want to use asynchronous
replication, at least in some cases?
AUDIENCE: I would guess
that it's an issue with data
being corrupted by someone?
CARTER ZENKE: So you're right.
There could be some
data corruption here,
where let's say the leader
sends some data to the follower.
And they confirm for me
that data has been received
across all instances of these servers.
Well, I mean, later on maybe the
follower encounters some problem.
And they don't actually follow through.
Well, at that point, I have had
a bad contract with my leader.
It told me everything was OK.
But actually, it wasn't.
So there are all kinds of trade offs
here, whether in terms of the time
that things take or redundancy.
But it's up to you to
decide which one might
work best for your own use
case, synchronous replication
or asynchronous.
Now, in addition to replication, there
is some other strategy for scaling
you should be at least familiar with.
And this is a process known as sharding.
Now, sharding is great
for really large data
sets on the order of many, many,
many gigabytes or terabytes of data
that you just can't fit on a
single server or a single computer.
Sharding involves taking
some data set like that
and essentially splitting it up in some
logical way across multiple servers,
like this.
And maybe for simplicity you
have some database of names.
And you decide that all of those names
that begin with, let's say, A to I
end up on this server
here, this first one.
But then all those names J through R,
well, they get stored on this server
here.
And S through Z, they get stored
on this third server here.
So our data has been split, or
sharded, across multiple instances
of some database server.
And this is helpful because if
I had a really large data set,
it now is smaller on every
individual database server.
You could also organize your
data by, let's say, primary key.
Maybe you have 3,000
rows, or 3,000 records.
And the first 1 through 1,000,
those go on this first server.
The second, 1,001 to 2,000 inclusive,
those go on the second server.
And 2,001 to 3,000 also inclusive,
those go on that third server.
Now, there's a lot of thought that goes
behind the best way to shard your data.
The goal is to really to avoid what we
call a hotspot, wherein one database
server becomes more frequently
accessed or requested than others.
Let's say for some reason
the data in 1,001 to 2,000
gets accessed quite a lot.
Well, now we're actually
trying to run into a problem
here where one server gets
overloaded, the same problem we're
trying to guard against using sharding.
So it's important then
to think about what's
the best, most logical way to
distribute your data so you
don't have one server being
accessed much more than another.
And there's another problem here too,
which is if I'm not using replication,
I'm only using sharding, well,
let's say that one server goes down.
What do we have now?
Maybe we're missing all the names that
went to the middle of our partition.
Or maybe we're missing
all of those rows,
let's see, 1,001 to 2,000 for instance.
And that would be what we call
a single point of failure.
If one system goes down, our
entire system is now not usable.
So something to keep in mind
as you work on sharding is also
could combine it with some
strategies from replication
to keep copies of your
data across servers too.
So these are some features built
into MySQL and Postgres for scaling.
But they also give us user accounts.
And we can perhaps enhance our
security by taking advantage
of some of those user accounts.
So let's talk now about
this idea of access control,
trying to have users and only grant
some of them certain permissions.
So here we saw before I was logging
into MySQL using the root user.
The root user is the admin.
But I could just as
easily create a new user,
perhaps one called Carter for myself.
So I will open up MySQL again.
And in this case, I will create
a new user, one named Carter.
So to do so, I can
use this command here,
this statement here, create a user
whose name is Carter in single quotes.
Now, I can say they are
identified by the password.
And this password is literally
password, P-A-S-S-W-O-R-D.
It is one of, unfortunately,
the most popular passwords.
Do not use this password.
So I will hit Enter here.
And now I have created
some new user named Carter.
And I can log in using
that Carter username.
So I'll create myself
a new terminal here.
And I will try to log in to MySQL again.
I will run this statement here.
I'll say MySQL, which is the command
line interface for the MySQL server.
And I will say I want to
connect using this user, Carter.
Before we used root.
But now I'll use Carter.
The host, the place the server is
located, is 127.0.0.1, my own computer
here.
This is the IP for this very computer.
I can then say dash P, capital P,
for the port number, 3306 by default.
And finally, dash P means
prompt me for my password.
I'll type it in here.
So I'll hit Enter.
And now I get prompted for the password.
I'll type that in here.
And now-- oh wait, I typed
in the wrong password.
So let me try this again.
I'll go back up.
And I will type in my password,
which was password, hit Enter.
And now I'm logged in as Carter.
So by default, if I try something
like this, show databases Enter,
I'll only see a few.
Like I'm pretty sure I had MBTA
and MFA in here and a few others.
But I just can't see them.
So when I create this
new user, by default
it has very few privileges, very
few ways of accessing this database.
But I could decide to
grant some privileges.
And just to show you, let me
be root again for a second.
Here I'm the admin.
I can do most anything I want.
And notice how in here
I have a new database.
I can type show databases Enter.
And I'll see I have
a new database called
rideshare, which is similar from a
prior week on viewing and security.
So if I say use rideshare
semicolon Enter,
I could say select star
from rideshare semicolon.
Whoops, sorry, the
table wasn't rideshare.
Select star from rides.
Then I'll Enter here.
And now I'll see all of the
rides in the rides table, which
is part of the rideshare database.
And if I look at this table,
in our week on viewing,
we talked about eliminating some PII,
personally identifiable information.
What was that PII here?
Seems it was the rider column,
like the names of those riders.
We know where each rider is going.
But ideally we should
make a new view, one
that allows us to see not the
riders, but only their origins
and destinations, removing
this PII of individuals' names.
So by default, Carter
can't see this data.
But neither can Carter see the
view I made called analysis.
If I go back to my computer
here, I could type select star
from analysis, hit semicolon Enter.
And now I'll see the view I had
made, the virtual table that
removes that PII.
But here I'm logged in as a root.
If Carter wants to see this, I
go over here, show databases,
I can't even see the rideshare database.
So the root user needs to grant access
to Carter to see this particular view.
Now, for that, I can use some syntax
that looks a bit like this here.
I can use both grant and revoke.
Grant means to give some privilege,
like select, or update, or delete
on some table to a particular user.
Revoke means simply to
remove that permission.
If I gave you select before, I'll
now revoke it down below like this.
And there are many
privileges you can use.
You could use all, like
everything, allow Carter
to do literally everything he could do.
There's create to create
tables, and views, and so on.
There's insert to add data, select to
read, and all the way down this list.
Look at documentation to figure
out what you can use here.
So I want to give Carter it seems
like a select privilege on the view I
created for analysis in this database.
So I'll come back over here.
And I'll try that.
I will log in as root here.
And I will try to grant
the select permission
privilege on the rideshare
database, and in particular,
the analysis table inside of it.
And I'll grant that to Carter,
like this, semicolon and Enter.
Now I'll see the query is OK.
If I log back in as Carter down here,
and now type show databases Enter,
I should see I can now see
the rideshare database.
So I'll type use rideshare semicolon.
The database changed.
I could say show tables.
And what do I see but that virtual
table, that view called analysis.
So now as Carter I can select
star from analysis semicolon
and see that same data.
But I can't see the ride data.
If I say select star from rides,
that table is currently hidden to me.
I get back, you don't have permission.
So this is the benefit of
MySQL's users and privileges
to make sure I can have multiple
users accessing this database
and then only allowing some
to access confidential data.
So let me ask now what questions
we have on access control
in MySQL and Postgres.
AUDIENCE: If we have to
ask a test for everything,
is there any particular syntax for that?
Or should we type on all the
select drive and everything?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, great question here.
Like if you want to give somebody
multiple privileges, what could you do?
One approach is you could say
grant and then say the privilege,
and then have a comma afterwards.
I could grant select comma
insert comma et cetera,
including the tables that this user can
insert, update, delete on, et cetera.
You could also use all.
Like if I say grant all on
star dot star to Carter,
that means grant all permissions on
everything to this user named Carter.
So you can absolutely do
either of those approaches.
But best to be more fine
grained particularly
in a production environment.
OK, great questions here.
Let's keep going.
So this then was how
to use access controls.
But it's also worth thinking about ways
we can prevent other kinds of attacks
and harden the security of our database.
Like here I have users and
passwords, which works well.
But if I were to expose my
application to the outside world,
I should also be concerned
about a few other attacks here.
Now, one of these attacks
is a SQL injection attack.
SQL injection means I have some query.
And somebody else adds in some malicious
code to finish that query for me.
So for example, maybe I have a query
like this, select ID from the users
table where the username
equals someone's username
and the password equals
somebody's password.
And if I find a user matching
this username and password,
if I get back an ID,
I'll log that user in.
Now, in a regular website of someone
who's actually behaving nicely,
they could type in their
username, like this.
And they could type in their
password a bit like this.
This is kind of what I did before.
I logged in as Carter and
gave the password of password.
And when you are entering your
own username and your own password
on some website, something similar
to this is likely happening.
There might be some SQL query that takes
your username and takes your password
and inserts them into a
SQL query to figure out,
are you who you say you are?
But let's think a bit more
maliciously about this.
Like here, if I gave you permission to
add anything to this dot dot dot here,
anything at all, what
could you do to try to hack
this database, to log in as Carter?
Keep in mind that this is
selecting an ID from users
where some condition is true.
What might you be able to add to
this dot dot dot to log in as me?
AUDIENCE: Yes, you could
use some kind of statements
like union, or [INAUDIBLE],, or
delete something, et cetera.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I could really
put most anything I want in here.
But the SQL injection attack comes
about when I deliberately put some SQL
statement that I think will give
me access to some data I shouldn't
have access to.
So you could imagine maybe
I type in my password.
But then I type in a single
quote followed by or 1 equals 1.
Now, what would that do?
Well, notice that 1 equals 1, that
condition will always be true.
And so this condition,
where username equals
Carter and password equals
password, well, in that case,
I have access to Carter's
account because I
modified the condition just
always be true whether or not
the password is correct.
Let's see one more example here.
Maybe I'm logging into my bank account.
And I want to check my balance.
We could maybe assume that the
bank has some table of balances
or has some table of
accounts that have balances.
And I could type in my account number,
like this, one, two, three, four,
all the way up to number nine here.
And that will give me access
to my account balance.
But now, let's take a
look at this query here,
select balance from accounts where
ID equals the account number.
What kinds of SQL statements could
you include in this ID value here
to get access to everyone's
account balances?
AUDIENCE: So we basically have
a web which there's some ID.
If we just commented that part out,
then it would be sort of a problem.
Or if we just did a similar example
to the last time, like put the or 1
is equal to 1, that
could also trigger it.
So there are multiple options.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I
like your thinking here.
There's definitely more than one option.
I like your thinking of
maybe we include some comment
that kind of messes up this query.
Maybe it removes the condition so I
just get select balance from accounts.
That could be one strategy.
I could maybe include an
or that maybe makes sure
that this where is just
always true, give me back all
balances from this account.
I could also use as
well a union like this.
I could say make sure I add my
own account ID but then union
some other query like this,
union select ID from accounts.
Now I have all the account
IDs from this table.
And I could then query them one
at a time for their balance.
So let's try this out in MySQL to see
some of the dangers of these injection
attacks.
I'll go back to my computer here.
And I'll show you how I already
have a database set up for this.
If I type show databases, hit Enter,
I see bank is one database here.
I want to use that database.
I'll say use bank and
then hit Enter semicolon.
And now I can say show tables
where I see an accounts table.
And I'll select star from
accounts, Enter semicolon here,
to see some familiar users
and some familiar balances.
So let's actually
complete this injection
attack we just saw on the slides.
Maybe this bank has some feature
where I can choose some ID.
I can enter in my own
account ID to see my balance.
So on the website they
complete this query for me.
I give them, let's say, the ID 1.
I am Alice in this case.
They might finish this.
They might say select star from
accounts where the ID equals 1.
And they might automatically
run this SQL query.
I'll hit Enter.
And now I'll see the
balance for this account.
Well, now, what else could I do?
I could try to deliberately
mess up this query
to run my own SQL injection attack.
I could select, let's
say, star from accounts.
And then let me try
where the ID equals 1.
I give them 1.
But I also give them some SQL
statements they unwittingly execute.
I say union and then select star
from accounts, a bit like this.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And if I complete this
query, I see not just my own.
I see everyone's balances
and their names too.
So this is one demo of how SQL
injection attacks can show and leak
data that isn't intended to be leaked.
And sadly, these are fairly common
today among people who just aren't
familiar with how to prevent them.
So let me ask now what questions
we have on these attacks before we
get how to guard against them.
AUDIENCE: And just, can we use
this in regular expressions also?
CARTER ZENKE: Could you
use regular expressions?
So if you're familiar,
a regular expression
is some pattern of characters
that can match some text
and find values within some text.
I personally haven't
seen regular expressions
being used for injection attacks.
But that doesn't mean they can't be.
And so always do your research
on what you can and can't
use for an injection attack.
But a good question here.
So we've seen now SQL injection attacks.
But how do we prevent them?
Well one strategy is using what
we call a prepared statement.
A prepared statement is
kind of what it sounds like.
A prepared statement
is a statement that we
will later on Insert some values into.
We might treat it like a fill in
the blank, like here is my select
and I'll let you fill in
what you want me to select.
But I'll make sure to clean your
input before actually adding it in.
So let's think through
a few of these here.
Here I have prepare name from statement.
This is a SQL statement I can use
to prepare some statement, to take
some user input to make sure that
when I add in that user input,
nothing malicious will happen.
And in particular, I can make
sure the statement looks something
like this, select balance from
accounts where ID equals question mark.
This question mark is
just a question mark.
But syntactically it stands for
the ability of this statement
to clean whatever I put inside of it
to make sure it doesn't inadvertently
run SQL code I don't want it to run.
So let's try making our very
own prepared statement to guard
against these kinds of insertions here.
I'll go back to my computer.
And let's try this one out.
I could go back to MySQL.
And let me prepare some statement.
I could say let's prepare
a statement called
balance check, like we had before.
And now if I try to
prepare this statement
from the following, select star
from accounts where the ID equals
question mark end quote semicolon.
So in single quotes I have the query I'm
trying to prepare to take user input.
And I'm giving it some
name, like balance check.
So I'll hit Enter now.
And I'll see the query is
OK, statement prepared.
Now if I want to run this statement
to check on somebody's balance,
I can go through a few steps.
I could first set my own variable.
Like let's say I get some
user input from the user.
They type in 1.
Underneath the hood in SQL, I could say
set this variable called ID equal to 1.
This at symbol, which is a
convention for variables in MySQL.
Now I'll hit Enter.
So the user input is stored separately
in some variable not inside of MySQL
query, like we saw before.
Now I can execute.
I can say execute, in this case,
the balance check statement using
that same variable at ID.
So that question mark I
had before I will then
take whatever the user typed
in and clean it, and then
substitute in that value into this.
So I'll say using ID.
And now I get back Alice's balance.
And just to be clear here, let me try
to make this deliberately malicious.
I want to see everyone's accounts.
Well, we saw before that I
completed this query by typing in--
let's see-- set at ID equal to 1 but
then union select star from accounts.
This was what I added to that query to
show me everyone's account balances.
And I'll try to do the same here.
I'll say this is what
I'm trying to substitute
into this prepared statement.
I'll hit Enter.
Now I'll execute again.
I'll say execute balance
check using at ID,
which has an ID, but also
some malicious SQL statements.
Now if I hit Enter, what do I see?
Only Alice's balance.
So it seems that the prepared
statement cleans up my input,
ensures that if I have SQL
statements they don't get run.
So we've seen now SQL injection
attacks and how to guard against them.
What questions do we have?
AUDIENCE: So for these previous
examples you've shown us,
the [INAUDIBLE] statements
only take into account
the first acceptable condition?
Or how does it work?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
So here, let me show you again the
ID that I had put inside of here.
So if I say select at ID, like that,
I'll see this is the value of ID,
one union select star from accounts.
And what happens is
this prepared statement
does a process called escaping.
It finds all of the SQL keywords, all
of the values that could be malicious
and escapes them so they
don't actually get executed.
So it seems like in
this case what actually
happened was if we type in
the query again balance check
was select star from
accounts where ID equals 1.
It seems like it just
did the equals 1 part
to give me back, in this case, the
account balance while cleaning up
the rest of it overall.
OK, let's take one more question here.
AUDIENCE: So is this
the same reason why we
shouldn't use a formatted string
in Python to execute a SQL query?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so if you're
familiar with Python format strings,
it's a similar kind of
pitfall, which is you
can add in any possible value for this
variable you're substituting into.
And that can lead to some
unintended consequences.
So similarly, should we
create prepared statements
that can actually clean
and escape the data
that we might want to insert into our
queries or our statements over there
too.
Good question.
OK, so we've seen here
SQL injection attacks
and also how to guard against them.
And actually, by now
you're pretty well equipped
to go off into the world of databases.
And even though this is our
last week, I hope you think back
on how far you have come.
So you began by querying a single
table, a table of books in this case.
You then graduated into tables that
were related of books, and authors,
and publishers, and so on,
and querying those as well.
Afterwards, you saw how to design your
own databases, learning about types
and create table statements to
build something up from scratch.
Finally, you saw how to write,
how to add data to those databases
you had designed.
And then you kept going.
You saw how to view databases, how to
see them in a more simplified light,
how to optimize those
queries, and finally today
how to scale up all of this so
you can serve more and more users.
So I hope after all these weeks that
you are proud of how much you've grown.
We are certainly proud of you all too.
Now go off and continue your learning.
We'll see you later.