[MUSIC PLAYING]
CARTER ZENKE: Well, hello, one and all,
and welcome to CS50's Introduction to
Databases with SQL.
My name is Carter Zenke.
And in this course, you'll learn how to
represent, how to organize and manage,
and how to ask questions of
the data that's around you
in your everyday life.
But why learn those skills?
Well, you may have heard we're living in
the information age, where we generate
so much information, so much
data by virtue of interaction
with computers and with each
other over the internet.
You might think of, let's say, Google
keeping track of the sites you click on
or the sites you search for.
You could think of maybe the smartphone
in your pocket or the smartwatch
on your wrist keeping track
of health information, emails,
text messages, and so on.
You might even think
of YouTube, where you
might be watching this same
video keeping track of all
the videos on their platform,
the creators of those videos,
and even the comment you
might leave on this video.
So although, we're living in
this information age, where
there is so much data,
so much information,
we can use these new tools,
like database and SQL,
to interact with that information
to store it and manage it.
And although we're using
some of these new tools,
some of the other concepts we'll
learn aren't actually so new.
So here is a diagram from
literally a few thousand years ago.
And notice how this diagram
has rows and columns.
And this seems to store the
stipends for workers at a temple
some few thousand years ago.
So given what you know based on your
prior knowledge, what kind of name
might you give this diagram
with rows and with columns?
What can we give a name to for this?
So I'm seeing some ideas of a table,
perhaps a spreadsheet as well.
For our purposes, we'll
call this a table, where
a table stores some set of information.
And every row in that
table stores one item
in that set, where every column
has some piece of information
about that item, some
attribute of that item.
So here, for example, we do have
a table of workers at a temple.
Every row is one worker.
And every column is their
stipend for a particular month.
So I could take this idea of a
table, this very ancient idea,
and apply it to a more modern context.
So let's say I'm a
librarian, for instance.
I want to organize my library.
Well, here I have book
titles and authors.
And I could certainly use a
table to store this information.
But how might you propose
I store this information?
What could I do with my
rows and with my columns
if I have book titles and book authors?
I see one thing I could do is probably
organize my titles and my authors
next to each other like this.
I could take my titles to my authors,
put them right next together.
So I have Song of
Solomon by Toni Morrison,
Goodnight Moon by Margaret Wise Brown.
And notice hear how
each book is one row.
But every row has two columns worth two
pieces of information for each book.
I have a title for one column
and an author for the other.
And so together, I have a table of
books where every column tells me
one piece of information.
And every row tells me
one book in this data set.
So thankfully, now that we're
living in this information age,
we no longer have to use stone
tablets or perhaps pencil and paper
to store our tables.
We have software now like Apple Numbers,
Google Sheets, and Microsoft Excel.
But this isn't a course on Apple
Numbers or Microsoft Excel or so on.
It's actually a course
on databases and on SQL.
So feel free to raise your
hand if you'd like, but why
would we decide to move
along from these spreadsheet
softwares towards a database?
What might that database give us
that a spreadsheet might not give us?
So I'm seeing a few ideas here and
among them are some simplicity,
some ability to organize some data.
But there are a few
other ideas which I think
about too for why we might move beyond
spreadsheets and go towards databases.
Now one of these is this idea of scale.
So let's say you are a
Google or an Instagram.
You're trying to store
not just tens of thousands
of users or hundreds of
thousands but literally
millions of users or billions of users.
And with that kind of scale may
be better served by a database
to store that much information.
Another reason to move from
spreadsheets to databases
is the idea of being able to
update data more frequently.
Maybe you're a Twitter
of the world, and you're
trying to have others tweet
multiple times per second.
Well, a database can handle
that kind of capacity
much better than a
spreadsheet could alone.
And a third reason to move
beyond this might be speed.
Let's say I'm trying to look up some
piece of information in my database.
Well, I could do that much
faster with a database
than I could with a spreadsheet.
You could think of yourself using
Command-F or Control-F to find
a piece of information
in your spreadsheet,
going one by one through the rows.
A database gives you
access to more kinds
of algorithms you could use to search
this data much faster, ultimately.
So these three reasons,
among others, are
those might want to move beyond
spreadsheets and start using databases.
Now, it's worth thinking
first, what is a database?
We'll be talking about databases
throughout this course.
So what is a database?
Well, a database is simply some
way to organize your data such
that you can actually create data,
update data, read data, and delete
data.
And often these our for interactions
that we'll do with a database--
like adding some data, looking at data,
deleting data, and even updating it
along the way.
But the database isn't the
only thing in our picture here.
We also have a database
management system,
a way to interact with our database.
So you might think of perhaps
writing a program on your computer.
You have some interface
with to write that program,
like VS Code for instance.
Or you might think of your own
desktop on your own computer.
You have icons that you interact
with the underlying operating system.
In the same way, we can use this
software called a database management
system, or a DBMS for short, to
interact with a database perhaps
using a graphical interface or
using a textual language too.
Now, there are a few varieties
of database management softwares.
And these are a few of them here.
MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, and SQLite.
But this is a non-exhaustive list.
So let me also ask again, what kinds
of other database management systems
have you perhaps heard of in this case?
I'm seeing one for Microsoft
Access, perhaps, MongoDB.
There are other kinds of softwares,
other companies out there that make
these ways to interact with a database.
And this is, again,
a nonexhaustive list.
Now, if you are a
database administrator,
or maybe you're somebody who's making
a choice of which software to use,
you have a few trade-offs to consider.
Let's say you might think of one being
proprietary, for instance, costing
money to work with.
What you get for that
money is additional support
to actually implement your own database.
On the other hand, you might have
open source software or free software
to use, stuff like
PostgreSQL, MySQL, and SQLite.
But the downside is you are then
responsible for actually implementing
that database.
Another thing to consider
too is that maybe some
are going to be heavier weight
than others, more fully featured
as a consequence but perhaps
heavier weight requiring
more computation to run.
You can think of those
like MySQL or PostgreSQL
being a little bit heavier weight
but being more fully featured,
whereas SQLite down below will be a
little lighter weight, as the name
might imply, but allow you
to do most of the same work
that these other softwares
could allow you to do as well.
And in this course, we'll
actually be using SQLite for you
to work with your own databases.
But gradually, we'll move on
to MySQL and PostgreSQL too.
So let me go ahead and talk
about then SQL in this case.
You might notice that in each of
these, MySQL and PostgreSQL and SQLite,
each of them have this
idea of SQL in them.
And SQL is that language that we'll
use to interact with our database.
Now, let me ask, what does
SQL stand for, perhaps?
We talk about S-Q-L or SQL,
but what might SQL stand for?
So I'm saying it stands for
Structured Query Language,
which is good if you already know
this, but not to worry if you don't.
So SQL does stand for
Structured Query Language.
As we'll see in this
course, it is structured.
It does have some keywords you can
use to interact with the database.
And it is a query language--
it can be used to ask
questions of data inside a database.
We'll see that this is the language we
can use to create data, to read data,
to update data, and delete
data all with SQL in this case.
And our next thing will be to
talk about this idea of querying.
So SQL is a query language,
but what can we do with SQL?
Well, the first thing we
can do, we'll focus on first
in this course is writing queries--
trying to ask questions
of data using SQL.
Well, what kinds of
questions could we ask?
Well, you might imagine perhaps working
at an Instagram or a Facebook trying
to work as an engineer to
figure out what kinds of posts
are the most liked on your platform.
That's a question you can answer
with databases and with SQL.
You might also think of whether
your numbers of daily users
are growing or shrinking if you
work at a startup for instance.
Even maybe you might be working for some
a company like Spotify that could ask,
how could we play songs that are
like those a user just played?
This too is a question you can
answer with databases and with SQL.
Now today, we'll be focusing
on this database of books.
And in particular, books
that have been longlisted,
quote, unquote, "for the
International Booker Prize."
The International Booker
Prize, if you're not familiar,
is an award given to books
written around the world
by authors from many countries.
And it's designed to award books
of fiction particularly good
in some cases.
And every year, the
committee selects 13 books
to include on a longlist for
consideration for this prize.
And our database then has
five years worth of longlists
for the International
Booker Prize inside of it.
We could use this
database, perhaps, if we
were a librarian trying to find books
for our library or even as a book
reader, an avid reader myself
trying to find books to read that I
could put on my own shelf overall.
So we'll look at this database.
But we'll need a few
tools in our toolkit,
metaphorically, to actually
interact with this database.
And one of them is going
to be Visual Studio Code.
Visual Studio code is an IDE, integrated
development environment, to write code
and to edit files with.
It's also often called VS Code.
Now, in VS Code, we'll also be able to
use SQLite, this database management
system, or a DBMS for short, to
actually interact with that database.
So we'll be using these
two tools combined
to work with the database of longlisted
books for the International Booker
Prize.
And although we'll be using it here,
SQLite is not just used in this course.
It's used in a variety of applications.
You could think too
of phone applications,
where SQLite is often used on those
devices have much lower memory.
You could think too of it being
used on desktop applications
to simplify the process
of storing data there too.
You could even think of
it being used on websites
to help store information that user
submits via a form, for example.
So we'll jump into using
SQLite, but keep in mind
that not just in this
course you'll use it,
but also, it's used in a variety
of applications here too.
So why don't we just jump right into
things and start using our environment
and start using SQLite?
So I'll go over here to my computer
and will open up, let's say, VS Code.
We're here.
You can see I have my
terminal environment.
And if you're familiar,
you can type things like ls
to see the files that are
in your current folder.
So I'll type ls right here.
And I'll see this database
called longlist.db.
Again, working with books that
have been longlisted or considered
for the International Booker Prize.
So if I want to open up this
file, I can use this command.
Then this command is going
to be called SQLite 3.
Or I can take some file that I
have, like longlist.db, and open
it using this program called SQLite 3.
Well, it's called SQLite 3 because
this is the third version of the SQLite
software.
So let's try this in our terminal.
I'll go back over here, and
I'll say sqlite3 longlist.db.
And now, I'll hit Enter.
And notice how my
terminal prompt changes.
It's no longer dollar sign.
It now says sqlite in front.
This means I'm inside of
my SQLite environment.
So to clear things up, let
me just clear my terminal.
I can use Control-L for this.
And now I have just that prompt up top.
And now a question I want to
answer in this case first is, what
data do I actually have in my database?
What data is actually here for me to
look at and to ask questions about?
Now, for this question, I
can use my very first SQL
keyword, which will be called SELECT.
So SELECT is a way for me to select some
rows in a table inside of my database.
Using SELECT, I can
get back certain rows
or, in this case, perhaps all of them
just to get a taste of what's inside.
So let's try using SELECT on
this database to understand
what rows we have in our table here.
Let me go back to my computer
and to my SQLite environment.
And I will try this
very first SQL keyword.
I'll say SELECT.
And I can use this star operator
here to say select everything.
I want every row and every
column from this table.
Now, it's not enough for me to simply
say select star and end my query.
I had to tell SQL which table
do I want to select rows from.
In this case, I know I
table was called longlist.
So I'll say SELECT star from
"longlist," quote, unquote.
And to end my query, I'll say Semicolon.
And then finally, I can hit Enter.
And notice how I get a lot of data back.
This is a lot of data all at once.
But it's because my terminal
is a little bit small,
there's a lot of rows and columns here.
So I could probably simplify
this just a little bit.
And instead of saying SELECT star, I
could also select a particular column
from my table.
I could say, for instance,
SELECT, let's say,
just the title column from my
database for my table like this.
I just know already that there
is a column called title.
So now, I'll try this instead-- not
select star, but select title instead.
I'll hit Enter.
And now, this looks a little bit better.
I can see the titles inside of
this table from top to bottom.
Now, the neat thing here is I can
select more than one column too.
Let's say I don't want just the title--
I want titles and authors in my search.
Well, I could do that as well.
Let me try this.
SELECT not just "title,"
quote, unquote, but then I'll
say comma and some new column to select.
I'll select also the
authors from this table.
And I'll select them from
the longlist table like this.
Now I'll hit Semicolon to end my query.
Hit Enter.
And now I'll see a
variety of columns here,
in particular the title
and the author column.
Now, this is going to be like
all of my columns so far.
And there is a way for me to
get back just to some of them
later on that we'll see.
But for now, let's
ask, what questions do
you have on this SQL SELECT statement
and how we're getting back these rows?
SPEAKER: Do I need to use the quotes
around the words like you are?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, great question.
Do I have to use quotes
around the words like I am?
In general, it's a good practice to use
these double quotes around your table
names and your column names.
These are called SQL identifiers.
Later on, we'll see we'll also
have strings in SQL-- strings
being collections of
characters we can use.
For those, we'll simply
single-quote them
to note the difference between a
string and an actual column name.
So good style convention here to
use-- double quotes for column names
and single quotes for string names.
Other questions too?
SPEAKER: OK.
I wanted to know, where did we
take all this information from.
Like, this data, I don't
know this list of books,
where did we take all
this information from?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a great question.
Where do we take this information from?
So some of this data
is publicly available.
In fact, if you look at
the Booker Prize website,
you can find a set of
longlisted books over the years.
In this case, we have
books from 2018 to 2023.
We'll also see later on this table
has data on the ratings of those books
and the number of votes that
were given to those books.
That data is from Goodreads,
the site that aggregates
reviews from people like you, people
like me who rate books online.
So we've taken data from a variety of
sources and combined it into one here.
Let's take one more
question to from Vinayak.
SPEAKER: Yeah.
So I wanted to ask regarding the syntax
of what you used in the terminal.
So is the whole SQLite
3 is case-sensitive
because while using the syntax you
used capital letters, whereas can we
use small-case letters as well?
CARTER ZENKE: A great question.
So here, I used capital
letters for SQL keywords
and lowercase, my table
names and column names.
Do I have to do that?
I, in some cases, do, some cases don't.
I think I could use lowercase
for these SQL keywords,
but it's not very good
style, for instance.
So let me just show you an example of
this while I go back to my computer.
So the question again was, can I
use lowercase for SQL keywords?
I think I could, but the
question is, should I?
And probably not.
So let me try this.
I'll say select, let's say, title from--
I'm in the habit of uppercase it.
So I'll say from in lowercase
longlist like this Semicolon.
Hit Enter.
And that still works.
But the problem you
might run into is someone
who's reading your query particularly,
a long one, might want to know,
what are the SQL keywords?
And what are your column names
and other identifiers here?
By capitalizing your SQL
keywords, you can make it clear
that this is a SQL keyword and
not some other name overall.
OK.
So let's keep going.
And we saw just a little bit ago that
we could select "title" from "longlist."
And we would get back a whole list of
titles, literally all the titles that
are in this database.
But it's often maybe good practice
for me to not look at all the data.
Like, imagine if we had
millions of rows in this column,
but only to give back some.
Take a peek of what's
inside this database.
And for that, I could use this other
SQL keyword, this one called LIMIT.
So LIMIT, as its name
might imply, limits
the number of queries or the number
of rows I get back from my query.
I could say LIMIT 3,
for instance, or LIMIT 5
to get back only the top 3 or
the top 5 rows from my table.
And let me ask folks,
if I wanted to peak
in this data set, how many rows
should I try to limit it to?
I could say SELECT
title from, let's say,
longlist, but limit to what number?
I'm seeing 10.
So let's try 10 first.
I'll go back to my computer.
I'll come back over here,
and I'll say, why don't I
select "title" from "longlist?"
But now, instead of hitting Semicolon,
I will instead say LIMIT 10 Semicolon.
And I'll hit Enter.
Now I see only the first
10 rows in my data set.
Handy for peeking in at the
top of my data set here too.
Let me try not just 10 but 5.
So I'll say SELECT "title" from
"longlist" LIMIT 5 Semicolon.
This then gives me just the
top 5 titles in my database.
Just in whatever order they
were added to my table,
I'll see them in that order here too.
So using LIMIT, we can actually try
to get back a certain number of rows.
But this isn't quite that interesting.
It's good for peaking in your data set.
I think we've answered that
question of, what data do we have?
But let's say we want to
make more advanced queries.
We want to find the books that were
nominated in 2023 or perhaps books
by a certain author.
Well, for that, we could use this next
SQL keyword, this one called WHERE.
So WHERE allows me to get
back not all rows, but only
some rows where some condition is true.
So WHERE is often combined
with other conditions
to make sure I only get back some
rows, where that condition is true.
Let's try looking at
that in SQLite to get
a feel for what it can do for us here.
So I'll go back to my WHERE.
And I will then go back to SQLite here.
Hit Control-L to clear my terminal.
And I'll then try this query.
I'll say SELECT "title."
SELECT "title."
And why don't we also
select author along the way?
Two columns here.
And I'll select them
from my longlist table.
But I don't want all rows.
I only want, let's say, those titles and
authors that were longlisted in 2023.
So I'll do this.
I'll say WHERE the "year"
column is equal to 2023.
And notice here how 2023
is not in quotes because it
is an actual number, an integer.
So I don't need to quote it like I would
a string some collection of characters
or a table or column name.
So I'll hit Enter here.
And what do I see?
Well, I see only those books
that were nominated in 2023.
Let's try this again.
I might try not just 2023--
I might try 2022 like this.
Hit Semicolon.
Now, I'll see those
books nominated in 2022.
I could keep going.
I could say why not 2022?
Why not 2021?
Now, I have all those
books nominated in 2021.
So this is handy.
We can set things equal to or not
equal to make some condition here.
And we also have others we could use.
We saw equals just now.
But we similarly have not equals.
And we have this kind of
obscure operator down here.
This one being also equivalent to not
equals as we'll see in just a minute.
But let me first ask
now, what questions do
we have on how to use WHERE
or using SELECT so far?
SPEAKER: Why are the subsets of SQL?
CARTER ZENKE: A good question.
Are there subsets of SQL?
So there are.
In fact, S-Q-L or SQL
was defined by the,
I believe it's the ANSI,
like standard corporation.
They have a whole set
of the SQL language
that is like the official version of it.
You might be able to use
some subset of that version
with the database manager
system that you actually use.
So for SQLite, we're using a subset
of SQL that works with SQLite.
Similarly, if you were using another
software like PostgreSQL or MySQL,
you could use another subset there too.
Let's take another question
from Tayas, perhaps.
SPEAKER: Then I want to know that, can
we add 2022 and 2021 in a terminal?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good question.
Could I, perhaps, try to
filter by 2021 and 2022?
I could do that.
And we'll see that in
just a moment here.
So let's keep going and exploring
some other options with not equals.
And then we'll see how we can
combine conditions using WHERE too.
So let's go back, and
let's focus first on trying
to use these not equal operators.
We saw the exclamation point equals and
this greater than, less than sign put
together.
So let's try a few of those.
Let's say I want to find books that
are written by a certain author.
Well, I could use equals for that.
But let's say I also want
to find books that are not
written in the hardcover
format, like they
tend to be more expensive and so on.
So I don't want hardcover books.
Well, I could try a query like this.
I could say SELECT "title" and "format,"
where format is either hardcover
or paperback, FROM my "longlist" table.
And now I'll say, WHERE the "format"
is not equal to hardcover Semicolon.
So notice here I'm using
single quotes for hardcover.
This is a string.
It's not a table name or a column name.
It is just a string.
So I'm using single quotes here.
Everything else, though, like
format, longlist, title, et cetera,
those are all table
names or column names.
So again, I'll hit Enter.
And now I'll see that these are all
in paperback according to my table.
I've omitted those that are hardcover.
Well, I could also use in this
case, the greater than or less
than sign put together to
say not equals as well.
Let me just hit the Up
Arrow on my computer
to reveal what I just previously typed.
I'll then tab back over and say not
exclamation point equals, but less than
and then greater than.
Hit Enter now.
And I should see the very same results.
But all I did was change this
operator from exclamation point
equals to less than and greater than.
It tends to be that the
exclamation point equals
is the more common operator in this
case, but they do the very same thing.
Now, one more keyword I could
use here that's worth mentioning
is this keyword called NOT.
So here, I was able to use
exclamation point equals or the less
than or greater than
sign to say not equals.
But I could also negate
a condition using NOT.
So let's try using this one
in our SQLite terminal too.
I'll go back over here.
And I'll bring back my SQLite terminal.
I'll say let's do not this
operator here, but instead use NOT.
So I might, in front of WHERE, say
WHERE NOT "format" equals "hardcover."
So I have a condition,
"format" equals "hardcover,"
but now I'm going to negate
it, take the opposite of it
and get back the very
same results here too.
OK.
So to the question earlier, how
we can combine these conditionals.
So let's try that here in just a minute.
So let's say I wanted
to find the books that
were not just written in 2022 or 2023
alone, but all the books together.
Well for this, I could use a
few other SQL keywords that
might be a little familiar to you too.
Let's try looking at
some of these over here.
So here, we have these called AND,
OR, and these parentheses here too.
So using AND and OR, I
can change conditionals.
I can put them together to make a
more complex conditional, a compound
condition.
And I could also use these
parentheses to symbolize
that this condition
should come first and then
some condition should
come afterwards as well.
So let's try these in SQLite as well.
I'll go back to my computer.
And again, our goal is to find
not just books in 2022 or 2023,
but books that work across
those years as well.
So I'll, in this case say, SELECT--
let's go for a "title" and
"author" from my "longlist" table.
Now, I'll say WHERE the
"year" is 2022, as we did
before, OR perhaps the "year" is 2023.
And notice how my query is kind
of wrapping around my terminal.
I could leave it like this, or
if I backspace just a little bit,
I could hit Enter.
And now I'm on a new line
to continue my query.
So here, I'll say OR "year" is 2023.
And now my query is done.
So I'll hit Semicolon.
And I should see those books published
in or nominated in 2022 or 2023.
Let's try a few more here.
Let's try using our parentheses as well.
Maybe I want not just
these books but also
those that are formatted
in a hardcover format.
So I'll say--
I'll clear my terminal, Control-L
again, and SELECT "title" as well as,
let's say, "format" from
my "longlist" table.
And now, I'll hit my new
line to extend my query
without wrapping it on my terminal.
I'll hit Enter.
And I'll say WHERE the "year"
is 2022 OR the "year" is 2023.
That's one condition.
And I can denote that with a
single set of parentheses here.
I also want it to be true that
the "format" is not "hardcover."
So now, I'm adding
another condition in here.
Now, I'll say Semicolon, hit Enter.
And I'll get back only those books
that are published in the paperback
format in 2022 and 2023.
OK.
So let me pause again and ask if
there are any questions so far
in how we've been using WHERE and
SELECT and other conditions as well.
SPEAKER: I would like
to know about the--
we can have a list of the top
titles available in the database.
Like you have mentioned, the title,
author, where we can know about that.
What are the titles available in
the database using command below?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So here I've been using these column
names called "title" and "author."
And I think your question is, how
would I know that I have these columns?
Well, as we'll see in
future times together,
I'll be able to actually look at
the schema of my database, what
columns are inside of it.
For now, just take it
on my own word that I
knew what was inside the database
before I actually started querying it.
We'll see later on how
you can take a database
and understand the columns
you have there too.
A good question.
Let's jump into some more queries then.
I'll go back to my computer.
And let's see what else we
could do with these conditions.
Well, not only could I try
to make compound conditions,
I could also try to find, let's
say, which data is missing.
So I know in this table, I
have not just authors of books,
but translators of those books.
Often, books for the
International Booker Prize
were translated from some
other language into English--
but some weren't or at least
they didn't have a translator
that was separate from the author.
So to think about what data
is missing from our table,
we should introduce this new idea--
this one called NULL.
So I'll walk over here.
And we'll see that we have this
type called NULL, where this
means that this value doesn't exist.
It's not in our database.
We can actually put together a condition
around this idea of null, something
not being there.
We could use IS NULL to
figure out if a value is null.
It's not there.
It's missing from our database.
Or IS IT NULL, meaning
that it actually is there.
So I'll go back to SQLite
and show you what we could
do with some of these concepts here.
Let me go back to my terminal.
And let's say I do want to
find those translators that
don't exist in my database.
Well, I could use SELECT, let's say,
"title" and "translator" from my
"longlist."
And I want to make sure that
these translators are null--
they don't exist.
So I'll say WHERE "translator"
IS NULL Semicolon.
Now, I'll hit Enter.
And I should see two books.
Titles are The Perfect Nine and
the indictment of The Enlightenment
of The Greengate Tree.
But notice how over here,
this value is null--
it doesn't exist in my table.
I could conversely find those books that
do have translators using IS NOT NULL.
And I will try this one again.
But in this case, I'll say, WHERE
"translator" IS NOT NULL Semicolon.
And I'll hit Enter.
And now, let me just
zoom out a little bit.
I can see that I have both
titles on the left-hand side
and translators on the right-hand side.
All of these actually exists.
These are books that did have
translators in this case.
So a good way to find data that's
missing in your table using
NULL or IS NOT NULL.
So let's come back over here
and figure out what more
we can do with some of these queries.
We've kind of exhausted our work
with some of our conditions,
like chaining them together
and using NULL and so on.
But one more thing we could do is
trying to use this idea of matching
some kind of pattern in my database.
So maybe I'm a book reader.
And I want to find a book with the
word "love" somewhere in the title.
Well, for this, I could
use another keyword--
this one called LIKE.
So LIKE is a good keyword to
use when I want to roughly match
some string in my database.
Let's say I want to look
at book titles and find
if some word exists in that title.
I could use LIKE for that.
And LIKE becomes powerful
when you combine it
with these other operators, namely
this percent sign and this underscore.
The percent sign can match any
character around a string I give it.
And the underscore can
match any single character
that I pass in with my string.
It's probably best
shown with an example.
So let me show you some
in my terminal here.
I'll walk back.
And, again, we'll try
to find these books that
have "love" somewhere in the title.
So I'll say in this case, SELECT,
let's say, "title" from "longlist."
But I don't want all titles.
I only want those that have
"love" somewhere in this title.
So I'll say WHERE "title" LIKE, let's
say, percent love percent Semicolon.
Now before I run this, let me
explain what this is doing.
I have here a SELECT query
asking for the "title"
column from my "longlist" table.
But I'll only get back those rows where
"title" is LIKE percent love percent.
But what does that mean?
Well, the percent, remember,
matches any string of characters.
It could match a, b, c, 1, 2, 3.
As long as any string of characters
comes after and has "love,"
I could match that value here.
Similarly, the percent
sign after says anything
that comes after "love," as long as
"love" is somewhere in the middle.
So anything before, anything
after, but so long as "love"
is just somewhere in
there, I'll get it back.
So let me try that running this
query then and come back over here.
I will hit Enter on my query.
And I'll see I get back four books--
Love in the Big City, More
Than I Love My Life and so on.
So notice how if I come back over
here that each of these titles
has "love" somewhere in it.
For this one, I match
love up front and then
had any string of characters
coming after it like this.
For this one, I had More
Than I Love My Life.
I got some string before it.
And then afterwards, any string after
it, "love" is somewhere in the middle.
Let me show you another
example too, where
we use percent in a different way.
Let's say I want to find
only those books that
have "The" at the very
beginning of the title.
Let me try this.
I'll say a SELECT "title"
from "longlist" then WHERE,
let's say, the "title" is
LIKE the percent Semicolon.
Now, I've changed something up.
I have not percent in front and
behind, but only after the "The."
So in this case, I'll
get back not anything
that has "The" the
title wherever, but now
at the very beginning of this string.
And I see perhaps a style mistake.
Let me ask the audience,
what style mistake did
I just make when I typed in this query?
So I'm seeing maybe I used double quotes
when I should have used single quotes.
So let me come back and fix that first.
I'll come back over here.
And, again, by convention, we tend
to use single quotes for our strings.
So let me fix that right here.
And now let me run this query
to see what we get back.
I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see only those
books that begin with "The."
Now, let me show this
query again, though.
This was our query here.
Knowing what we know
about the percent sign,
what other titles might I accidentally
get back by running this query?
I have "The" percent.
But what other words actually
begin these book titles
if I were to run this query here?
We saw only those with "The," but if
I had other book titles, what might
I get back?
So I might get back
those book titles that
have not just "The" the
beginning but also, let's say,
"There" or "They" or so on.
There are many words
beginning with T-H-E.
And if I had the percent
sign right after it,
I might match one of those
words like Y or R-E or so on.
So I didn't have any of those
titles in this database.
But you can imagine a different
database where I have that kind of data.
Let's fix this then.
I say, I want to match not just
"The" but "The" and a space,
and match any characters
after that to make this
query better designed in this instance.
OK.
So let me pause here then
and ask what questions we
have on using percent along with LIKE.
SPEAKER: Can we use two percent
signs between two words?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I think so.
So let me go back to my terminal here
and let me try to answer this question.
So can we use two percent signs to
say something's between two words?
So let me say this.
I'll go with SELECT, let's say,
"title" from "longlist" WHERE maybe
the "title" has something like--
maybe it begins with "The."
So I'll say WHERE "title" LIKE "The."
And then I'll take any set
of characters afterwards.
But I want to have
"love" also in here too.
So I'll say "love."
And then I'll take any other characters
after it, percent again, single quote,
Semicolon.
Now, I don't know if I have any
books that actually fit this search.
But I could say the percent
love percent to mean give me
back any title that has
"The" at the beginning
then any words or characters then
"love" then any words or characters
after that.
I'll hit Enter.
And I see I don't have any books
that fit that kind of description.
But if I did, I would see them here
with "The" at the beginning and "love"
somewhere in the title.
All right.
So let's keep going.
Let's focus not just on this percent
sign, but also on this underscore.
So if I want to find--
let's say, I don't know what a
particular character is in my title.
I could use this underscore to
match any particular character.
Not any string of characters,
but any single character too.
So let's try this in our terminal.
And there is a book,
this one called a Pyre.
And I actually keep
forgetting how it's spelled.
I don't know whether it's P-I-R-E
or P-Y-R-E. It could be either one,
but I want to find it in my database.
So let me try this.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, "title"
FROM "longlist," WHERE, in this case,
"title" is LIKE--
well, I know that it
starts with a P. And I
don't know if this is an I or a Y. But
I'll at least leave it as an underscore
now to say it could
be any character here.
Then I'll say R-E
single quote, Semicolon.
And now I could try hitting Enter.
And I'll see I get back
this title called Pyre.
So notice in this case that
the underscore is matching
literally any single character.
This could be a Y. It could be an I.
But in this case, I have this Y here.
OK.
Let me go back.
And let's actually ask in
this case what questions we
have on using LIKE with these
single underscores if any.
SPEAKER: Yeah.
So Carter, I wanted to ask you, that
as you use the underscore sign here,
so for multiple characters, can we
use multiple underscores in order
to find something in the database?
CARTER ZENKE: A great question.
Could we use more than one
underscore to try to find
some characters in our database?
You absolutely could.
So let me try that myself.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And let me try to find a book
title this could work with.
I'll say maybe SELECT
"title" from "longlist"
to get back all the books in this table.
I'll hit Semicolon.
And maybe I will go with--
let's try this one called Tyll.
Well, maybe I want to just find the
titles that have a Y or an I in here,
but I also don't know if it's one
L or maybe two L's, for instance.
Let me go back and try this.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, "title" FROM
"longlist" WHERE my "title" is LIKE--
I know it begins with a T. I
don't know if this is a Y or an I.
And maybe I know that it has maybe
one or two characters after it.
So I'll try this one.
Now I have three underscores,
single underscore.
So match any book title that
has T and then any three
individual characters after it.
I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see I get back Tyll.
This is the only title that has T
and then three characters after it.
I could try to get better with this.
I could say maybe I'll accept
five or six characters like that.
Hit Enter.
And I'll see-- whoops, I
didn't compute my query here.
Let me just try it from the top again.
I'll say SELECT "title"
from "longlist" where
title is like, let's say,
T-Y underscore, underscore,
underscore, underscore.
Hit Semicolon.
And now I get no matches.
So there is no book in
the database that has T-Y
and then, let's say, three or four
underscores for any character after it.
OK.
So this covers our
use of LIKE, but let's
keep going and building
more complex conditions
to find even more answers to questions
we have about this data over here.
Let me think what we should show next.
We've seen LIKE.
We've seen some compound conditionals.
Well, let's go back to trying to find
books that are in a certain year.
So we saw earlier we
had this kind of query.
We could say SELECT "title" and "year"
FROM, let's say, our "longlist."
Now I can try to find those books
that are written or nominated
in 2022 and 2023.
But let's say I want to go further.
I want those from 2019 to 2022,
a span of multiple years here.
So I could try it like
this, WHERE "year" equals--
let's go ahead and say 2019--
OR "year" is 2020 OR "year" is 2021.
And let me make a new line again.
OR "year" is 2022 Semicolon.
And before I run this query,
let me ask our audience,
what strikes you as being not very
well designed about this query?
What could I be doing better here?
So I'm seeing maybe one improvement
is that I don't need to write out
OR "year" is this, OR "year" is that.
I could probably do better with this.
And let's introduce some
new keywords for working
with ranges in terms of our conditions.
So here, we can see some
new operators to use.
We have this greater than
sign, this less than sign,
greater than or equal to,
and less than or equal to.
And we can use these to build
ranges inside of our queries to say,
I want something to be greater than this
number or less than this number too.
And we can combine these
with AND and our OR
we saw before to get back in
this case some set of rows
that match what we intend to find.
So let me go back and
try some of these out.
I'll try to improve the
design of this query.
Let me first run it, and we'll
see we do get back 2019 to 2022.
But I could probably do better.
So let's try using
our new operators here
that can give us some
range capabilities.
I'll say SELECT "title" and also
SELECT "year" from "longlist."
But now I want those rows where the
year is greater than or equal to 2019,
and the year is less than
or equal to 2022 Semicolon.
I'll hit Enter.
Notice I'll get the very same results.
So I get all those same rows.
But now my query is much smaller.
It's making use of these range
operators I've seen so far.
I could even further improve this.
I could make this a
little better designed to.
Let me go back to some slides and
show you we could use these keywords
BETWEEN blank AND blank, where
this can be some condition
or some number in this case.
I could say between,
let's say, 2019 AND 2022.
This is inclusive.
So if I say 2019 AND 2022, I'll get back
a query that includes 2019 and 2022.
So let me try this one.
I'll go back over here.
And I will now try
SELECT "title" and "year"
from "longlist," WHERE the
"year" is between 2019 AND 2022.
Same results now, which is a different
way of writing this same query.
Now what else can we
do with these ranges?
Well, as we've said before, these books
actually have some ratings involved.
These ratings are
crowdsourced from Goodreads,
a site you can review books online.
And I want to find maybe the books
that have a rating of 4.0 or higher.
Well, I could do that now with my ranges
I could say SELECT "title" and "rating"
from my "longlist."
And I could say WHERE the "rating"
is greater than 4.0 Semicolon.
I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see now only those
books that have a rating of 4.0
or higher like this.
I could even combine conditions.
So I know that these books
have a certain rating,
but how many votes do they really get?
Well, let's take a peek.
I'll come back over here.
And let me try this one.
I could say SELECT "title."
Oops, let me clear my terminal
again so it's back up top.
SELECT "title" and
"rating" and the number of
votes that these books got from,
let's say, our "longlist" table.
Now, I want to find those that
have a rating of greater than 4.0,
and, let's say, a number of votes--
a number of votes which
is greater than at least--
let's go with 10,000.
So at least we know a good number of
folks actually voted on these books
to find the best among them.
I'll Enter.
And now I'll see we're
only down to a few books,
four in fact, where each one
has a rating higher than 4.0.
And indeed, every vote row has a vote
total greater than 10,000 in this case.
So a good way to try to find the
top books in our data set here.
Let's keep going with these ranges.
And let's think about one
more thing we could do.
Maybe I want to find books that
are less than a certain length.
So I'll try that as well.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, "title"
and "pages" from my "longlist."
And now I can make a
condition based on pages.
I'll say WHERE "pages" is less than 300.
Hit Enter.
And now I should see that
I have all these books that
are less than 300 pages long
when they were first published.
So let's pause here
and ask what questions
we have on these range conditions.
SPEAKER: I just wanted to check
if for a proper query in this case
to be able to run operations, they
have to be integers in the database.
And my second question is for
when we're matching a string,
is it case-sensitive or not?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, two great questions.
So the first one here is going to be,
do I have to use integers in this case?
And what types, maybe, should I use?
And the second one being, could I
match strings like case insensitively?
So for the first one,
in this case, it'll
depend on the design of your database.
So we'll see later on
in the course, how we
can choose the types for our columns.
And how that might impact the types
we actually use in our queries.
For now, I made this database.
So I just know that my
year column is an integer,
my ratings column is a real number
or a float, if you're familiar,
and my votes is an integer.
So I just know to use
those numbers there.
To the question of matching
things case-insensitively,
let's actually revisit LIKE just briefly
here to show you what that can do.
So I go back to my terminal, and let's
say I want to find just a book title.
And I want to type it
in kind of sloppily.
I don't want to capitalize
it like capital books are.
So I'll say SELECT let's
say "title" from "longlist."
And maybe, I'll want to
find that book Pyre again.
So I could say WHERE "title" is
LIKE 'pyre', but all in lowercase.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see I do get back Pyre.
So even though I said WHERE "title"
is LIKE lowercase 'pyre', I got back
capital Pyre.
Now this is in contrast to saying
WHERE "title" equals lowercase 'pyre'.
Let's try that.
I'll come back over here.
And I'll say again SELECT
"title" from "longlist,"
but now WHERE "title" equals,
quote, unquote, 'pyre' Semicolon.
I'll hit Enter.
And now I see no results.
So in this case, the equal is
going to be case-sensitive.
Case matters in this case,
but LIKE is case-insensitive.
OK.
Why don't we keep going then?
And let's take a look
at a few other things
we can do with these SQL
keywords for querying.
Well, earlier, we were
trying to find a way
to find the best books in our data set.
And we did that by filtering
them based on some ranges.
But we could probably do
that a little bit more
methodically in this case using a new
keyword, this one called ORDER BY.
So ORDER BY allows us to
take the results of our query
and order them, as it suggests,
by some column itself.
So we could put them in alphabetical
order or in order by a number of votes
or in order by number of ratings.
And let's just try an example of this
to see how ORDER BY works for us.
But in the end, we'll see it can
arrange columns, arrange rows for us
in our resulting query.
So I'll go back to my computer.
And let's try this question here.
I want to try to find the
top 10 books in my table.
So I'll say SELECT "title"
and "rating" from "longlist."
Enter.
Not only query yet though.
Now I'll say ORDER BY the rating.
And let's only take the top 10.
So I'll say limit 10 in
this instance Semicolon.
So now I've combined some
of my prior keywords.
I'm using SELECT.
I'm using ORDER BY.
And I'm still using
our old friend LIMIT.
So let me hit Enter here.
And I'll get back, well,
not quite the top 10.
I see rating of 3.05 here
and rating of 3.42 down here.
So based on this, what do you think
the default ordering of ORDER BY is?
So you might be from least to greatest.
So we saw here that we have
rating being pretty small,
but we said ORDER BY our rating.
So it starts from small
and goes down to large.
So we need to fix this in some way.
And let's introduce a
new addition to ORDER BY
to have us fix this query overall.
So let me show you that ORDER BY does
by default sort from least to greatest.
But let's try some addition here.
We have not just ORDER BY
but ORDER BY some column
and then ascending or descending.
So ascending is the default. It
means from least to greatest.
Descending, we can specify
meaning from greatest to smallest.
So let's try using ORDER BY
but now with this other keyword
called DESC for descending here.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And let's rewrite this
query to include DESC.
I'll say SELECT "title" and
"rating" from "longlist."
And let me-- before
I run this query, let
me just clear my terminal
so it's back up at the top.
I'll backspace this.
And then a moment here, I'll press
Control-L. Now I'm back at the top.
I'll say SELECT "title", SELECT "title"
and "rating" from "longlist" WHERE--
actually, not WHERE.
We're not filtering yet.
I'll say ORDER BY rating but
not by ascending by default--
going from least to greatest.
I want greatest to least.
So I'll say DESC here.
Now, I can say LIMIT 10 Semicolon.
Hit Enter.
And now I'll see the top 10 books.
Here, I have The Eighth Life coming
in at 4.52 and The Books of Jacob
coming in at 4.06.
So now we're going from
greatest to smallest.
Well, I could order by
not just these ratings,
but also by the number of votes.
It seems there's a tie to break here.
If I look at Still Born and When
We Cease to Understand the World,
those both have a rating of 4.14.
But presumably, one book has
maybe more votes than the other.
So I could try to break this tie by
ordering not just by rating but also
by votes, the number votes this book
actually received on Good Reads.
So let's try that then
to break this tie.
I'll come back over here.
And I'll try this query now.
I'll say, again, SELECT "title"
and "rating" from "longlist."
Now I'll order by, first, the
rating column in descending order.
But I also want to order by the number
of votes after I order by rating.
So I'm saying first order
by rating, but afterwards,
followed by a comma, let's
order by the number of votes
also in descending order--
from greatest to smallest.
Now I'll just continue my
query on the next line.
And I'll say LIMIT 10 Semicolon.
This then gives me, let's
see, the books but now
they're going to be in the order that
allows us to see the number of votes.
Let me just actually refine this.
Let me say not just title
and rating, let's make
sure we can see the votes here too.
So SELECT "title" and "rating"
and "votes" from "longlist."
Hit Enter on my query.
Now I'll say ORDER BY
"rating" and "votes."
Then I'll say LIMIT 10.
And here, I'm just getting
the Up Arrow on my computer.
I'll hit Enter.
And now I'll see the votes included.
So let me show you
this on the big screen.
Here, we see that the tie is broken.
So when we cease to
understand the world,
these both have 4.14
along with Still Born.
But here, this book has more votes
and so is higher in our order
now that we've ordered
by multiple columns.
So let me pause here
and ask what questions
we have on ordering with data.
Ordering by one column or multiple,
and how we can sort data like this.
SPEAKER: Sir, I want to know that
can we write rating to 4.93 to 4.9?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah good question.
I think if I understand you
correctly, how can we select a rating
or try to find a rating that's like
equal to 4.92 or things like that.
Let's try that here.
So if I want to find
a particular rating,
I could simply use my
WHERE friend from before.
I could say SELECT, let's
say, "title" and "rating."
And maybe I could try to find
a particular rating for a book
from longlist.
I could say then WHERE this rating is
equal to, let's say, 4.932 Semicolon.
If this book exists, it
will get it back here.
So I'll hit Enter.
And I see there's no book with
this particular rating, 4.392.
But good question for how to find
particular ratings for our books here.
OK.
Other questions too on how we've been
able to sort our data and use ORDER BY?
SPEAKER: Will descend work on a
string on an alphabetic basis?
Or do we need to have special
conditions for alphabetic characters?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a great question.
So how could we use ORDER BY with some
characters or strings or some text
in our database?
Let's try that one out too and
see how that works with ASC
for ascending and DESC for descending.
So I'll go back to my terminal.
And I'll demonstrate here how
we can use this for some text.
So let's try to simply sorting our
books alphabetically for, let's say,
our library.
I'll say SELECT "title"
from "longlist," Enter.
And I want to order by
title, just plain and simple.
And then hit Semicolon.
Let's see what happens.
I'll hit Enter.
And now I'll see that
these books are ordered.
But they seem to be
ordered alphabetically.
So here, we have some titles
lower in the alphabet.
And up here, we have titles
earlier in the alphabet.
So by default ORDER BY seems
to order alphabetically.
If I change that default, though,
from ascending to descending,
let's see what happens.
I'll go back over here.
And I'll try the same
query but now using DESC.
SELECT "title" from "longlist."
ORDER BY "title" now
in descending order.
Hit Enter.
And now I'll see these titles
in reverse alphabetical order.
So notice how earlier on, we have
titles that are lower in the alphabet.
But down below, we have titles that
are earlier in the alphabet here.
So you can use ORDER
BY with these texts.
But you then have to specify whether
you want it in alphabetical order
or in reverse alphabetical order.
OK, so let's show a
few other concepts here
we can use alongside of these orderings.
One thing we could also do is
try to find more information
about the ratings of these books.
So let's say I want not
just to order these books
but try to find the average rating,
or to try to find the number of books,
or try to find let's say maybe the sum
of my total votes on each of my books.
Well, for this, we could
introduce some new concepts,
these ones called SQL's
aggregate functions.
These allow us to take a whole set of
rows and return not each of those rows
individually.
But instead, in this case, one number
based on the values in those rows.
You could imagine trying to
count the number of rows you have
or take the average
of the number of rows,
or take the average of let's
say a rating, for instance.
Finding the minimum rating
of the maximum rating
or finding the sum of some votes.
And we'll see each of
these in action here.
Let's go back to our terminal,
try some of these out.
I will try, in this case
first trying to find
the average rating from my longlist.
Well, I just from experience,
and as you now know too,
I can try to find the
average of some column
by using the AVG aggregate function.
So I'll say SELECT not
just rating in this case
but select the average
rating FROM "longlist."
Notice how in this case, I'm using this
kind of syntax, where I take rating,
my column I want to aggregate or
to sum up or to average like this.
And I apply the function
by saying its name
followed by some parentheses
around that column name.
So this will return to
me not all of the rating
rows but the average of the
rating rows in one single cell.
Let me try this.
I'll come back, and I
will then hit Enter.
And I'll see this is the average rating.
We have 3.7537179471795 is our
average rating for all of these books.
But of course, this isn't great.
What might I want to do if I was
going to show this to somebody else?
I could probably improve the
presentation of this in some way.
So I could probably round
this result. I have 3.75371,
we can probably stop after
two decimal points, right?
Just simply like 3.75.
So I could introduce some new keyword
here, this one around the results.
Let me show you this one in action.
I'll come back, and I'll try
not just select average rating
but select the rounded average rating.
So I'll say SELECT ROUND and then
take average of "rating" and round
to 2 decimal points FROM
"longlist" Semicolon.
So now this query decides to first
find the average of the rating column.
Then take the result and round
it using two decimal points.
Notice how round takes two inputs
or two arguments, the first one
being the rating, the average
rating, the second one being number
of decimal points to round, 2.
And we complete our query in the way we
usually do by saying FROM this table.
So let's try this one
to figure this out.
I'll come back.
And I'll hit Enter.
And now I'll see we do get back 3.75.
But there is still one
thing to improve here.
When I write this query, I
see this ugly title name--
ROUND average "rating" comma 2.
I wouldn't send this to my
boss or somebody else who I
work for or maybe even a friend, right?
I want to make sure it's pretty
so they can read it correctly.
So what could I do then to
try to make this prettier?
I could maybe rename this column.
I could try to take this and make
it not just this ugly mess of SQL
keyword but to give it some
name I could use instead.
So for this, we'll
introduce a brand new one--
new brand new keyword called AS.
Let's try this one too.
I'll come back, and I'll say SELECT,
again, ROUND average "rating" comma 2.
But now, I'll select it AS,
let's say, average rating.
And now before I actually
finish this query,
let me try to bring it up to the top
my terminal so we can see it all in one
go.
I'll backspace this.
And I'll say SELECT the rounded
version of the average rating rounded
to 2 decimal points AS--
let's call this one "average rating."
Now hit Enter.
And I'll say FROM my
"longlist" table Semicolon.
Now, I see it's much prettier overall.
I have no longer these
SQL keywords but instead
just average rating as my column name.
OK.
So let me pause here
and ask questions then
on using average or using ROUND
or using AS in these cases.
SPEAKER: I'm wondering, do these
sorts of commands have a funct--
are these commands encode something like
data types or just encode something?
Do these commands also have a name?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
And can I ask are you referring
to the AVG like COUNT like SUM
those kinds of things, or?
Yeah.
So these functions do have a name.
They are called aggregate functions.
And aggregate means to
combine, to bring together.
So they're called aggregate functions
because they take some number of rows,
like all my ratings for instance,
and bring it down to one single cell,
like the average or
the sum or the count.
So if you look up or read more
about SQL aggregate functions,
you'll see all of these
and perhaps some more
depending on the software you're using.
OK.
So let's keep going then and try
to start counting some other rows
and use our other
aggregate functions here.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And so far, we've seen average, as
well as we have seen ROUND and so on.
But why don't I try to find the maximum
or the minimum rating in my table?
I'll say SELECT, let's say, the MAX
"rating" FROM my "longlist" Semicolon.
Hit Enter.
Now I see the highest rated
book had a rating of 4.52.
Well, what about the minimum rating?
I could use MIN here too.
I could say SELECT, let's say, MIN of
my "rating" column FROM my "longlist"
table.
I'll hit Semicolon.
And I'll see it 3.05.
It is the lowest-rated
book I have in this set.
Well, as we've seen, let me
try to view this for you all.
I could say SELECT "title" and
"votes" FROM my "longlist."
SELECT "title" and "votes"
from my "longlist."
Here, I have many books with
many user-generated votes.
Maybe people on the internet
decided to rate this book out of 5
and maybe Go, Went, Gone got
about, let's say, 592 votes.
So I'm curious then, how many total
votes do I have in my data set?
Well, for that, I could use
the SUM aggregate function.
Try to count up each one of these
rows and/or turn it back to me
in a single cell.
So I'll use SUM here.
I'll come back and I'll say I want
to find the sum of my votes column.
I'll say SELECT, let's say,
the SUM of my "votes" column
FROM my "longlist" table.
And then I'll just Enter--
Semicolon Enter.
And I'll see over 600,000
people offer to vote
for each of these books that were
longlisted for the International Booker
Prize.
Now there'd be a few more here.
Let's check out what else we have left
to do and our aggregate functions.
We could also try to count up just
the number of books in our data set.
So why don't I try to find
the number of rows I have?
For that, I could use count.
And often to find the number
of rows in your data set,
you might use count and star
as we saw a little earlier.
I could say SELECT COUNT
star from "longlist"
And this means, again star means
give me every row and every column.
Give me basically my whole table, right?
And if I say COUNT star, that
means count up the number of rows
that I have in my database.
So I'll say COUNT star from "longlist."
And I get back 78
books in this database.
Well, let me try counting up
the number of translators here.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, COUNT
of "translators" FROM "longlist"
Semicolon.
Hit Enter.
And now I see 76.
So I have 78 books, but if I count
translators, I have 76 of them.
So why might that be?
Free to raise your hand
and try to guess at this.
Why do I have 78 rows
but 76 translators?
SPEAKER: Hi.
I actually had raised my
hand for the question.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, go ahead.
SPEAKER: Also, I wanted
to know whether the MAX
and the MIN functions can be used for
finding the longest or the shortest
string as well?
Or do you have a different
command for that?
CARTER ZENKE: Good question.
Could we use MAX and MIN to find
the longest or shortest string?
That's a good question.
So let's actually pause on this counting
here and try that out real quick.
So I'll come back to my terminal.
And let me try to use MAX and
MIN with some book titles.
So I'll say Select--
let's select the MAX title.
And at the same time, why don't
we select the MIN title as well?
And I'll select these
from my "longlist" table.
I'll hit Semicolon.
And now, let me try this out.
I'll get back Wretchedness
and A New Name--
Septology VI-VII.
Now, there's a few hypotheses here.
It does seem that our MAX "title"
is shorter than our MIN "title."
So it's probably not that MAX
gives us the length of the string,
but what do you notice?
Well, I see MIN is really
early on in the alphabet.
It has an A here, whereas MAX has
a W, pretty low in the alphabet.
And I would bet if we
ordered these book titles,
we would see a new name up at the very
top and a Wretchedness, the book here,
down at the bottom.
So MAX seems to give us the
lowest alphabetically, which
is kind of contradictory
with titles here or strings.
And MIN gives us the earliest in
the alphabet using this A as well.
OK.
So a good question.
Let's come back to our counting here.
Let's go back to my terminal.
And again, we had, in this case,
78 rows, but only 76 translators.
So, again, if I did SELECT
COUNT star from, let's say,
"longlist" then
Semicolon, I get back 78.
But if I do SELECT COUNT of "translator"
from "longlist," I get back 76.
And let me ask again, why do we
have 78 rows but 76 translators?
Feel free to say it.
OK, so I'm seeing maybe we
have some number of rows, 78.
But for our translators, you remember,
two of those were null values.
They didn't exist in our table.
So it seems like if we use COUNT
star, we're counting all the rows.
But if we use COUNT "translator,"
some column that has null values,
we're only getting back those rows
or those values that aren't null.
So COUNT, when given a
column, counts only those that
are not null that exist in our table.
OK, let's look at one more
example here for counting.
And let's try this.
Let's say I want to find all of
the publishers in this database.
I'll say SELECT COUNT of
"publisher" from my "longlist."
And I'll hit Semicolon.
So you might think that I have
78 publishers in this long list.
But would it be accurate
if I were to say
I have 78 different
publishers in this longlist?
Could I say that?
I'm seeing no, right?
I couldn't try to count
up these publishers
and then say I have 78 different ones.
I might double count the
publisher along the way.
And let me show you what we mean here.
So I'll go back to my table.
And let me try to select from publishers
or select the publisher column
from longlist.
I'll select "publisher" from "longlist."
Hit Semicolon.
Oops, and now I see
something a little odd.
Let me scroll back up and maybe
ask for a raised hand here.
Why might I get this odd result?
SPEAKER: Because of the quotes?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah.
So I think I mistyped
some of my query here.
I said it looks like "pubsliher"
instead of "publisher."
And in this case, SQL will
give me what I asked for.
I said SELECT "pubsliher"
from "longlist."
And says, OK, here it is.
But that column doesn't exist
so it creates this data for me.
So let me try this again.
I'll go back.
And I'll hopefully type
this correctly now.
I'll say SELECT, let's say, "publisher,"
this one, FROM "longlist" Semicolon.
And now I'll see all of the
publishers that I have in my table.
But what do you see?
Well, some repeat, right?
I have Harvill Secker
multiple times here.
I have similarly MacLehose
Press multiple times as well.
So if I count it up,
these publishers, I would
get each one counted one
time, which I want to find
the distinct ones the different ones.
I need a new keyword for this.
And for this, we'll use this keyword
indeed called DISTINCT, trying
to find unique values from our column.
So let's try this.
I'll go back over here and I will
now select not just publishers,
but distinct publishers.
I'll say SELECT DISTINCT publisher
from "longlist" Semicolon.
Now, if I scroll through here, I
should see each publisher in here
only one time.
If they have the same name,
they've been filtered out.
And now they're only the
same publisher here too.
So I will then try to
say SELECT, let's say,
COUNT of "publisher," SELECT
COUNT of "publisher" from--
COUNT of DISTINCT
"publisher," for instance.
COUNT distinct publisher-- oh, typo,
"publisher" FROM "longlist" Semicolon.
And I'll see I have 33
distinct publishers.
OK.
So this just about brings
us to the conclusion
of all of these new SQL keywords here.
We've seen so far that we
have several here to use.
But let's figure out how to
actually exit this prompt.
So you might it be in your
SQLite prompt right now.
If you want to leave it, you could
also use this command, dot quit.
Dot quit is not a SQL keyword.
It's a SQLite keyword
to leave your terminal
and go back to where you started.
So just to review then,
what we've seen so far
is how to select data from our table.
We can use select column to
take some column from our table
and give us back all of those rows
from that table for that column.
We've seen we can apply some
aggregate functions to take
maybe the count of our columns
or the average or so on.
And we can get back not
just all of our rows,
but only some of them using our WHERE
clause here along with a condition.
We could have multiple conditions,
having not just one but perhaps two.
Like, let's say, here,
condition 0 and condition 1.
And we could also use, we saw
before, this idea of equals and LIKE
to match some pattern or to make
something exactly equal over here.
We could, again, use AND and OR.
And we saw later on how
we could order our data
and use our LIMIT function to get
back only some number of rows.
Now, this then is our
interaction to querying.
And so far, we've seen
this world of books.
And the table we've had so far
really just has books inside of it.
But next time, what we'll see is how
to take this world of books and split
into multiple tables.
How do we find information on
publishers or books or authors too?
And how do we try to
put that in a table that
can present the relationships among
all of these different entities?
We'll talk about all that and
more when we come back next time.
And we'll see you there.