CARTER ZENKE: Well, hello one and
all, and welcome back to CS50--
Instruction to Databases with SQL.
My name is Carter Zenke
and up until now you've
been learning how to
design databases and how
to add data to them, like how
to insert, update, and delete
some values all together.
Now, along the way, we've
added some complexity.
That is, we went from one table to
multiple, , and we had relationships,
too, among all those tables, as well.
Now, what we'll introduce today is a
way to simplify some of that complexity
and give you a way to see your
data all the more clearly-- .
this tool called a view.
Now, we'll begin with a familiar
data set-- this data set of books.
And we learn about this data
set of books back in week zero.
If you remember, we
had a table of 78 books
that had all been nominated for
the International Booker Prize.
It was a single table,
just of these books.
Now quickly, in week one, we introduced
more than just this single table.
We actually had multiple tables-- a
table for books, a table for authors,
for example, and also some relationship
between those authors and those books.
We said that an author could write
not just one book, but multiple books.
And similarly, a book could be
written by not just one author,
but multiple as well.
This is what we call a
many-to-many relationship.
Now, we also saw this not just
visually, but in our database,
in terms of tables, as well.
We had this kind of schema, where we had
a table for authors, a table for books,
and then a table in the middle, to talk
about the relationship between authors
and books-- which
author wrote which book.
We can see this in the author
table, looking at these IDs here.
And now to recap, if I wanted to find
the book that Han here has written,
let me ask, how could I do that?
How could I find the book that
Han, in the authors table,
has written, over here
in the books table?
Feel free to raise your hand.
AUDIENCE: By looking
at the author_id, 31.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
So start by looking at the author_id.
That's a great idea.
So here we see that
Han's author_id is 31.
And we could make this link between the
authors table and the authored table.
So I'll highlight this here,
so we can see it visually.
Han has the ID 31.
And here on the authored table,
we see the author_id of 31 next
to, actually, some book_id.
This book_id is 74.
Well what book has that ID, 74?
Turns out it's the white
book, all the way over here.
Now, this is adding some
complexity to our queries.
If I want to find who
wrote what book, I have
to go through the authors table,
then the authored table, and then
the book table.
That's just a lot of
steps to go through.
And we could, though,
try to simplify this,
to have a better view
of this data, to see it
with just a single column for authors
and a single column for title.
So let's try to visualize this together.
What I might do first is try to flip
around this primary key of authors,
this ID column.
Let's put it closer to the author table,
just visually, metaphorically, here.
Now I might see that these
IDs line, up one to another.
And we saw in a previous lecture
that I could use a join in SQL
to put these tables into a single table.
And what a join does, if you remember,
is take the primary key in one table,
and the foreign key in another,
and just find which ones match,
to put the rows of each table together.
A bit like touching your
fingertips together, like this.
So I'll then visually
move these together,
join these tables into a single table.
And notice how if I, now,
just get rid of these IDs--
metaphorically, just visually here--
I now have a much more simple
table, a simple view of this data.
And if I want to find which book Han
has written, well, I could do that.
Just look at a single row here.
Look at the name column and
then the title column here.
Now, what we're doing, by creating
this new view of our data set,
is actually creating a view.
And a view is defined by
this here-- a virtual table
that is itself defined by a query.
Now, what does this mean?
What is a virtual table?
What is a query?
Let's go back a few steps
and see this in action.
So we started with, in
this case, three tables--
authors, books, and authored.
And presumably, there's some query here
that gets us from point A, these three
tables, to point B, this single table.
That query might involve some selects,
some join we talked about earlier.
But there is some query we can write
to get us from point A to point B.
And notice here that the result
of this query is itself a table.
Like, this has rows and
columns and what we can do
is see all of those in terms of
a table we could later on query.
So a view is a way of writing some
query to see our data in a new way
and then saving this view of our
data, so we can query it later on.
Now, why might you want to build a view?
Well, you might want to
for a few reasons here.
You could use it to simplify
your data, as we just saw here.
You can use it to aggregate your
data, to try to sum up some values
and store that in a single table.
You could use it to partition your
data, or divide it into logical pieces.
And you could even use
it to secure your data,
to perhaps hide some columns
you don't want somebody to see.
There are more reasons,
too, to use views.
We'll focus on these four today.
And let's begin by
focusing on simplifying.
So we saw earlier a way to simplify
these multiple tables down in to one.
If I go back here, we'll see, we
got from this set of three tables
to a single table, that had both
author names and author titles.
So let's see here exactly how
much we're reducing complexity
by trying out different
queries, and then
adding in a view to see all the
benefits of this new view we have here.
So we'll go back.
And we'll see, in this
case, our three tables--
authors, books, and authored.
And let's say I want to find the
books a particular author has written.
I could write a query to do just that.
And let's go back to SQLite here,
to run that query ourselves.
I'll come back to my
computer, here in SQLite.
And my goal will be to find which
author wrote which particular books.
So if I go to my database, here, I can
go to my terminal, and type sqlite3
longlist.db, to reopen this database.
And now, I should see,
if I type .schema,
all the tables that are inside of it.
I have a table for authors, if I scroll
up a little bit, a table for books,
and a table for authored-- that is,
relationship between authors and books.
Now, let's say I want
to write a query to find
which books Fernanda Melchor wrote.
Well, I probably first need to
find Fernanda's ID, as we just
saw visually in our earlier example.
So let's find Fernanda's ID.
I could say SELECT, let's say,
id FROM the authors table,
where the name equals Fernanda Melchor.
So I'll say SELECT id FROM authors.
Then, WHERE the "name" equals
Fernanda-- 'Fernanda Melchor' semicolon.
So it seems Fernanda's ID is 24.
And I could use this ID
in the rest of my query,
but I could probably
do better than this.
I could use what we
saw before, something
called a subquery, to take
this query I just wrote
and put it inside some other one here.
So let's take the next step and find
the book_ids that Fernando wrote.
So let's try looking in the authored
table for that, which has author_ids
and book_ids, side-by-side.
OK, I'll SELECT, in this case, the
book_id from the authored table, WHERE,
in this case, the author_id is
equal to-- well, I could say 24,
but I want to do better--
I could actually have a
very own subquery here
to find Fernanda's ID dynamically.
I could put parentheses here, then
hit one, two, three, four, spaces,
and say SELECT id from
the authors table, WHERE
the name equals Fernanda Melchor--
that same query from before.
I'll close this out,
close out my subquery.
And then if I hit Enter, I should see
now the book IDs Fernanda has written.
But there's still one more step here.
What do I now need to do?
I have book IDs that
Fernando wrote but how
do you think I could find the
titles from those book IDs?
AUDIENCE: You could select
the title from the books.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
When you select title
from that books table--
so if you remember, we have
titles inside of our books table,
but we still need to link
those titles through their ID
to the book IDs Fernanda has written.
So let's do one last step here.
I'll come back to my terminal.
And I'll write the query in full now.
So I know I want to end up with titles.
I'll say SELECT, in this case,
title from the books table.
Now, I want to find
particular titles where
the ID is in that list of
books Fernanda has written.
So I'll say WHERE the id is IN some
subquery, the query we actually
just wrote.
So let me write it again.
I'll say one, two, three, four
spaces here to indent for style.
Then I'll say SELECT the book_id from
the authored table, in this case,
WHERE the author_id is
equal to some number--
in this case, Fernanda's ID.
But what is Fernanda's ID?
Let's find out.
I'll make another subquery here
to find Fernanda's ID, indenting
four times just for style here.
Then I'll say SELECT id
from the authors table--
and then again indent--
WHERE the name equals Fernanda Melchor.
Then I'll close out all my queries to
create this single long query to find
all the books Fernanda has written.
And, again, the order here
is first find Fernanda's ID,
then find the book IDs
associated with that ID,
then find the titles associated
with those book IDs themselves.
Now I'll hit Enter and I should see all
those books that Fernanda has written.
Now, as we talked about,
this is a lot of complexity,
a lot of tables to go
through, and there's probably
a better way to do this.
So let me open up a new
terminal and try out
a different way of going about this.
I'll make a new
connection to my database.
I'll make a new terminal and I'll
say sqlite3 longlist.db, hit Enter.
Now I should see that I have a
brand new connection to my database.
And I could try to find
a better way to do this.
Let me try to do what we did visually
and join these tables together.
Well I could try SELECT name and
title FROM the authors table.
But notice how authors table
doesn't have titles in it.
It does have the name of the author,
but it doesn't have book title.
So to get titles, I have to
join in some new table here.
I'll hit Enter and I'll say JOIN, let's
say, the authored table on authors
dot id equals authored dot author_id.
And all I'm doing here is saying I'll
take first the authors table and then
why don't I try to combine this
table with the authored table,
linking it up by looking at
the authors dot ID column
and the authored dot author_id column.
And visually, let's take a look
what we're doing here in this join.
If I look at this in my
slides here, I should see--
I started with my authors table.
Here I had names of those authors and I
had an ID column in that author table.
Now I'm trying to join
the authored table
by telling SQL that these two columns,
author_id and id, should align.
They should line up like this
so their rows are all together.
But there's still one more step.
I've joined the author table
and the authored table,
but what's the next step
to find book titles?
I still have to join the books table.
So let's try that here.
I'll come back over and instead of
joining just the authored table,
let me now try to also join--
let me hit Enter--
to also join the books table.
I'll JOIN books ON books dot id equals,
in this case, authored dot book_id.
And to be clear, this line here
means that what I'm trying to do
is now join this book table, which
is over here, with this author table,
aligning it so that their IDs
match up into a single row,
as we see here with 74 and
74, 1 and 1, and so on.
I'll come back.
And now let me try this.
Come back over here.
And I'll just try hitting Enter to
see what I can see from this query.
Let me zoom out a little
bit and you'll see
I actually do have author names next
to book titles all in one table,
just as we thought we would.
So this is useful to me, but what if
I wanted to have this stored as a way
to see my tables?
I want to be able to query this
kind of table I see right here.
Well for that, I could
try to introduce a view.
Now a view starts with
a query, as we just saw.
I wrote a query to select names and
titles from three different tables,
joining them together.
But if I want to save
the results of that query
so I can query them later on, I
could use this syntax here create
a view that has a name that I can give
to it as this query down below here.
So CREATE VIEW given some name
AS the result of this query
gives me a view that is then
saved and part of my schema.
So let's try that here to create a
view by which you can see both author
and book titles side by side.
I'll come back to SQLite here and I'm
already in this brand new terminal.
So I could try to remake this view
and save it now for later usage.
I'll say create a view
and call it longlist,
the same name we gave our
single table back in Week 0.
Now I'll say this view is the
result of this following query AS,
let's say, SELECT name and
title from the authors table--
but not just the author's table--
join, let's say, the authored table--
JOIN authored on authors dot id
equals authored dot author_id.
And then join again our book
table as we saw visually here.
JOIN books ON books dot id
equals authored dot book_id.
Now that is the query I used before to
see author names and book titles side
by side.
If I create this as a view--
hitting semicolon and Enter--
nothing quite happens.
But now if I type .schema and hit Enter,
I should see a view called longlist
that has two columns, name and title,
and actually see the query I use
to create this view.
So let me think now.
I want to see what's inside this view.
And to query a view I can use
it exactly as I would a table.
I could say SELECT star FROM
longlist semicolon hit Enter,
and now I should see author names
and book titles side by side.
So if I have this kind of table with
authors and book title side by side,
what then does my query become to
find the books written by Fernanda?
Let me ask our audience here.
What query could I use now on this view
to find the books written by Fernanda?
AUDIENCE: Thank you, Mr. [INAUDIBLE].
We can query the book or all of
the books using her specific name.
CARTER ZENKE: A good idea.
I can use a particular name in this case
and perhaps just use a simple WHERE.
So let's try that here.
I'll go back to my terminal.
And if I want to find the
books written by Fernanda,
well, I could just query for
them in this single table
that I created called longlist-- or
not really a table but now a view.
I'll say, in this case,
SELECT the title from--
SELECT title from longlist WHERE--
to Muhammad's point--
I could just say name equals
Fernanda Melchor semicolon.
I'll hit Enter here and
I see those same books
Fernanda has written Paradais
and Hurricane Season.
So let's see where we started here.
We started with this kind of query--
long, multiple lines, many
subqueries involved-- just
to find the answer to which
books Fernanda had written.
Now, though, that we have a new
view, I can simplify this query
to just this here--
SELECT title FROM longlist
WHERE the name equals Fernanda.
And I can do all of this without
using much, if any, more disk space.
A view, remember, is a
virtual table, not a real one.
And I can then have the result
organized like this while still
being in those underlying tables
stored essentially elsewhere.
So let me ask then--
what questions we have on how
views can simplify our data?
AUDIENCE: Can we then somehow manipulate
the views to maybe order the results
or display them just differently?
CARTER ZENKE: A great idea.
So if I wanted to maybe
order these books,
I could absolutely do that in the
same way I would do in a table.
So let me go back and
show you how to do that.
Let's say I want to organize these
books alphabetically by title.
So if you remember, using our regular
old table, we could use ORDER BY.
I could do the same thing here.
I could say SELECT both the name and
title columns from my longlist table.
And now let me try to ORDER BY
the title column in this case
and I'll hit semicolon.
Now, if I hit Enter, I should see the
book titles organized alphabetically.
Now, the view itself does
not have these titles
automatically alphabetically sorted
for me, but I could make it do that.
If I had, when I was making this view
included ORDER BY, let's say, title
at the end of that query, I would then
have those titles saved in this view
automatically as A to
Z. So very powerful
if you want to not just find
particular ways of seeing your data
but also organizing
it or ordering it too.
So with that note, we've seen how
to simplify one example of having
multiple tables down into one.
We'll come back in just a few and
see what we can aggregate data too,
putting that data into
a single table for us
to see some statistics and such as well.
Come back in a few.
And we're back.
So we just saw how to simplify some
data, how to take multiple tables
and see them as one.
What we'll do now is think
about how we can aggregate
data, that is to take many
individual data points
and summarize them to find an
average, or a min, or a max,
but see those results inside of a view.
So if you remember in our longlist
database, we had a table of ratings.
And in this case, books had individual
ratings from individual people,
like maybe I gave book_id
1 a four out of five stars,
but David gave it only a three.
Now, we store these individual
ratings in our database,
but ultimately I don't care
so much what I rated it,
or maybe what David rated it, I care
about the average rating, let's say,
for each book.
But if we care about those
averages, why then would
we store all the individual ratings?
Let's think of this as
a design question here.
Can you think of a reason
we might want to actually
have these individual ratings
stored in our database?
What does that give us
at the end of the day?
AUDIENCE: Perhaps reliability, to
know how many persons rated the book.
CARTER ZENKE: Nice.
So it's nice to have some more data.
I could know how, let's say, I rated
a book or how you rated a book.
That's good here too.
And I would argue that from
having this additional data,
we could compute more statistics.
I could find not just the
average rating but also
the minimum rating, or the maximum
rating, or the median rating,
and so on.
So these individual results
allow us to find and compute
more statistics, like
averages, mins, and maxes,
as opposed to just storing the average.
Now, if I wanted to find the average
of these results, what could I do?
We saw before--
I could try to group ratings
buy individual book IDs.
Let's say I want to find the
ratings for book_id 1 and book_id 2.
I could group by the book ID column,
turning these into individual groups.
And let's say I want to find the
average here using a SQL query.
I could say find me the
average of the rating column
when I have groups by book ID.
That effectively takes my
table like this and says,
OK, I'll combine all the ratings
for each individual book ID
and find for you the average.
I'll first compress this data
together, literally putting it one on
top the other here, and then find
the average of all those results--
let's say, 3.67 book
1 and 2.5 for book 2--
compressing all of our
data into a single result--
in this case, the average.
So let's walk through then how we
found the average using a SQL query
and then we'll turn that into a view.
So I'll come back over here to that
computer and I'll open up longlist.db.
I'll already here, so I can type .schema
ratings to see the schema for this
ratings table.
And you'll see it does have a book_id
column and a rating column as well.
So if I want to find the average
rating for each individual book ID,
what could I do?
I could try to SELECT the book_id
column and the rating column like this.
But I don't want to select
just the rating column itself
that gives me individual values.
I want to find the
average rating instead.
I could instead say find me the
average rating from this table.
Now let me give this a new name.
I'll say AS rating, calling the average
rating now newly, in this case, rating.
And I'll select this
FROM the ratings table.
And finally I need to
GROUP BY something.
I need to GROUP BY book_id.
That means I'll calculate the
average rating for each book ID.
I'll hit semicolon here and Enter and
I should see all of these book IDs,
top to bottom, with their own rating.
But here it doesn't look so pretty.
What could I do to try to make this
not so long, like 3.774019431--
there's a better way to do
this and we saw it before.
What could I do to enhance
this view of my ratings table?
AUDIENCE: I see some suggestions
about rounding the ratings.
But I was also going to suggest
adding the book titles, of course.
CARTER ZENKE: Ah, good point here too.
So we first want to add the-- first
we want to probably add the book title
to see what titles are talking
about-- not just, in this case,
individual book IDs--
but also a good point to
say let's try rounding these
so we don't see 3.7740194.
Let's try to round that maybe to
two decimal places just to be safe.
So let's first try
rounding this and then
we'll try adding in some book
titles to your suggestion here.
I'll come back over and let
me just try rounding it first.
So I will come back to
my terminal and I'll
say I want to find the average
rating for each book_id.
And I want to select, not
just the average rating
as we did before, but the
rounded average rating.
So I can use ROUND and say
take the average rating
and round it to two decimal places.
And I'll call this column just
rating in the final result.
And I'll select this
from the ratings table.
And now I can group by, in
this case, book_id Enter.
I should see I have rounded ratings
now, a little more pretty than before.
Now, to your point, let's try to add in
not just book IDs but also book titles.
What does it mean for a
book ID to have some rating?
I want to see titles here in the end.
So let's do that.
I'll say SELECT book_id,
and also SELECT title,
and maybe even select the year that
book was nominated for the Booker Prize.
I'll then select the rounded average
rating to two decimal places as rating.
And I want to select this from
the ratings table, from ratings.
But what do you notice?
If I were to select just from
ratings, what data am I missing
and where could I find it?
AUDIENCE: Hey, you're missing
the titles from the books table.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
I have to have titles
and those are stored in the books table.
So what should we do?
Probably just join in the books
table matching up that primary key
with some foreign keys.
So I'll come back over
here and we'll do that.
I want to select from
ratings, of course,
but I also want to join, in
this case, the book table.
So I'll hit Enter and now I'll
say JOIN as well the books table.
Now, how can I match up the books
table with the rating table?
Well, I know that the rating table
has a foreign key called book_id.
And the book table has
a primary key called id.
So I'll tell SQL I want to match
these two up a bit like this.
I'll say JOIN books ON
ratings dot book_id--
that foreign key that's
inside of ratings--
equals, in this case, books dot id.
Now, there's one more step, which
is to group by book_id still.
So I'll hit Enter and GROUP BY book_id.
But now I should be able
to hit semicolon and Enter
and I should see, not just book IDs,
but now titles and the years those books
were nominated as well.
So this view is getting
better and better.
And I might say we can actually go
ahead and just add this to our schema.
We could create a view that returns
to us the results of this query.
So let's try that.
I'll say, create a view called maybe
average book ratings, average book
ratings for people to come in and
do analysis on if they'd like.
Then I could say, I want to create this
view as that query we wrote before.
So I'll say, again, select
the book_id, the title,
and let's say the year column,
the rounded average rating
to two decimal places.
And then I want to select as rating.
I'll select this from the
ratings table, from ratings.
And then I'll join, as we did
before, the book table from ratings
and then join books on that
primary key and not foreign key.
So I'll say on ratings.book_id
that foreign key in ratings,
and set that equal to books.id, that
primary key we're going to use to join
these tables together.
Then I'll say group by book_id.
And I should have if I hit Enter my
very own view called average book
ratings that I can use to then see
the averages for each of these books.
I'll say select-- let's say star--
from average_book_ratings semicolon.
And now I should see all of those
results just as we had before.
Now notably, because
this is in a view, I'm
not using much, if any,
additional space in my database.
I still have underlying this
view individual ratings.
But because I saved this query and
the results it created in a view,
I can actually have access to
the rounded average ratings
for each of these.
And I can query that view as well.
So let me ask then what questions
we have on how we've used views
to aggregate some data so far?
AUDIENCE: Actually, I have a question.
Can we use both the same name,
like before it was long list.
And here we're using
for average something.
Can use long list for both of them?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so if you
remember before we had this view
called long list.
And long list had book titles
and authors inside of it.
And I think you're asking,
could we try to join, let's say,
the long list table with our ratings
to get book titles and so on?
We couldn't do that because we don't
have the ID column in that long list
view.
We could though perhaps
write some queries that
involve that long list view as well.
OK, let's keep going here and
seeing what advantages this view
might give us.
So I'll come back over here.
And one more advantage is that if
I were to add in some new rating
to my ratings column, I
could just requery this view
to find the updated average.
So let's say we use some
INSERT INTO statement here
and I update some books ratings.
Well, if I'm a data analyst and
I come back in a little later
and I want to find the updated
rating, I can do it just again,
by selecting from, selecting star,
from average book ratings like this,
average book ratings.
Hit Enter.
And now I see perhaps some
updated averages as well.
Every time I query this view, I'll rerun
essentially that query from before.
And now I'll see the updated
averages for each book.
Now, sometimes as a data analyst,
I might want to create a view
but not store it long
term as part of my schema.
Like here if I type dot schema,
I see both our prior view
called long list right here.
And I also see our
average book ratings view.
But if I am somebody
who comes in and I maybe
want to find the average book ratings
not by each book, but by each year,
I could do that, but then not
store that view long term.
Maybe I don't want
others to see this view.
Or maybe it's just from my own
analysis on this given day.
Well, to do that, I could
move beyond just create view.
And I could also enhance this to
be create temporary view, where
a temporary view exists
only for the duration
of my connection with the database.
So to be clear, that means if I
type SQLite three long list dot DB,
I'm opening a connection
to the database.
If I then type dot quit, I
would then lose that connection,
quit that connection.
And that view would no longer be there.
So let's try this.
I'll come back to my terminal.
And we'll create a
temporary view that shows
us the average ratings for the books
by the year they were nominated,
not by every individual book here.
So I could try doing the
same query from before,
like select, let's say, the
average rating select it
from the ratings table, join
books, and titles, and so on.
But what do I have already
to build on top of?
If I wanted to find a view that
has a title, a rating, and even
let's say the year that
book was published,
what do I already have
in my schema for that?
AUDIENCE: So we could use the
view that we just created?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, a nice idea.
So we could actually use the
same view we just created
to create ourselves a brand new view.
So just because something
is a view doesn't mean
we can't use it to then
create another view as well.
So we'll do exactly that.
We'll come back over here.
And I can type dot schema
to see I still have
this view called average book ratings.
And in it I have book IDs, their
title, the year they were nominated,
and their average rating.
But now I want to find,
let's say, the average rating
for each individual year,
not for each individual book.
So what could I do?
I could say select the year column
and the rounded average rating,
in this case, from the rating
column in average_book_ratings.
And I'll wrap this query here.
Let me zoom out, so you
can see it all on one line.
Now, I'll say I want to
group by the year column.
So here I'm now saying,
find me the average rating
of each book, of each book's average
rating, for each individual year.
I'll hit Enter.
And we should see, if I zoom
back in, for 2018 we have 3.75.
For 2019, we have 3.64.
So this means that apparently
in 2023, the average rating
for books that were longlisted
for the international Booker Prize
was 3.78, and same for 2022, 3.87.
2021 was 3.69.
So I have this new view here.
I could store this
temporarily inside of a view
that I could use while I'm doing
some analysis on this given day.
So I'll say create a temporary view.
And I'll call this one
average ratings by year.
How were the books rated each
individual year on average?
And I'll say this is the
query that I just did before.
Select, in this case, the year
and the rounded average rating
to two decimal places, as the rating
column from average book ratings,
that same view from before.
Now, I'm creating a view from my view.
I'll group by here, group by year.
And then I'll hit Enter.
And I should see nothing popping up.
But now if I wanted
to query this view, I
could say select star from
average ratings by year.
And I'll see the results of that view.
Now, though, here's the
catch and why it's temporary.
If I were to type dot quit now,
dot quit, and try it again,
SQLite 3 long list dot DB.
Let me retype that.
If I now try to select star from
average ratings by year semicolon,
I'll get no such table
and really no such view.
I don't have a view called
average ratings by year
anymore because this was temporary.
So let me ask, what questions do we
have on temporary tables, if any?
Temporary views rather.
AUDIENCE: Right, so thank you.
So the first thing that
I notice is that it just
helps us to do some kind of testing
when we use temporary views.
Basically, the views will
not be saved in the database.
But again, it's just a good way just
to test the query, whether it is usable
or not.
CARTER ZENKE: That's a
great use case for them.
And in general, if you
are working on a database
and you want to organize
the data in some way,
but you don't want to store
that organization long term,
a temporary view is great for that.
If though, you are a
developer and you want
to ingrain this view as
part of your database,
you might just use create
view, plain and simple,
to have it always be in your database
for you wherever you connect to it
and whenever you connect to it.
Great question.
OK, let's keep going.
And let's introduce now something called
a common table expression, or a CTE.
And a common table
expression is simply a view
that exists for the
duration of a single query.
So a regular view, as we saw
before, exists forever in my schema.
A temporary view exists
for a single connection.
But a CTE exists for a single query.
And the syntax looks
just a bit different.
With a CTE I can write a single query,
but at the beginning of that query,
define the CTE, the
Common Table Expression.
To do so, I would say with and
give it some name, as and then
inside these parentheses say the
query I want to be this CTE here.
I could then optionally follow it up
with more CTEs for this same query.
Or I could omit the comma, and then
use just select from the name of a CTE
up above.
This is useful if you want to have
some very temporary view that you don't
want to store in your schema, but you do
want to use for this particular query.
So let's see an example now recreating
our average ratings by year,
but now using a CTE.
So I'll come back to my computer.
And I'm already in my SQLite terminal.
What I should do, though, is
try to drop the prior view.
I want to remove that
view called average book
ratings to create room to have now
a CTE with that very same name.
So I'll say, drop view and the
name of the view I want to drop,
average book ratings, average
book ratings, semicolon.
And now I should see that view
is no longer in my schema.
So I want to recreate
though what we did before,
which was finding the average
ratings of books year over year.
So let me try to write this query.
But it would be handy if
in that query I had access
to a view that gave me the
average rating for each book.
So I'll write the query like this.
I'll use a CTE.
And I'll say, with average book
ratings, average book ratings,
as now this query I'll write now inside.
And this query should be familiar.
It's the same query we use to find
the average rating for each book.
I'll say here, I want to select the book
ID column, the title column, the year
column, and the rounded average
rating to two decimal places,
calling it rating, in this case
from my ratings table, like this.
Now, what do I need to do?
I also need to, as you saw
before, join in my books table.
Join books on the primary
and foreign keys aligning.
So I'll say the book ID column, that
foreign key in the ratings table,
should equal books dot ID, that
primary key column in books.
Then I will group by the book ID to
find the average rating for each book.
And now, let me close out this CTE.
I'll close my parentheses.
And because I'm only using
one CTE, I don't need a comma.
I can then just write
the rest of my query.
I'll hit Enter for style sake.
And now with this CTE
called average book ratings,
I want to find the average
rating year over year
grouping not by book, but by year.
So I'll say select, in
this case, year, and then
select the rounded average rating still
to two decimal places as a new rating
column.
Then I'll select this
from, in this case, my CTE.
So I'll hit Enter here as well
from average book ratings,
that same CTE I defined
earlier in my query.
Now finally, to find the average
rating across individual years,
I'll say group by year semicolon.
And now hopefully, if I hit Enter,
I should see the average rating
for each year in my database.
OK, so this CTE is useful when you have
subqueries you don't want to repeat
or when you want to
make a view that only
exists for the duration of a query.
And it's with all of these tools,
like views, temporary views, and CTEs
that we can get away with storing
statistics about some data in our data
set and not storing them
in the actual database,
but only inside this
view we might have here.
What we'll do next is
see how we can use views
to create not just these aggregations,
but also partitions of our data.
A way to split our data up into logical
pieces for use for our own sake or even
for application sake as well.
We'll come back In just a few.
And we're back.
So we've seen so far how to use views
to simplify and also aggregate our data.
What we'll see now though, is how
to use views to partition our data.
That is to break it into smaller
pieces that will be useful
to us or to some application.
Now, on the International
Booker Prize website,
they have a page for each
year of longlisted books.
But in our table, we have all the books
together, regardless of their year.
Well, maybe it will be useful
in the application, even for me
personally, to have a table
one for each year of books that
have been nominated for this prize.
But before I create
that view, I should ask,
how do I try to find the
books nominated in 2023?
If my table looks like this, I
have a table of books with ID,
title, and year columns,
what query could
I use to find only those
books nominated in 2023?
AUDIENCE: Use the WHERE
clause with the year?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I
could use the WHERE clause
and try to search for a given year.
Like I could try to say, where,
in this case, the year is 2023
or equal to 2023.
And that would give
me back these two rows
if only two books were
nominated in 2023.
In reality it's 13.
If I wanted to find the next
ones from 2022, what could I do?
I could just change the WHERE clause
to say where year equals 2022.
And then same thing for 2021.
I could say where year equals 2021.
Now, each of these
segments of my data is
what we'll call a partition,
a certain breaking down
of my data into smaller pieces,
in this case, organized by year.
So let's now create smaller
tables, one for each year that
might be in our data set here.
I'll come back to my terminal.
And let's think about writing
this query from before.
So if I wanted to find the books
that were nominated in 2022,
I could say select the ID column and
the title column from my books table.
And then I want to find only those
books, where the year equals 2022, then
semicolon, and then Enter.
And I should see only those books
that were nominated in 2022.
But now, I want to create
a view that might actually
store the results of this
query more long term.
I could say create view
and call this, let's
say, 2022 as now same query from before,
select ID and title from my books
table, in this case where the
year equals 2022 semicolon.
Now, if I ever want to find only
those books nominated in 2022,
I could now use my view.
I could say select star from 2022
quote and then semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I should see
those very same books.
So what could I do now?
Maybe I want those
books from 2021 as well.
Let me ask the audience,
what could you do
to create the view for the books in
2021 based on what we've just seen now?
AUDIENCE: We could just change
the year from 2022 to 2021.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah,
just change the year.
And what would you propose
we call this new view?
if you had to take the reins on naming
this view, what would you name it?
AUDIENCE: Books that
were written in 2021.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, we could call it
books that were nominated in 2021.
But I would argue that might
be a bit of a long view title.
So let's shorten just a little bit.
And maybe in keeping with our current
naming, we'll say 2021 instead.
So I'll come back over here.
And let's try this.
I'll say create a view.
And we could, by all
accounts and purposes,
we could say books nominated in 2021.
And that's totally OK.
But if I were to pass this view on to a
new programmer, a new database analyst,
well, I kind of want to shorten it
for them, make it more simple for them
to read.
So I could just call this 2021.
Of course, this title
is kind of ambiguous.
Like if I pass you a view called
2021, are you automatically going
to know what's inside that view?
Probably not.
So it's actually a balance
between how descriptive
you want to be with your names here.
We'll stick though with 2021
to our earlier example here.
Now I'll say create view 2021
as select ID, title from books.
And to Fabian's point, I'll say where
the year equals 2021 semicolon Enter.
And now I could say, select
star from 2021 semicolon.
So this is a good way to break apart
a large table into logical pieces.
It's useful for both you as a
programmer and also for applications
that might only need to access
some subset of your data,
where some condition is true.
So based on what we've
seen so far, what questions
do we have on partitioning
data with views?
AUDIENCE: We have created
two views for 2021 and 2022.
Rather than creating two views, is
it possible to simplify it as one
and then use it rather like where
you simply change that alone?
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I mean,
it's a trade off here.
So you could imagine
trying to do, let's say,
a single view that maybe has
just titles and just years in it.
But then you'd have to
rewrite the query later on
to find only those books
for a certain year.
Here, what we're trying to do is
just like break up this big table
into smaller pieces.
And you can imagine
it's being particularly
useful if you had not just
78 books, but even like
thousands, or tens of
thousands, or millions of books.
It could be useful to have a view for
each logical segment of those 10,000
or more books.
Let's take one more question here.
AUDIENCE: I would like to ask
about updating the view itself.
If I update a single table,
any element in each table,
their view can be updated automatically?
Or maybe it [INAUDIBLE].
CARTER ZENKE: OK, a good
forward-thinking question here.
You can, you're right, update a table.
You can say update the table and
set some column to some value.
What you can't do
actually is update a view.
And that's because a view doesn't
have any underlying-- actually,
it doesn't have any data
inside of it exactly.
It only pulls data
from underlying tables.
So let me show you how I
could update this view,
or at least try to update this view.
I'll come back to my computer.
And let's say we wanted to
change a book in the 2021 view.
I could say select star
from 2021 semicolon.
And maybe it turns out
there's a typo in here.
So instead of a minor
detail, it's called something
like the minor detail,
this book on ID 34 here.
I could try to update this view.
I could say, update
2021 and set the title
equal to the minor detail, where
the title currently is minor detail,
like this, minor detail.
Then I'll hit semicolon.
And if I do this, I get this error,
cannot modify 2021 because it is
a view.
Now, why can't we modify a view?
Well, recall that a view
is simply the combination
of data from underlying tables.
I've assembled data from
different pieces of my database
and put them into a single view.
But I can't then update
that data because that data
is located in multiple individual
tables around my database.
What I should instead
do is try to update
the underlying table, which I can
do as we saw before with just update
and set to.
So more on how we can update,
or at least try to update,
views a little bit later.
We'll take a break and
come back to talk about how
we can secure data using views as well.
And we're back.
So one more use case for
views is being able to secure
the data that's in your database.
You might imagine having a table.
But some columns in that table you
don't want to share with somebody else.
Well, a common practice in
security is to only give someone
the information they need to know.
With views you could
do that very principle.
You could accomplish
that by taking a table
and reducing the number of
columns somebody else might see.
So let's consider here
some rideshare company.
And rideshare companies keep track
of a lot of information about us.
They keep track of where we're
going, where we're coming from,
who's in the car with us, and who
drove us there even sometimes.
Let's say that a rideshare
company has a table called rides.
And inside this table is
the origin of several rides
and the destination along with
the rider who took that ride.
Now, if I were to ask
you here, let's say,
I want to give this data
to an analyst to figure out
which rides are most popular or
which rides are highly rated.
What data should I probably omit?
If I wanted to share this
data with somebody else,
what should I remove from this table?
AUDIENCE: The data you could
remove would be the rider.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, good point.
So if I look at this table and
I think of what information
is personally identifiable, PII,
Personally Identifiable Information,
it seems like this rider column could
identify somebody who took a ride from,
let's say, Good Egg Galaxy
to Honeyhive Galaxy,
and we don't want to
leak that information
if I gave this to some analyst.
Well, with a view I could
keep this underlying table.
But I could create a view that only
has the origin and the destination,
that omits the rider column.
And I could more confidently share
this view with an analyst, not
the underlying table.
So let me try to implement
this view, so we can see it
in action inside this database here.
I'll come back to my computer.
And in this case, I have a new database.
I have one called rideshare dot DB.
I'll type SQLite 3 rideshare
dot DB to open up this database.
And if I type dot schema to
see the schema of the database,
I should see I have
one table called rides,
where each ride has an ID, an
origin, a destination, and a rider.
Now, I'll select star from the
rides table, select star from rides,
hit semicolon.
And I should see the very same
data we just saw in our slides,
where Peach is going
from Good Egg Galaxy
to Honeyhive Galaxy, Mario going from
Castle Courtyard to Cascade Kingdom,
and so on.
So now, I know I don't want to
share this data with somebody else.
What could I do?
Instead of selecting
everything, I could try
to omit this rider column
to the point before.
So let's try that.
I'll select just ID, and just origin,
and just destination from rides.
I'll deliberately omit
that rider column.
Now, I'll hit Enter.
And I should see the
origin and destination.
But I actually don't
see the rider column.
So this is a decent view.
But I could probably
improve this even more.
It turns out that in SQLite if I want
to fill a column with some arbitrary
value, I can do that a bit like this.
Why don't I try to select ID and
select origin and destination.
But I also want to let somebody know
that this data has been anonymized.
There is rider information
in the underlying table.
But you don't have access to it.
What I'll do instead is say, let me
make this new column that's filled
with this value anonymous as a string.
I'll say quote unquote "anonymous"
as this column name called rider.
And I'll select all of this
from the rides table semicolon.
Now I have more helpfully indicated
that there is a rider column.
But you deliberately don't have
access to see who those riders are.
So my last step here is probably
to turn this into a view.
I have a good query.
But I want to save it so
I could query it later on.
Well, I could type select or not select.
I could type Create View first.
I'll create a view.
This one just called analysis.
I'll give this to my data analysts here.
Create view analysis.
And then I'll say as let's go with
select ID, origin, and destination,
as well as the anonymous column
as, in this case, the rider.
And I'll select all of this from my
rides table semicolon, hit Enter.
Now, if I type dot schema,
I see my new view analysis.
And if I say select star
from analysis semicolon,
I should see my "anonymized",
quote unquote, this data.
But this is helpful.
I'd argue it's not very
secure, at least in SQLite.
And if you're thinking
adversarially here,
what might you be able to do still?
If I gave you access
to this database, what
could you do to de-anonymize
this data and to see
the data I didn't want you to see?
AUDIENCE: You can just
query the riders table
and find what are the riders
values in the riders column.
CARTER ZENKE: OK, so you're correct
that we can still see the rides table.
Maybe I look at the ID column in the
analysis view and I see those IDs.
I might be able to link those IDs
with the IDs in the rides table.
And nothing's stopping
me at least in SQLite
from saying select star
from the rides table.
So I'll come back over here.
And I'll try that.
I'll say, in this case, select
star from rides, hit semicolon.
And now I see all that ride
information, although I hid it
in this view called analysis.
And this is a downside of SQLite.
In SQLite we can't set access
controls, meaning I either give you
the entire database or nothing at all.
In other DBMSes though, I
could set access controls.
I could give David access
only to the analysis view.
I can give myself access to both the
rides table and the analysis view.
So keep that in mind when
you're working with SQLite.
OK, so we've seen here how to secure
some data using SQLite and using
views in this as well.
Let's come back in just a minute
and see how we could actually
use SQLite and views to
not just secure our data,
but also to work on soft deletions,
which you saw just a bit ago.
And we're back for one
final application of views.
We saw just a few weeks ago how we
can implement soft deletions, that
is not fully deleting
something in our database,
but only marking it as deleted.
And we saw this in the context of
Boston's own Museum of Fine Art.
It's keeping track of items
inside their collection.
So let's say we had this table called
collections full of items in the MFA,
the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston.
Here I have four items currently in
our collections ID one, ID two, three,
and four.
But I also have this deleted column,
which is either 0 or 1, depending on
whether an item has been deleted or not.
So I want to delete, let's say, Farmers
Working at Dawn, this first piece here.
Instead of deleting it
from the table fully,
I could set this deleted column
from a 0 to a 1, just like this.
And now, it's only soft deleted.
I still have the data here.
I still have the title.
But now instead of being
a 0, it's marked as a 1.
Now, this is useful.
But what could I do to only see now
the items that have not been deleted?
If I show you this database,
collections here, the table here,
I have titles and the deleted column.
But if I only want to see those items
that are not deleted, what query could
I use for that?
AUDIENCE: You would
use a WHERE statement.
CARTER ZENKE: I could
use a SELECT statement.
And I could use probably
a WHERE clause as well.
I could say select star
where perhaps deleted
equals 0 because in this
case, when deleted is 0,
we know this item is still
supposed to be in our table.
So here's the query here,
select star from collections
where deleted equals 0.
Now, we can try to convert
this query into a view,
so we could always only see the
items in our current collection,
not those we have marked as deleted.
So I'll come back over here.
And we'll see we have
our collections table.
But we also have now perhaps
a new view of this table
called current collections.
Well, if I set current collections
to be the result of this query,
I should see when I update deleted
to be 1 for some of these items here,
it should be removed from this
current collections table.
So let's try that.
I could take Farmers Working
at Dawn and delete it.
I could see this correspondence between
this row here and this row here.
It's in both our collections
table and current collections.
But if I set deleted
from a 0 to 1, I should
see that item removed from current
collections, thus updating my view
and keeping track of my items that
are not currently in my collection.
So let's come back here and implement
this in terms of our own database.
I'll come back over here.
And I will open up MFA dot DB, that
old database from a few weeks ago.
I'll say SQLite 3 MFA dot DB.
And now if I type dot
schema, I should see
the tables inside of this database,
collections, artists, and created.
We'll focus in particular
on the collections table.
So if I say select
star from collections,
I should see that I have the title,
the accession number, and the date
this piece was acquired by the MFA.
Now, though, if I want
to add a deleted column,
I could do so by using alter table.
I could say, let's
alter table collections
and add a column called deleted.
I'll say this column
has the type integer.
It stores whole numbers.
And the default number is 0 semicolon.
Now, if I say select star
from collections semicolon,
I should see there is this
new deleted column where
all the values are 0 at first.
So if I want to delete something,
I could instead of typing
delete from as we saw before I can
just update this deleted value.
I could say maybe update collections
and set deleted equal to 1
where a certain title is present.
I'll say this that the
title is equal to Farmers--
title equals Farmers
Working at Dawn semicolon.
So now, I've soft deleted this item.
It's still in my table,
at least the title is.
But now I've marked it as being deleted.
It should not be in my ultimate view.
I'll hit Enter here.
And I'll say select
star from collections.
I'll see that in this case, I
still see Farmers Working at Dawn.
But what do I want?
I want a view that only shows me those
items that have not been deleted.
So I'll try this.
I'll say select star from collections
and apply a condition to it,
to our earlier point before.
So I'll say where, in this case,
deleted equals 0 semicolon, hit Enter.
And now I should see only those
items that are not marked as deleted.
But I want to turn this
into a view, which I could.
I could say maybe create a view
called current collections.
And then I'll make this the
following query as select ID,
select title, accession
number, and acquired.
But now I'll actually
omit that deleted column.
I don't want this column to show
up in my current collections.
I only want it to be in
the underlying table.
So I'll select all of these
columns from the collections table.
And then I'll say where deleted
equals 0 to apply this condition
and only get those items that
are not marked as deleted.
Now, I'll hit Enter.
And I should be able to do this,
select star from current collections
semicolon.
And now I'll see only those
items that have not been deleted.
So this seems worthwhile.
I'm now able to view the items that
are currently in my collection.
But a problem remains.
Like if I tried to update
this table and insert
something into it, what might happen?
Let me ask our audience here.
Based on what we saw
before, what would happen
if I tried to insert into this
table here, this view perhaps?
AUDIENCE: I think we cannot update
the view itself, as we saw before.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, we can't
update the view itself.
We can't insert new data.
We can't even delete data.
So let me try first to delete data.
And then we'll see how to insert
some data a little bit later.
I'll come back over to my terminal.
And what I wanted to delete,
Imaginative Landscape,
I could say delete from current
collections where the title equals--
let me make a new line here--
where the title equals
Imaginative Landscape semicolon.
Now, I'll see that same
error we got before when
we tried to update some view.
I can't modify this
because it is a view.
Well, it turns out there is
a way to work around this.
We can't modify the view.
But we can modify the underlying table.
So to do this, we rank from old friends,
in this case, those called triggers.
So if you remember, a
trigger is a way to specify
some SQL statement I want to run
when some other SQL statement is run.
We saw before we could
use before or after
to say run this SQL statement either
before or after some other SQL
statement here.
What we didn't see until now
is this INSTEAD OF trigger.
I can create a trigger that has a name.
And I can run it instead of
some other SQL statement.
So I could say INSTEAD
OF deleting on this view,
let me give you the proper
query to run, in this case.
So instead of deleting on
this view, I will for each row
run this other statement.
I'll say begin.
This is the statement I
want you to run instead.
And in this statement, we could
have something that actually updates
not the view, but the underlying table.
And we then end that query here.
So based on what we know about
our view and the underlying table
called collections, what query should
we put in here to actually delete
something from our table?
Let me ask our audience.
Instead of deleting from our view,
what should we instead do to our table?
AUDIENCE: Yeah, you should
update the deleted column
in the collections table.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, so instead of
deleting from our view, what I really
want to do is update that table.
So let's try to trigger
it to do just that.
I'll come back to my computer here.
And I'll start on this trigger.
To our point, I want to
create a trigger that
runs instead of deleting on this view.
And what I want to instead happen is
an update on the underlying table.
So I'll say create a trigger,
this one called delete.
And then I'll say instead of
delete on current collections, that
is whenever SQL listens and hears a
delete on the current collections view,
I don't want that to happen.
I instead want this other
statement to happen.
I'll say for each row
affected by that delete,
for each row I ask delete
on current collections, run
instead this other statement.
I'll say begin.
Here is that statement.
One, two, three, four
indents for style sake.
And now I'll say I want to update
collections and set deleted equal to 1.
But I don't want to
leave this just as is.
If I say update collections,
set deleted equal to 1,
what's the problem with that
statement, if I end it there?
AUDIENCE: So yeah, it will
update all the columns,
whether it is we want
it to be deleted or not.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, with no condition
it'll update all the columns here.
So I want to apply a condition
to make sure it only affects
the particular row I'm working with.
Well, what uniquely identifies each row?
The ID does.
So let's try using the ID here.
I'll come back.
And I'll say I want to update
collections, set deleted equal to 1
but only when some condition is true.
I'll indent again four times
and say where, in this case,
the ID column is equal to the old ID.
Now, old here is a special keyword
that means the row we just deleted
or that we would have deleted
from current collections.
I want to update that same row with that
same ID in the underlying collections
table.
So I'll put a semicolon here to end.
And then I'll say end this statement.
This is the entire
statement I want to run
after I try to delete all my
current collections table.
Now, I'll hit Enter.
And I'll see nothing changes.
But if I say dot schema, I
should then see down below here,
I have a trigger called delete that
will instead run an update when
I try to delete from this view.
So let's try that.
What I can do now is try again to
delete from current collections.
I'll say delete from
current collections where.
In this case, the title
equals Imaginative Landscape.
Let's say we sold this painting.
It's no longer part of our collection.
Imaginative Landscape semicolon.
And now it actually seems to work.
I get no error here.
So it seems like it went OK.
Well, if I select star
from current collections,
I actually see that it's gone.
But is it really gone?
If I try select star from collections,
not current collections, the underlying
table for current collections
semicolon, what do I see?
That the ID column has been
updated from a 0 now to a 1.
So a good way of trying
to use triggers here
to update our views by instead
modifying the underlying table.
Now, going to be one more issue we
encounter here, which is the following.
Let's say I'm at this
current state in my tables.
I have collections, where Farmers
Working at Dawn is deleted.
It has a 1 right here.
And we thus can't see it
inside of current collections.
Well, let's say I want to not
delete from current collections,
but also add to current collections.
I could try to insert into this view.
But I probably actually won't be
able to do that because it is a view.
Let's think then.
If I wanted to insert into this view,
what should I really do instead?
AUDIENCE: You should add it to the
collections table instead of the view.
CARTER ZENKE: I like that idea.
So I should add this row to the
collections table instead of the view.
But now, here's a bit of a trick.
Let's say I add Farmers Working at Dawn.
We reacquired it.
What should I do in that case, when I'm
adding a painting I previously deleted?
AUDIENCE: So what we could do is
we know that the deleted column--
we can check if the deleted column
is gone and then based on that,
we could update that particular column.
Or if there is no title
in the collections table,
we can just add it, insert it.
CARTER ZENKE: Yeah, I
like your thinking there.
First trying to check, do we have
this item already in our table?
Or do we not?
If we do already have it in
our table, we should just
flip this bit from 1 to a 0.
If we don't though, let's add a
brand new row, as we heard before.
So let's think then.
What could we use to conditionally run
some code on the collections table?
Well, it turns out that you can
use some other aspects of triggers.
In this case, triggers have not just
unconditional use cases, but also
conditional ones too.
So let's try this.
I could try to insert on this view
and then run some code down below.
But to our discussion
a little bit earlier,
I don't want to unconditionally do this.
I want to check, is
this item in my table?
Or is it not already?
So for that, I could use
this keyword called when.
I could say for each row when some
condition is true run this trigger.
And you can imagine having
two triggers to insert
into our view, one that runs when
the item is already in our table.
We could then flip that
bit from a 1 to a 0.
We could also have a different
trigger to actually insert a new item.
In that case, actually
inserting a brand new row
to our underlying collections table.
So let's work on this now to finish
off and polish our collections view.
I'll come back to our terminal here.
And what we'll try to do is
now insert into this table.
I'll create a new trigger, in this
case, called insert when exists.
I'll say create trigger
insert when exists.
So this trigger will run when
an item we're trying to insert
is already in our collections table.
I'll say instead of insert on
the current collections table,
I want this to happen instead.
I'll say for each row.
Now I'll Enter again and say when--
just for style sake-- when new dot
accession number is in my table
already.
I want to find which accession
numbers I already have.
And if you remember, accession
number is a unique ID for the museum.
It's not the ID column
of my table, but a unique
ID to keep track of items in the museum.
So if I've already given this
item an accession number,
I should already see
it in my table already.
So I'll say then Enter,
Enter, Enter for style sake,
select accession number
from collections.
So this subquery tells me what
accession numbers do we already have.
And this condition tells me
is the new row I'm inserting,
does that have the same
accession number or not?
Now, I'll close this subquery.
And I'll continue my trigger.
I'll say begin.
Well, in the case that this item
already exists in my collections table,
I just want to update.
I want to flip that integer
from a 1 back down to a 0.
So I'll say update collections
and set deleted equal to 0.
Now, I want to do this
not on my entire table,
but only where the accession number
is equal to the new accession
number, that is the accession
number I'm inserting here as well.
I'll then end like this.
And now I have my entire trigger.
I'll say instead of inserting into
my view, I want to run this instead.
Check if I've already added this item.
And if I have, change that
deleted column from a 1 to a 0.
Now I'll hit Enter.
And let me hit Enter again.
And let me check.
I needed to have a
semicolon after my where.
So let me try to run this again.
I'll do Control D to restart.
And I'll say SQLite 3.
Let's do MFA dot DB.
And I'll restart this trigger.
So here I'll say create
trigger insert when exists.
We gave the name before.
Then I'll say instead of insert
on current collections, what
I want to do is run this.
I'll say for each row I
insert, check some condition.
When the new accession number
that is the unique ID the museum
has for this item is in my already
available accession numbers.
I'll say select in this case, select
accession number from collections.
And then I'll close the subquery.
Now, I'll say I want to begin
the same way I want to run.
Begin now update, in this
case, my collections table and
set the deleted column
from a 1 back down to a 0.
Update collections and set deleted
equals 0 where, in this case,
the accession number is equal
to the new accession number,
only modifying that particular row.
Now semicolon to close this statement.
And then I'll say end below,
a second semicolon, Enter.
Now if I type dot schema,
I should see my new trigger
to insert into my collections table
when I try to insert into my view.
So let's try this.
I'll say maybe I want to insert
into my current collections.
Well, let me try this.
I'll say select star from collections.
And let's say I want to reinsert,
in this case, Profusion of Flowers.
So I'll say insert into
my current collections.
Actually, reinsert into
current collections.
And I want to insert
Imaginative Landscape.
So I'll say insert into current
collections some set of values along
with some columns.
I'll say the title is Perfusion of
Flowers as Imaginative Landscape
later on, then accession number, then
the date it was acquired, like this.
Now I'll hit Enter and
provide the values.
I'll say the title is
Imaginative Landscape like this.
The accession number is 56.496.
And the acquired date is going
to be null, in this case.
We don't know when we got it.
I'll hit semicolon here and Enter.
So if I select star from collections
now, select star from collections
semicolon, I should see that I
didn't actually insert a new row.
I only flipped that deleted
value from a 1 back down to a 0.
Now, there's certainly more to do here.
I could write a trigger to actually
add a brand new row to this table here.
I could also try to update this data,
change, for example, the acquired
date from null to a date
that we actually do know.
For now though, we leave
all that up to you.
And we'll see you next time.